<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Thoughts on Things</title>
<link>https://mftokic.github.io/</link>
<atom:link href="https://mftokic.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A collection of thoughts on things from the mind of Mike Tokic</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.57</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>December Learnings</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-01-january-learnings/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I love reading books, watching YouTube videos, listening to podcasts, you name it. Anything learning related is my jam. But I recently realized that if I don’t take notes on what I’m learning, I will probably forget everything. Now when I hear something interesting, I write it down in an Apple note for that month. Below are some of the learnings I jotted down in January, summarized by ChatGPT. I hope you find them as interesting as I did.</p>
<section id="work-life-balance-fulfillment" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="work-life-balance-fulfillment">1. Work-Life Balance &amp; Fulfillment</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Fun, not discipline</strong>: Scheduling enjoyable activities each week prevents work from creeping into all free time.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Success definition</strong>: True success is loving both your work and your personal life.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Capping success</strong>: Decide how much growth you can handle without losing who you are.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="tradeoffs-decision-making" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tradeoffs-decision-making">2. Tradeoffs &amp; Decision-Making</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>No perfect solutions</strong>: Everything has pros and cons; success lies in choosing the right tradeoff.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Red flags</strong>: If you find yourself thinking “but it’s so much money,” reassess your motives.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Fear of big goals</strong>: While aiming high is less crowded, it can also be used as an excuse if you fail.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="competition-high-performance" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="competition-high-performance">3. Competition &amp; High Performance</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Hidden costs</strong>: Emulating high performers may mean accepting hidden sacrifices.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Consistency</strong>: Deliberate, ongoing practice filters out those who can’t sustain effort.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Focus vs.&nbsp;Obsession</strong>: The lazy lose to the average, the average lose to the focused, the focused lose to the obsessed.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="adaptability-innovation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adaptability-innovation">4. Adaptability &amp; Innovation</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Pivot or perish</strong>: Like Western Digital clinging to telegrams post-telephone, ignoring new tech can be fatal.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Company reinvention</strong>: Nintendo, YouTube, and Slack all started with entirely different products.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="human-needs-motivations" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="human-needs-motivations">5. Human Needs &amp; Motivations</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Beyond basics</strong>: After food and shelter, people want affiliation, status, and freedom from fear.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Status &amp; affiliation</strong>: These drive many personal and social decisions, from kids to career choices.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="simplicity-execution" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="simplicity-execution">6. Simplicity &amp; Execution</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Complexity as an enemy</strong>: Simpler approaches often yield better execution (Tony Robbins).<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Stress from neglect</strong>: Stress arises from ignoring important tasks or problems.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="personal-growth-mindset" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="personal-growth-mindset">7. Personal Growth &amp; Mindset</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Meditation zones</strong>: Mindfulness, Support, Flow, and Awakening each expand consciousness in different ways.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Courage gap</strong>: For most smart people, the missing piece is the bravery to act.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Thinking in writing</strong>: Writing clarifies thoughts and fosters deeper understanding.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="entrepreneurship-career" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="entrepreneurship-career">8. Entrepreneurship &amp; Career</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Keys to success</strong>:
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Courage</strong> to start<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Perseverance</strong> to test multiple approaches<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Skills</strong> to build, sell, and harness luck<br>
</li>
</ol></li>
<li><strong>Building an audience</strong>: Focus on the right followers, share your niche expertise, and aim for ongoing improvement.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>If you don’t choose a goal</strong>: Society will assign you one you might not want.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="health-well-being" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-well-being">9. Health &amp; Well-Being</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Weight control</strong>: Balance palatability with low calorie density.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Dental health</strong>: Poor oral care can raise dementia risk by up to 30%.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Marriage vs.&nbsp;career</strong>: A great marriage and an average job can be happier than a great job but unhappy marriage.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="education-parenting" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="education-parenting">10. Education &amp; Parenting</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Raising a sovereign child</strong>: Freedom over control; allow exploration and independent thought.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Scaffolding</strong>: Provide temporary support or structure until a child (or learner) can handle it on their own.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Beware status games in youth</strong>: Sports can become more about prestige than personal growth.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="angel-investing-business-acumen" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="angel-investing-business-acumen">11. Angel Investing &amp; Business Acumen</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Founder first</strong>: Investors should look at who’s running the startup more than the idea itself.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Pratfall effect</strong>: Revealing small imperfections <strong>after</strong> showing competence makes you more relatable.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="societal-observations-history" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="societal-observations-history">12. Societal Observations &amp; History</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Slowing progress</strong>: Bigger scientific fields often have slower breakthroughs.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Policy &amp; power</strong>: Politicians can stifle innovation (e.g., Facebook’s Libra).<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Odd facts</strong>: 80% of US cash is in $100 bills; 70% of restaurant food is delivered.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="influence-conformity" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="influence-conformity">13. Influence &amp; Conformity</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Preference falsification</strong>: Publicly supporting what you don’t believe privately.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Conformity vs.&nbsp;prestige</strong>: We follow the crowd for safety or follow those with status to elevate ourselves.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="ai-the-future-of-work" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ai-the-future-of-work">14. AI &amp; the Future of Work</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Leadership vs.&nbsp;management</strong>: As AI handles tasks, leadership (direction, strategy) grows more important than micromanagement.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Using AI</strong>: Either harness AI to assist your projects or risk falling behind.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="overarching-wisdom" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="overarching-wisdom">15. Overarching Wisdom</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>“Enough” vs.&nbsp;“more”</strong>: Don’t let the pursuit of endless growth blind you to the beauty of having enough.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Fail fast, learn faster</strong>: The cost of being wrong is often lower than the cost of doing nothing.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Mind as friend</strong>: Wisdom comes from taming your own mind.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-01-january-learnings/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-01-january-learnings/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What Item Would You Bring to a Deserted Island?</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-31-knowledge/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>For the first time in history, the answer to the following questions of “what item would you bring to a deserted island” and “what item would you keep to start civilization over from scratch” is now the same thing. You would bring ChatGPT, or put more generally a large language model (llm) or generative AI model. At its core, these AI models condense the knowledge of the data it was trained on. It can acquire knowledge and know how to apply it, which is the definition of intelligence. This proves that the most important thing in our world is access to knowledge and how to use it, aka intelligence, and AI models are the best container for knowledge. Let’s dive deeper into why ChatGPT is the best item to bring to a deserted island. Before everyone gets their panties in a bunch about needing internet access for ChatGPT, let’s assume it’s an offline model running locally inside an indestructible cube that is powered by a hand crank and solar panels. Ok? Good. Let’s continue.</p>
<p>When you crash on the island, the AI would tell you what you need to do first to survive. Most likely how to build a shelter with the elements you have around you. Teach you how to get fresh water. Show you which mushrooms are poisonous and which make for a tasty treat. It could entertain you with stories. Even act as a friend for companionship in a lonely place. Having a physical tool like a hatchet would be nice, but it’s not going to help administer first aid to you when you accidentally cut yourself while chopping wood.</p>
<p>Imagine trying to bring other forms of knowledge to the island. Maybe a waterproof copy of a survival manual. That would definitely help you survive the first few nights and eventually thrive on the island. But only for your most basic needs. What if you found other people on the island? Maybe a potential partner you want to settle down with and start a family? The survival book is not going to help you deliver a child.</p>
<p>Instead of a survival book you could bring an entire encyclopedia. Either one of those old school physical books, or a print out of everything on Wikipedia. That could help you with a lot of things. But now your problem is knowing where to find the right knowledge to help you with new problems. Does that rash on your arm match with the description of a rare disease in the encyclopedia? Hard to say. You then find another tribe on the island that speaks a different language as you and they seem pretty pissed off. Scrolling through Wikipedia for 30 minutes can’t help you there. So it’s not enough to have the knowledge itself at hand, but easy ways to access exactly what you need, when you need it.</p>
<p>Easy access to knowledge used to be driven by search engines like Google and Bing. They could search through various information for you automatically. In a sense they condensed the entire internet into a text box to ask questions. But what came out on the other side are things that might be able to help, but not the exact knowledge you might need immediately or how to apply it to solve your problem. New AI services like ChatGPT can do just that. It knows most of what a search engine might know, but it can find the right answer immediately. It’s also able to create new information never thought possible, because it wasn’t in the original training data. Google search may not know what to do when a completely new event like a meteorite hits your island. But ChatGPT can reason and give you the knowledge and implementation to deal with the incident. It not only knows what, it also knows how. Knowledge is power. But being able to apply knowledge correctly, aka intelligence, is even more powerful.</p>
<p>The cost of intelligence with AI is quickly going to zero. What happens then? It feels like the two most important jobs going forward in an AI future is either building smarter AI models. Or finding the right data to feed them. By building smarter models you are improving the how (intelligence), and by getting better data you are improving the what (knowledge). The scary part is that AI models can now create their own synthetic training data, and techniques like reinforcement learning allow them to essential train themselves. So manual human intervention in these models might go away too. What’s left to do if the AI can train itself and get better every day?</p>
<p>The answer is to use the AI to make humans better. To increase their knowledge of the what and the how. Imagine a 30 year old accountant who has never camped outside in their life lands on the island with ChatGPT. They would most likely be able to get by with the help of the AI, but they would still struggle initially, maybe even perish from plain bad luck. Now replace that person with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bear_Grylls">Bear Grylles</a>, the famous British survival expert. I mean, the dudes name is literally “Bear”, how could he not survive in the wild? Combine him with ChatGPT and now he turns into a superhuman. He already knows how to survive, and paired with ChatGPT he can now build an island empire.</p>
<p>Having a smart AI is good, but having a smart AI combined with a smart human is even better. As these AI models get smarter, they should also enable humans to get smarter as well. If you want to start learning how to code today, you shouldn’t read a textbook on python. Instead have ChatGPT start teaching you. It’s a world class tutor available 24/7, tailored to your learning style, and is infinitely patient. It can write code for you, explain how it works, and then quiz you about it. <strong>Using AI to increase the collective knowledge and intelligence of every person in the world should be a top priority.</strong></p>
<p>So many problems in our world today can partly be due to a lack of education. When using a college degree as a proxy for education, the problems in our society stick out. People who don’t have a college degree have more problems.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://www.idra.org/resource-center/college-degrees-are-worth-it-people-with-bachelors-degrees-have-lower-poverty-rates/">Poverty</a>: In 2019 people with a college degree earned $25,000 more than someone with only a high school diploma.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.prisonpolicy.org/blog/2018/10/30/education-report/">Crime</a>: Less than 4% of formerly incarcerated people have a college degree.</li>
<li><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28756896/">Suicide</a>: Men without a college degree are twice as likely to die from suicide compared to a college graduate.</li>
</ol>
<p>Having a college degree is not a perfect measure of who has knowledge and who does not. But the above stats paint a bad picture for those without a degree. Soon everyone with an internet connection will have access to the best tutor in the world, essentially for free. AI tutors can teach billions of people at once. The only limiting factors will become tailoring the AI tutor to each persons wants and needs, and a person’s thirst for knowledge. There’s an old saying that goes: “The cure for boredom is curiosity. There is no cure for curiosity.” We can tailor the AI tutors to the learner, but creating the want inside of people to learn is the hard part. In a world of video games and TikTok, getting someone excited to learn about chemistry or to simply read a book will be a challenge.</p>
<p>This is where the multimodal nature of AI models can save the day. The AI can print out text, talk to you via voice, even create photos and videos. This unlocks limitless ways for an AI to teach you something. Someone may prefer a book like experience with an AI using chat, whereas another may learn best through a superhero movie that teaches you about greek mythology. Creating an AI tutor that a person can’t turn away from is one of the most important problems to work on. Imagine your 10 year old staying up all night because they don’t want to stop learning about the migratory patterns of birds, or how nuclear fusion works, instead of watching TikTok dance trends. This is a possible future. AI is up to the task.</p>
<p>AI models are not only positioned to make the world better, they are also well positioned to make humans better. Let’s go build one.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>AI</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <category>school</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-31-knowledge/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-31-knowledge/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploratory Data Analysis: External Regressors</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-24-ts-fundamentals-eda-xregs/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>This post is part of the <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-03-ts-fundamentals-eda/">exploratory data analysis chapter</a> within a larger learning series around time series forecasting fundamentals. <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-25-ts-fundamentals/">Check out the main learning path</a> to see other posts in the series.</em></p>
<p><em>The example monthly data used in this series <a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/posts/2024-10-02-ts-fundamentals-whats-a-time-series/example_ts_data.csv">can be found here.</a> You can also find the <a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/notebooks/2025-01-24-ts-fundamentals-eda-xregs.ipynb">python code used in this post here.</a></em></p>
<section id="may-the-outside-forces-be-with-you" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="may-the-outside-forces-be-with-you">May The Outside Forces Be With You</h3>
<p>When creating a time series forecast, you really only need three columns. One to identify one time series from another, a timestamp (date) column, and your target variable. With these three things you can produce high quality forecasts. Unfortunately most time series do not live in a vacuum, and are subject to outside forces. These forces could be things like macroeconomic factors like inflation or consumer sentiment. The growing market share of your competitors. Or even when your product might go on sale. These are all external regressors (xregs), or outside data points that can be used to improve the predictive accuracy of our time series forecast.</p>
<p>External regressors come in many shapes and sizes. They are usually chosen based on the <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-04-02-time-series-domain-expertise/">domain expertise</a> of whatever you’re trying to forecast. Outside of a hunch that they might work, how can we tell if they should be used in our time series forecast? Let’s walk through a few methods to measure the relationship between external regressors and our target variable.</p>
</section>
<section id="measuring-linear-relationships" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="measuring-linear-relationships">Measuring Linear Relationships</h3>
<p>The most straightforward approach is a simple correlation analysis. We take the external regressor time series, and calculate the correlation against our target variable time series. This gives us a value between -1 and 1. Having either a strong negative correlation or positive correlation are both helpful. Here are a few rules of thumb to measure strong correlations of external regressors based on the date grain of your data.</p>
<ul>
<li>Year/Quarter/Month: Absolute value correlation of 0.5 or higher.</li>
<li>Week/Day: Absolute value correlation of 0.2 or higher.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s important to note that those values are arbitrary. This isn’t a perfect threshold to use. So make sure you adjust that based on your own time series data. Let’s take a time series from our example dataset and calculate the correlation against a few external regressors.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Date</th>
<th>Country</th>
<th>Product</th>
<th>Revenue</th>
<th>xreg1</th>
<th>xreg2</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2019-01-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>12.37</td>
<td>27</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2019-02-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>15.73</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2019-03-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>39.68</td>
<td>67</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2019-04-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>60.17</td>
<td>95</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2019-05-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>72.84</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2019-06-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>53.31</td>
<td>21</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2019-07-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>9.65</td>
<td>31</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2019-08-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>12.20</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2019-09-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>10.04</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2019-10-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>19.62</td>
<td>88</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-24-ts-fundamentals-eda-xregs/chart1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The first external regressor (xreg1) seems to have similar trend and seasonality patterns as our revenue target variable. The second external regressor (xregs2) on the other hand is all over the place. Here is the correlation with each xreg.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Variable 1</th>
<th>Variable 2</th>
<th>Correlation</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1</td>
<td>0.83</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2</td>
<td>0.05</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The table confirms our initial smell test after reading the line chart. Xreg1 has a strong correlation, and xreg2 does not. This tells us that xreg1 could be a good candidate to use as a feature in our ML forecast model. What if we don’t know what xreg1 values are going to be in the future? That’s where calculating correlation on lags becomes valuable. We can calculate lags for 1 month, 2 months, 3 months, and onward to see if lag values of our external regressors can also be used as features.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Variable 1</th>
<th>Variable 2</th>
<th>Correlation</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1</td>
<td>0.83</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2</td>
<td>0.05</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_1</td>
<td>0.64</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_2</td>
<td>0.24</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_3</td>
<td>-0.17</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_6</td>
<td>-0.07</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_9</td>
<td>-0.43</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_12</td>
<td>0.65</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_1</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_2</td>
<td>-0.11</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_3</td>
<td>-0.15</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_6</td>
<td>0.17</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_9</td>
<td>0.04</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_12</td>
<td>0.15</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>In addition to the original xreg1 (at lag 0), the 1 and 12 month lags also have a high correlation. A 12 month lag shows that there is strong seasonality in both our original time series and xreg1. This will be helpful once we start to train models.</p>
</section>
<section id="measuring-non-linear-relationships" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="measuring-non-linear-relationships">Measuring Non-Linear Relationships</h3>
<p>Traditional correlation is great and all, but falls short if there are non-linear relationships between the variables. In order to capture non-linear relationships, we have to bring in some heavy firepower. Using either of the below approaches.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Mutual Information (MI)
<ul>
<li>Overview:
<ul>
<li>Measures the shared information between two variables (or time series).</li>
<li>Captures linear and non-linear dependencies.</li>
<li>Based on information theory: higher MI indicates more shared patterns or dependencies.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Key Points:
<ul>
<li>Values are always non-negative.</li>
<li>MI = 0: No dependence (variables are independent).</li>
<li>Higher MI: Greater dependency or shared information.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Interpretation:
<ul>
<li>MI doesn’t distinguish between positive or negative relationships (unlike correlation).</li>
<li>It only reflects the strength of dependency, not its direction or type.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Distance Correlation (dCor)
<ul>
<li>Overview:
<ul>
<li>Measures the dependence between two variables by analyzing distances between all pairwise points.</li>
<li>Captures both linear and non-linear relationships.</li>
<li>Unlike MI, dCor is normalized to a specific range.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Key Points:
<ul>
<li>Values range from 0 to 1.</li>
<li>dCor = 0: Variables are independent.</li>
<li>dCor = 1: Perfect dependence (linear or non-linear).</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Interpretation:
<ul>
<li>A value closer to 0: Weak or no dependency.</li>
<li>A value closer to 1: Strong dependency.</li>
<li>It is symmetric and doesn’t distinguish between causation or directionality.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>Distance correlation is easier to understand and compare scores across different data sets, but mutual information can understand more complex non-linear relationships. So either can be helpful. Dealers choice on what you want to use. Let’s calculate a mutual information score on our external regressors and their lags.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Variable 1</th>
<th>Variable 2</th>
<th>Mutual Information</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1</td>
<td>0.52</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_1</td>
<td>0.18</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_2</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_3</td>
<td>0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_6</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_9</td>
<td>0.04</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_12</td>
<td>0.05</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_1</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_2</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_3</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_6</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_9</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_12</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Similar to regular correlation, xreg1 shows a strong relationship with revenue. But for MI it only has a relationship with lag 0 and lag 1. All other values are either very small or zero, meaning there is not strong relationship. This differs from the original correlation values. Usually it’s a good idea to use a few of these methods together. If external regressors are flagged as important in more than one of these approaches, then it’s safe to say they have some predictive power for our target variable. So for our data we can keep xreg1 to use in our model and drop xreg2 since it’s mostly noise with no signal.</p>
</section>
<section id="dealing-with-binary-regressors" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dealing-with-binary-regressors">Dealing With Binary Regressors</h3>
<p>There’s one final type of analysis we are missing. Sometimes adding simple binary variables as external regressors can result in major accuracy improvements. These are 1 or 0 values that can represent a certain event or action happening. For example you might have new product launches in random months throughout the year. These can be represented with a 1 when there is a product launch, and a 0 when there is not. Without this binary data, a model may pick up on trends and patterns that may not repeat in the future. Your business might thrive during the months leading up to the US presidential election, but that only comes around every four years. So giving the model context of those events is important.</p>
<p>An interesting binary regressor in recent years has been a COVID-19 flag. This shows when COVID was impacting the world the most. When looking at the chart of our time series above, we can see a large dip in 2020. So it looks like COVID has a potential effect. Let’s create a COVID flag with a value of 1 for every month in 2020 and a value of 0 for all other months. We will also create a second flag that contains random 1 and 0 values to see if we can determine which regressor is important to our specific time series.</p>
<p>We can calculate a mutual information score for each one.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Variable 1</th>
<th>Variable 2</th>
<th>Mutual Information</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>COVID Flag</td>
<td>0.0033</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>Random Flag</td>
<td>0.0000</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>While the mutual information score for COVID is small, it’s still above zero. Which proves that this COVID flag may help improve our models predictive performance.</p>
<p>Finally there are other ways to figure out the importance of external regressors, but most of them deal with training actual models. I’ll wait on discussing those techniques until we build up some more foundational knowledge and eventually get to the sections on models themselves. Stay tuned.</p>
</section>
<section id="reversal" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reversal">Reversal</h3>
<p>When working with external regressors, it’s important to approach correlations and relationships critically. A strong correlation might suggest a connection, but it does not prove causation. This distinction is crucial, as relying on variables without clear logical links to your target can mislead your analysis and undermine your forecast.</p>
<p>Another issue to watch for is multicollinearity. This happens when external regressors are highly correlated with one another. Models can struggle to differentiate the effects of variables that overlap significantly, leading to instability in coefficient estimates and diminished interpretability. To mitigate this, examine the correlations among your regressors before including them. If two variables are redundant, consider removing or transforming one to reduce redundancy.</p>
<p>Ultimately, external regressors should be chosen based on both statistical evidence and domain knowledge. They should have a clear, interpretable relationship with the target variable. Without this foundation, even the most promising-looking variables can introduce unnecessary complexity and noise.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>
<p>Incorporating external regressors into your time series analysis can significantly enhance the accuracy and robustness of your forecasts when done carefully. The methods discussed, including correlation analysis and mutual information, are essential tools for evaluating potential regressors. However, they should always be applied alongside sound reasoning and a thorough understanding of the business.</p>
<p>It’s also worth noting that the relationship between external regressors and your target may not always be straightforward. Non-linear relationships, lags, and interactions with other variables often require additional exploration to capture their full impact. This underscores the importance of iterative experimentation and validation throughout the forecasting process.</p>
<p>As you refine your approach, prioritize quality over quantity. A well-selected set of regressors tailored to the problem at hand will yield better results than an overly broad or poorly vetted selection. The goal is not just to improve the model’s performance but to ensure that the improvements are grounded in meaningful insights.</p>
<p>In time series forecasting, the integration of external regressors bridges the gap between historical patterns and the broader forces shaping the future. By combining statistical rigor with contextual understanding, you can build models that not only predict but also provide actionable insights into the dynamics of your business.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>machine-learning</category>
  <category>time-series</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-24-ts-fundamentals-eda-xregs/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-24-ts-fundamentals-eda-xregs/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>80/20 SaaS: Why AI-Driven Customization Is the Future</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-02-80-20-saas/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="introduction-will-ai-kill-saas" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction-will-ai-kill-saas">Introduction: Will AI Kill SaaS?</h2>
<p>Artificial intelligence (AI) has advanced to a point where one or two developers, working with AI-generated code, can build functional software in a matter of weeks. That prospect has led some to conclude that it spells the end of Software-as-a-Service (SaaS). After all, why rent a platform if you can build a decent alternative in-house—cheaply and on-demand?</p>
<p>However, I believe there’s a more practical way forward. Instead of entirely replacing SaaS with AI-built tools, <strong>SaaS providers should deliver 80% of the core features</strong> and allow customers to <strong>customize the remaining 20%</strong> via AI. This approach maintains the convenience of off-the-shelf software while offering personalized functionality.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-some-believe-ai-will-kill-saas" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-some-believe-ai-will-kill-saas">Why Some Believe AI Will Kill SaaS</h2>
<p>The primary argument for “AI replacing SaaS” goes like this:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lower Development Costs:</strong> With AI writing boilerplate code, you need fewer developers.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Faster Time to Market:</strong> AI can generate basic functionality quickly.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Tailored Features:</strong> Instead of dealing with generic solutions, an in-house AI tool can theoretically be customized to meet specific business needs.</li>
</ul>
<p>On paper, this sounds like a dream come true for businesses. But the reality is more complicated. Building robust, production-grade software, from scratch, requires <strong>significant resources</strong>, including project management, maintenance, and ongoing support. Most companies aren’t equipped (or willing) to handle the long-term overhead that comes with building and hosting complex systems themselves.</p>
</section>
<section id="embracing-the-8020-model" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="embracing-the-8020-model">Embracing the 80/20 Model</h2>
<p>Rather than viewing AI and SaaS as competing forces, I propose a hybrid model. The <strong>80/20 approach</strong> involves:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Core Product (80%)</strong>
<ul>
<li>SaaS providers develop and maintain a set of core features that almost every customer needs. Think user authentication, data storage, basic dashboards, etc. This allows them to keep their development teams lean and focus on rock-solid functionality.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Customer Customization (20%)</strong>
<ul>
<li>Customers then use AI (offered as part of the SaaS platform) to build out the features that are specific to their individual business needs. This might involve specialized workflows, custom dashboards, or niche integrations.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>By dividing responsibilities this way, the SaaS provider avoids bloating its product with endless feature requests. Customers, in turn, get <strong>exactly what they want</strong> without having to pay for an army of developers.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-crm-example" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-crm-example">A CRM Example</h2>
<p>Consider Customer Relationship Management (CRM) software. Giants like Salesforce and Microsoft Dynamics offer thousands of features, but not every company needs each one. Despite the vast customization options, many organizations still find themselves <strong>adapting to the CRM</strong>, not the other way around.</p>
<p>What if a startup CRM provider offers a bare-bones product that covers 80% of what most sales teams require. Things like contact management, basic analytics, and lead tracking, and then <strong>invites customers to build the rest</strong> with AI-driven tools? For instance:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>A sales manager wants automated follow-up emails that adapt to different time zones.<br>
</li>
<li>She types her request into the built-in AI feature: “Generate customized follow-up emails that go out at optimal local times for each lead.”<br>
</li>
<li>The AI creates this functionality on the fly, integrating it seamlessly into the CRM interface.</li>
</ol>
<p>No waiting for lengthy releases, no large development staff. Just a straightforward 80% solution with a customizable 20%.</p>
</section>
<section id="benefits-for-both-sides" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="benefits-for-both-sides">Benefits for Both Sides</h2>
<section id="for-saas-providers" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="for-saas-providers">For SaaS Providers</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lean Development Team:</strong> Focus on a stable core, lowering overhead.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Reduced Feature Creep:</strong> No more chasing every edge case. Let AI and customers handle that final 20%.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>New Revenue Streams:</strong> Providers can charge a flat monthly fee for the core product plus incremental fees for AI-built custom features.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="for-customers" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="for-customers">For Customers</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Faster Customization:</strong> No waiting for your feature request to pass through the SaaS provider’s roadmap.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Lower Costs:</strong> Pay for essential features plus only the custom pieces you really need.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Reduced Risk:</strong> Save time and money by not building entire applications from scratch.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="potential-challenges" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="potential-challenges">Potential Challenges</h2>
<p>Of course, the 80/20 model comes with its own complexities:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Maintenance of Custom Features</strong>
<ul>
<li>AI-generated features could break when the core platform updates. SaaS providers will need robust versioning and testing to ensure stability.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Security &amp; Compliance</strong>
<ul>
<li>As customers add custom modules, the platform must ensure data remains secure and compliant with regulations like GDPR.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Quality Control</strong>
<ul>
<li>Who is responsible when an AI-built feature malfunctions? Customers will demand that providers offer at least minimal support for AI-generated functionality.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Training Data &amp; Privacy</strong>
<ul>
<li>AI systems rely on data to learn. Providers must have clear policies on how user data is used to train and improve models.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="startups-vs.-giants" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="startups-vs.-giants">Startups vs.&nbsp;Giants</h2>
<p>This business model has the potential to disrupt established SaaS giants. Companies like Salesforce and Microsoft <strong>already offer</strong> highly customizable platforms, but they are weighed down by <strong>thousands of existing features</strong>. Re-engineering their entire codebase to an AI-first platform would be like trying to rebuild an airplane in mid-flight.</p>
<p>Enter the <strong>new startups</strong>:<br>
- <strong>Clean Slate:</strong> They can design products from the ground up with an 80/20 approach.<br>
- <strong>Modern Architectures:</strong> They can embed AI customization layers from day one, rather than retrofitting existing systems.<br>
- <strong>Agile Mindset:</strong> Less legacy overhead means they can pivot faster to market demands.</p>
<p>The incumbents won’t disappear overnight, but they may lose out on smaller, more agile customers who prefer a streamlined, customizable experience.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion-thriving-in-an-ai-future" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion-thriving-in-an-ai-future">Conclusion: Thriving in an AI Future</h2>
<p>AI may not spell the end of SaaS, but it <strong>will</strong> transform it. By offloading the final 20% of custom features to AI, SaaS providers can remain lean, stay focused on a reliable core, and still give customers the freedom to adapt software to their unique processes.</p>
<section id="final-thought" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thought">Final Thought</h3>
<p>Are you ready to adapt? If you’re a <strong>SaaS provider</strong>, consider slimming your product down to the essential core and building out an AI-driven customization layer. If you’re a <strong>customer</strong>, think about the time and money you could save by adopting an 80/20 approach, rather than building or buying bloated software.</p>
<p>The future of SaaS will hinge on who best embraces this new reality. Those who see AI not as a rival to existing software, but as an ally in creating truly personal, on-demand solutions.</p>
<p><strong>Which side of the 80/20 equation is your business on?</strong></p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>AI</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-02-80-20-saas/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-02-80-20-saas/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>December Learnings</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-01-december-learnings/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I love reading books, watching YouTube videos, listening to podcasts, you name it. Anything learning related is my jam. But I recently realized that if I don’t take notes on what I’m learning, I will probably forget everything. Now when I hear something interesting, I write it down in an Apple note for that month. Below are some of the learnings I jotted down in December, summarized by ChatGPT. I hope you find them as interesting as I did.</p>
<section id="business-entrepreneurship" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="business-entrepreneurship">1. Business &amp; Entrepreneurship</h3>
<section id="passive-income-productized-services" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="passive-income-productized-services">Passive Income &amp; Productized Services</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Best passive income model:</strong> Offer a service that helps companies make more money.
<ul>
<li>Ideally, “productize” your service so it’s standardized, repeatable, and less reliant on your day-to-day involvement.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="starting-a-company-from-scratch" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="starting-a-company-from-scratch">Starting a Company From Scratch</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Validate demand first:</strong> Ask people if they want what you’re selling; presell if possible.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Find a repeatable way to get customers</strong> (test channels early).<br>
</li>
<li>Build only after talking to potential customers; keep it simple until proven.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Know if you’re building to sell or building to run:</strong>
<ul>
<li>LLC if you want to pay yourself along the way.<br>
</li>
<li>C Corp if you want to sell eventually (consider QSBS after five years).</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="monetization-branding" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monetization-branding">Monetization &amp; Branding</h4>
<ul>
<li>Even in a commodity space, <strong>branding can create a unique edge</strong> (e.g., Liquid Death water).<br>
</li>
<li>“Startups fail, founders don’t”: Persistence leads to eventual success if you keep learning.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="key-mindsets" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-mindsets">Key Mindsets</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>“The fundamental algorithm of life is to repeat what works.”</strong><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Pair your primary metric with a “check” metric</strong> (e.g., revenue + profit margin) to avoid over-optimizing in one direction.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="management-leadership" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="management-leadership">2. Management &amp; Leadership</h3>
<section id="types-of-delegation" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="types-of-delegation">Types of Delegation</h4>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Tell them what to do.</strong><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Allow them to make decisions.</strong>
<ul>
<li>Aim for #2, but you might start with #1 until trust and competence are established.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="avoid-monkeys-on-your-back" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="avoid-monkeys-on-your-back">Avoid “Monkeys on Your Back”</h4>
<ul>
<li>When employees bring a problem, coach them to leave with their own solution.<br>
</li>
<li>Ask guiding questions (“Are you sure we need to do anything right now?”) instead of providing answers.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="one-metric-management-peter-thiels-approach" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="one-metric-management-peter-thiels-approach">One Metric Management (Peter Thiel’s Approach)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Assign each employee exactly <strong>one</strong> main metric or goal.<br>
</li>
<li>That’s all you focus on in 1:1s.<br>
</li>
<li>They own the outputs and figure out the inputs themselves.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="firing-role-clarification" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="firing-role-clarification">Firing &amp; Role Clarification</h4>
<ul>
<li>The moment you think “this might be a firing situation,” have a clarifying conversation about expectations.<br>
</li>
<li>Firing ultimately benefits both parties if the role isn’t a fit.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="hiring-strategy-for-new-business" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hiring-strategy-for-new-business">Hiring Strategy for New Business</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>First hire:</strong> Virtual assistant to free up time (low-risk, low-cost).<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Second hire:</strong> Sales/marketing to boost cash flow, then operations.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Hiring internationally</strong> can be a “no-brainer” for cost savings (e.g., via Shepherd).</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="who-not-how" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="who-not-how">Who, Not How</h4>
<ul>
<li>When a problem arises, ask <strong>“Who can solve this for me?”</strong> instead of <strong>“How will I solve it?”</strong><br>
</li>
<li>This mindset shift helps you move from owning a ‘job’ to owning a ‘business.’</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="productivity-personal-growth" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="productivity-personal-growth">3. Productivity &amp; Personal Growth</h3>
<section id="daily-vitamins-for-health" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="daily-vitamins-for-health">Daily “Vitamins” for Health</h4>
<ul>
<li>Walks/Nature<br>
</li>
<li>45 minutes of exercise<br>
</li>
<li>Reading, YouTube (educational), Writing, Building<br>
</li>
<li>1:1 time with family/friends<br>
</li>
<li>150 grams of protein</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="preventing-burnout" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="preventing-burnout">Preventing Burnout</h4>
<ul>
<li>Ask: <strong>“Is this important? Will it make a difference?”</strong> Only focus on the important.<br>
</li>
<li>Our <strong>state determines our story</strong>—manage your energy and emotions.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="habits-dopamine" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="habits-dopamine">Habits &amp; Dopamine</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Dopamine gained without effort</strong> (e.g., instant gratification) can be dangerous.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Good results</strong> today come from consistent, small choices made previously.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="time-freedom-over-money" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="time-freedom-over-money">Time Freedom Over Money</h4>
<ul>
<li>Many people chase money for freedom but ironically lose freedom by obsessing over it.<br>
</li>
<li>Consider designing a life you enjoy <strong>now</strong>, rather than waiting for a financial milestone.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="health-longevity" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-longevity">4. Health &amp; Longevity</h3>
<section id="key-factors" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-factors">Key Factors</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Excess fat (adipose tissue)</strong> has the largest negative impact.<br>
</li>
<li>Maintain a healthy weight and an 80–90% healthy diet for most of the benefits.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="other-longevity-insights" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="other-longevity-insights">Other Longevity Insights</h4>
<ul>
<li>Developing countries often have lower life spans due to poor indoor air quality.<br>
</li>
<li>As you age, <strong>vacations should be longer</strong> because your body needs more time to relax.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Creativity</strong> correlates with longevity.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="environmental-lifestyle-factors" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="environmental-lifestyle-factors">Environmental &amp; Lifestyle Factors</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Blue light</strong> and <strong>flickering LEDs</strong> can contribute to stress or weight gain.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Posture</strong> affects how much you believe your own thoughts—mind your physical stance.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="mindset-philosophy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mindset-philosophy">5. Mindset &amp; Philosophy</h3>
<section id="q-filters-test-jon-acuff" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="q-filters-test-jon-acuff">3Q Filters Test (Jon Acuff)</h4>
<ol type="1">
<li>Is it <strong>true</strong>?<br>
</li>
<li>Is it <strong>helpful</strong>?<br>
</li>
<li>Is it <strong>kind</strong>?</li>
</ol>
<p>If your thoughts are not one of these, discard it immediately.</p>
</section>
<section id="socratic-method-curiosity" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="socratic-method-curiosity">Socratic Method &amp; Curiosity</h4>
<ul>
<li>Instead of disagreeing, ask questions to uncover someone’s reasoning.<br>
</li>
<li>Serve as a “midwife” to help them birth new ideas rather than forcing your own.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="quotes-wisdom" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="quotes-wisdom">Quotes &amp; Wisdom</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>“Content is about emotion, not information.”</strong> —Shaan Puri<br>
</li>
<li><strong>“Slow is smooth, smooth is fast.”</strong><br>
</li>
<li><strong>“No one is wrong on purpose.”</strong> —Socrates<br>
</li>
<li><strong>“Make a sense of humor your default emotion.”</strong> —Matthew McConaughey<br>
</li>
<li><strong>“If you want to win, only run races where winning is up to you.”</strong> —Epictetus</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="identity-diversification" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="identity-diversification">Identity Diversification</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Don’t let your job (or parenthood) be your sole identity.</strong><br>
</li>
<li>Spread your sense of self across multiple areas for resilience.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="live-verb-focused-not-noun-focused" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="live-verb-focused-not-noun-focused">Live Verb-Focused, Not Noun-Focused</h4>
<ul>
<li>Focus on what you <strong>do</strong>, not the title you hold.<br>
</li>
<li>Prioritize experiences and meaningful actions over static labels.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="relationships-social-insights" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="relationships-social-insights">6. Relationships &amp; Social Insights</h3>
<section id="delegation-autonomy" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="delegation-autonomy">Delegation &amp; Autonomy</h4>
<ul>
<li>Not every employee wants total autonomy; many prefer structure and a clear path to win.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="friendships-connections" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friendships-connections">Friendships &amp; Connections</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>“What is a friend? A single soul dwelling in two bodies.”</strong> —Aristotle<br>
</li>
<li>~200 hours of shared experience can turn an acquaintance into a close friend.<br>
</li>
<li>25% of adults are estranged from a parent; relationships can be complex, so invest in those that matter.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="family-societal-trends" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="family-societal-trends">Family &amp; Societal Trends</h4>
<ul>
<li>People have fewer kids because <strong>expectations</strong> (and costs) for each child have gone up dramatically.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="handling-lows-in-relationships" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="handling-lows-in-relationships">Handling Lows in Relationships</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>“It’s the lows, not the highs, that make or break a relationship.”</strong><br>
</li>
<li>Approach conflicts with empathy, short bursts of feedback, and open communication.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="planning-year-end-reflection" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="planning-year-end-reflection">7. Planning &amp; Year-End Reflection</h3>
<section id="close-out-the-year" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="close-out-the-year">Close Out the Year</h4>
<ul>
<li>Clear old emails, clothes, subscriptions; do a full evaluation.<br>
</li>
<li>Implement a consistent “planning system” to incorporate mini-adventures regularly.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="adding-one-new-winning-habit-per-quarter" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adding-one-new-winning-habit-per-quarter">Adding One New Winning Habit per Quarter</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Incremental habit-building:</strong> small, sustainable changes that compound over time.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="misogi-year-defining-challenge" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="misogi-year-defining-challenge">Misogi (Year-Defining Challenge)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Each year, take on one big challenge or adventure.<br>
</li>
<li>Meanwhile, schedule smaller weekly “mini-adventures” to stay engaged and curious.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="common-threads" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="common-threads">Common Threads</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Empowerment Through Delegation &amp; Systems</strong>
<ul>
<li>From “One Metric Management” to “Who Not How,” there’s a recurring emphasis on freeing yourself from minutiae so you can focus on strategic, high-impact work.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Validation &amp; Focus in Business</strong>
<ul>
<li>Your notes repeatedly stress testing ideas early (e.g., presales), focusing on the one crucial metric or channel, and doubling down on what works.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Healthy Mind &amp; Body for Sustainable Success</strong>
<ul>
<li>Longevity strategies, stress management, and daily rituals (walks, exercise, reading) show a consistent theme of taking care of yourself to thrive over the long term.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Mindset Shifts &amp; Philosophical Anchors</strong>
<ul>
<li>Using the 3Q filter, the Socratic method, and quotes that highlight freedom, creativity, and identity diversification. Emphasizing how perspective, curiosity, and humor make life richer.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Importance of Connection &amp; Relationships</strong>
<ul>
<li>Whether it’s rotating leadership roles, maintaining close friendships, or supporting employees appropriately, relationships and the way you interact with people matter.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Continuous Reinvention &amp; Reflection</strong>
<ul>
<li>The idea of year-end reviews, building new habits quarterly, and tackling “misogi”-level goals underscores the desire for ongoing personal evolution and adaptability.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-01-december-learnings/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-01-december-learnings/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Who Ya Gonna Call? ChatGPT!</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-12-19-who-ya-gonna-call/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>OpenAI has gotten into the holiday spirit by launching <a href="https://openai.com/12-days/">12 Days of OpenAI</a>. Each day at 10am PST they release a new product or feature to the world. We are currently on day 11 of their 12 day ship’mas extravaganza. Previous days have seen massive product launches of their new Sora video model and ChatGPT Search. The most exciting one of them all though has been the product they launched yesterday on day 10, something called 1-800-chatgpt.</p>
<p>You can now, toll free, call ChatGPT on any phone in the United States. For people outside of the US you can talk to it via WhatsApp. How cool is that! No account or credit card required. Just a friend you can phone 24/7 for whatever you need. This may seem like a small gimmicky feature but it’s actually one of their most profound launches to date, because now everyone has easy access to AI.</p>
<p>Nothing is truly mainstream until our parents, and to an extent our grandparents, start using the technology. My grandpa lives on a small farm in Kansas. He has no WiFi at his house, and most days he keeps his cell phone turned off and in a drawer. He does use his landline phone every day though. With this latest launch he can now talk to the most powerful language model in the world, using only his voice. No set up necessary, just call and chat. AI has jumped the walled garden of the internet and is getting embedded into more aspects of our lives. Now it can live as a contact in our phones. The barrier to entry on AI is getting closer to zero.</p>
<p>In addition to having the technically challenged use AI, there are countless other use cases of the new toll free AI number.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Anywhere there is poor cell service. Stranded in the middle of Montana with a flat tire? The ChatGPT app may not work but you might be able to make a phone call. Now the AI can walk you through step by step how to change that flat tire, all for free.</li>
<li>Find yourself in jail for a crime you were wrongly convicted for? The AI can be your one phone call, and might give you better advice than a paid lawyer.</li>
<li>Are you one question away from untold riches on “Who wants to be a millionaire?” Phone your AI friend and have them provide an immediate answer to win the cash prize.</li>
</ol>
<p>The power of AI is now available to everyone. No one knows what will happen when every human has equal access to limitless intelligence. Now we are one step closer. If you’ve never tried out ChatGPT before, get out your phone and make the call!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>AI</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-12-19-who-ya-gonna-call/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-12-19-who-ya-gonna-call/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>ChatGPT Pro is Cheap</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-12-06-chatgpt-pro-is-cheap/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The latest offering from OpenAI costs $200 a month, and it’s actually a steal. It’s called <a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-chatgpt-pro/">ChatGPT Pro</a> and it’s 10x more expensive than their existing paid product called ChatGPT Plus. That sounds like a steep price tag but if you write code or do any complex reasoning for a living it could well be worth it.</p>
<p>Let’s break down the math. The average software engineer in the United States <a href="https://www.indeed.com/career/software-engineer/salaries">get’s paid $105,000 a year</a>. In Seattle and SF that can be 2-3x higher. But let’s just use the average. The new ChatGPT Pro subscription costs around 2% of their annual salary. To be worth it the product needs to give them back the same amount in productivity.</p>
<ul>
<li>$105,000 salary</li>
<li>250 days worked a year (50 weeks of 5 days, 2 weeks for vacation)</li>
<li>$420 daily salary (105000/250)</li>
</ul>
<p>If a dev makes $420 a day writing code, then paying $2,400 a year for ChatGPT Pro equals out to just under 6 days of their salary. The new models offered in ChatGPT Pro are the best in the world at coding. So it’s safe to say using them will make a developer more productive. If using the service saves you one hour a week in time spent coding then it will have already paid for itself.</p>
<ul>
<li>200x12 = $2,400</li>
<li>2,400/420 = 5.7 days</li>
<li>5.7x8 = 46 hours</li>
</ul>
<p>So by using the service you are technically getting 6 more hours of yearly productivity for free, which is about $315. Using the new service is actually putting more money in your pocket.</p>
<p>If you think paying buku bucks for services like this is stupid, well you are just not using them correctly. AI will become the most powerful form of leverage in the world, so not using it to its max today will only hurt you tomorrow. OpenAI said they will also be rolling out more features to the pro service going forward. This could include access to the next generation of models like GPT5 and access to their upcoming agents capabilities. Once these come out you will gladly fork over thousands a month for them, because they will allow you to get 2-3x more done. So paying $200 a month now might just be a steal.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>AI</category>
  <category>work</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-12-06-chatgpt-pro-is-cheap/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-12-06-chatgpt-pro-is-cheap/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>November Learnings</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-12-01-november-learnings/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I love reading books, watching YouTube videos, listening to podcasts, you name it. Anything learning related is my jam. But I recently realized that if I don’t take notes on what I’m learning, I will probably forget everything. Now when I hear something interesting, I write it down in an Apple note for that month. Below are some of the learnings I jotted down in November, summarized by ChatGPT. I hope you find them as interesting as I did.</p>
<section id="personal-growth-and-mindset" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="personal-growth-and-mindset">Personal Growth and Mindset</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Happiness and Presence</strong>: True happiness comes from being present and avoiding overthinking. Expectations play a big role in happiness: reality minus expectations equals happiness.</li>
<li><strong>Action and Results</strong>: Be impatient with actions but patient with results. Start quickly, but allow time for outcomes. Enthusiasm and belief are competitive advantages. Avoid the vicious cycle of inaction fueled by doubt.</li>
<li><strong>Overthinking</strong>: Rumination is the #1 symptom of depression. Action is a better way to change your thoughts than overthinking.</li>
<li><strong>Quotes on Mindset</strong>:
<ul>
<li>“Knowledge is knowing what to do; wisdom is doing it.”</li>
<li>“Cynics get to be right, optimists get to be rich.”</li>
<li>“Ask a better question, get a better answer.”</li>
<li>“At the end of the day you’re going to feel some type of way. So why not feel unbeatable. Why not feel untouchable. Why not feel like the best to ever do it.”</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="productivity-and-decision-making" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="productivity-and-decision-making">Productivity and Decision-Making</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Action Frameworks</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Time between deciding and acting defines success.</li>
<li>Be clear on priorities: what you choose to work on is more important than how hard you work.</li>
<li>Use tools like the Dickens Method to evaluate how today’s actions affect your future.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Worry Management</strong>: Schedule a time to worry instead of letting it linger. Outside of that window, maintain a zero-worry mindset.</li>
<li><strong>Teams and Companies</strong>: Companies should be viewed as sports teams, not families—performance matters. Be clear about whether a role requires a commando (startup mindset), soldier (scaling), or policeman (stability).</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="business-and-sales" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="business-and-sales">Business and Sales</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Product-Market Fit</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Before product-market fit: founders must engage directly with customers in unscalable ways.</li>
<li>After product-market fit: scale with sales staff and established processes.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Sales Approach</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Use the problem-solution-specifics framework. If the customer disagrees about the problem, drop them.</li>
<li>“Reality vs.&nbsp;narrative” moments are key opportunities for emerging tech.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Wealth and Risk</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Wealth is a byproduct of knowledge.</li>
<li>Risk is what remains after considering every possible variable.</li>
<li>“Survive” is the golden rule for emerging technologies.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="society-and-systems" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="society-and-systems">Society and Systems</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Social Observations</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Older industries prioritize regulation capture and splitting spoils over innovation.</li>
<li>Traditions can empower tyranny when unquestioned.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Homelessness and Addiction</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Addiction and trauma are major causes of death for homeless individuals. Programs like Haven for Hope in San Antonio show promise in recovery-based justice systems.</li>
<li>Fentanyl is a growing public health crisis, being 50x more addictive than heroin.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Economic Realities</strong>:
<ul>
<li>78% of Americans live paycheck to paycheck.</li>
<li>The first 15 years of mortgage payments largely benefit banks, not homeowners.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="storytelling-and-communication" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="storytelling-and-communication">Storytelling and Communication</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Power of Stories</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Stories connect human brains like APIs. They involve intention, obstacle, and stakes.</li>
<li>The best podcasters are “vibe architects,” creating environments that feel like casual, engaging conversations.</li>
<li>Great tweets follow principles of truth, novelty, and conciseness while being opinionated.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Music and Stories</strong>: Both resonate emotionally and inspire action.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="practical-knowledge-and-insights" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practical-knowledge-and-insights">Practical Knowledge and Insights</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>General Insights</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Hanlon’s Razor: Never attribute to malice what can be explained by incompetence.</li>
<li>Recruiting agencies charge ~25% of the first-year salary for hires.</li>
<li>Warren Buffet owns more treasury bills than the U.S. government.</li>
<li>Success is a window (external factors), and failure is a mirror (personal responsibility).</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Teaching and Learning</strong>: Computer literacy has untapped potential. Teaching AI-based math instead of manual long division could redefine education.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="miscellaneous-wisdom" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="miscellaneous-wisdom">Miscellaneous Wisdom</h3>
<ul>
<li>“Tradition is the crown of the tyrant.”</li>
<li>“The larger the group, the worse the conversation.”</li>
<li>“Trying to think your way out of overthinking is like sniffing your way out of a cocaine addiction.”</li>
<li>“Life without love is the worst prison of all.”</li>
<li>“Make your life your hobbies, but don’t make your hobbies your job.”</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-12-01-november-learnings/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-12-01-november-learnings/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>DIY Ozempic For 90% Less Cost</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-27-diy-ozempic/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>I’m not a doctor, I don’t play one on TV. This is not health advice. Make your own damn decisions.</em></p>
<p>It’s the day before Thanksgiving. Or as I like to think of it, the day before the month+ holiday eating binge. While it truly is the most wonderful time of the year to eat, it’s not the most healthy. I think everything should be moderation, including moderation. So I like to go nuts myself during this time of year and eat whatever. For most American’s though, going nuts on food for a month straight is not a good idea. Most are obese, and have been that way for decades.</p>
<p>Thankfully new weight loss medicines like Ozempic have risen in popularity over the last few years. These drugs contain a hormone called GLP-1. Which is something your body produces naturally. It’s what makes you feel full after eating a meal. If your body consumes this hormone from Ozempic, it will naturally make you feel full quicker. Which makes you less hungry. Which makes you eat less. Causing you to lose weight. Seems like a miracle drug right! Unfortunately <a href="https://tim.blog/2024/02/02/no-biological-free-lunches/">there are no free lunches</a> in the world of biology. It always comes with a catch. For drugs like Ozempic the catch has to do with it’s price ($1,000 a month) and <a href="https://www.healthline.com/health/drugs/ozempic-side-effects#long-term-side-effects">potential impact on major organs</a> like your thyroid, pancreas, and heart. But if you’re 100 pounds overweight, your organs are already suffering, so taking the drug knowing the tradeoffs is probably worth the risk. Being overweight is bad, mmmk?</p>
<p>The rise in these drugs has definitely caught my attention, so I’ve been studying them closer. They have the potential to not just make people more healthy, but their downstream impacts can be enormous. Planes may not need as much fuel on flights, because people onboard will weigh less. McDonald’s stock might drop 50% because people aren’t impulsively buying milkshakes after work each day. Even gyms could close down, because people can now look good while only taking a pill/shot versus doing 45 min on the stairmaster every day. There will be countless effects. Both good and bad.</p>
<p>What if you could get all of the good effects from Ozempic without having to pay an arm and a leg while also avoiding the harmful side effects? I think I’ve come across a combination that will naturally produce more GLP-1 in your body, while also being 1/10th the price of Ozempic. Here is the stack.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Supergut-Prebiotic-Replacement-Strawberry-servings/dp/B0C645Q2CT/ref=sr_1_4_pp?crid=23XDI3ALKQLWE&amp;dib=eyJ2IjoiMSJ9.ftkuxSBzIaWukfVtnXPvZqBYlET7P_DPpqUuEN5VnUiOlBxfOMzcgkMiL86iJAQ0GeA0vssfvxntIN3Y-jpq2Jr_foimcrO1orPTmc26vPj0zWYqPcTnejj0MwKQICLXWiwlEJSfJtTbo5Q2ENGCwCDK4rtNaAjM9UFz9e_ZJNsryI19XvCxIOYsn05ghGOoAHhr4dXeYIZOebY6ufrQyjSfcTU86deki-ovxQBnhDJTQFcD9aEjuI9cMrhEkIUFg-tKC7DY1nrwm6puUBFgl8nXXy17KZ_zWO8J3keUr8A.RYEHioYWLX2J2QAdYpL0AlnSLvNF7ys-Tw_dT4tW3QA&amp;dib_tag=se&amp;keywords=supergut&amp;qid=1732722580&amp;s=hpc&amp;sprefix=supergut%2Chpc%2C177&amp;sr=1-4">Prebiotic Shakes by Supergut</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0CY3VZDYP?ref=nb_sb_ss_w_as-reorder_k0_1_8&amp;amp=&amp;crid=2T0LC4RNRX9EX&amp;amp=&amp;sprefix=pendulum">GLP-1 Probiotic by Pendulum</a></li>
</ol>
<p>I’ve written about Supergut in a <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-15-hacking-blood-sugar/">previous post</a>. It’s a fiber supplement that contains prebiotic fiber that has been proven to stimulate the release of GLP-1 in your gut. Pendulum is a company specializing in supplements for your gut microbiome. Their GLP-1 probiotic contains living bacteria that creates the precursors to GLP-1. I first learned about Pendulum from <a href="https://www.kevinrose.com/p/a-natural-alternative-to-glp-1-drugs">Kevin Rose</a>, and the science behind it looks legit.</p>
<p>I think the combination of both could be a game changer. The prebiotic fiber from Supergut will help give your microbiome the food it needs to thrive. And the probiotics from Pendulum will help develop the right strains of bacteria in your gut that help produce more GLP-1. This one two punch could be very powerful. I don’t think they’ve been studied in combination before, so this could definitely be some bro science, but my research so far tells me it’s a good combination.</p>
<p>These two products combined cost around $100 a month, compared to $1,000 for Ozempic. So you don’t have much to lose by trying these products. At a minumum your bathroom visits will become 10x more productive and your microbiome will be better off. Why not try it and see how it might help you fight the good fight during this upcoming season of countless food temptations?</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>health</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-27-diy-ozempic/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-27-diy-ozempic/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="145" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploratory Data Analysis: Missing Data and Outliers</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-26-ts-fundamentals-missing-outliers/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>This post is part of the <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-03-ts-fundamentals-eda/">exploratory data analysis chapter</a> within a larger learning series around time series forecasting fundamentals. <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-25-ts-fundamentals/">Check out the main learning path</a> to see other posts in the series.</em></p>
<p><em>The example monthly data used in this series <a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/posts/2024-10-02-ts-fundamentals-whats-a-time-series/example_ts_data.csv">can be found here.</a> You can also find the <a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/notebooks/2024-11-26-ts-fundamentals-missing-outliers.ipynb">python code used in this post here.</a></em></p>
<section id="garbage-in-garbage-out" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="garbage-in-garbage-out">Garbage In, Garbage Out</h3>
<p>Having quality data helps produce quality forecasts. There’s an old saying in the data universe, <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-04-08-time-series-garbage/">garbage in, garbage out</a>. When your data is bad, you will get bad outcomes. The presence of missing data and outliers can reduce forecast accuracy. Which is a shame because they are so easy to fix.</p>
</section>
<section id="missing-data" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="missing-data">Missing Data</h3>
<p>Time series are unique from other types of data because they have a built in order, based on time. For this to work it’s important that each period of time is represented in the data. For example with a monthly data set spanning five years, we want there to be no missing value for any of the month’s during those five years. Having missing values creates challenges when trying to analyze and model the data, since most statistical and machine learning techniques assume all available time periods are present in the data. This leads to reduced forecast accuracy.</p>
<p>There are a few ways data can be missing in a time series.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Missing Completely at Random (MCAR)</strong>
<ul>
<li>Meaning: Data is missing for no specific reason, it’s just random. The missing data doesn’t depend on any pattern or the actual value that’s missing.</li>
<li>Example: A sensor that records the temperature randomly fails to record a value now and then.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Missing at Random (MAR)</strong>
<ul>
<li>Meaning: Data is missing for a reason that depends on other information you already have, but not on the missing values themselves. You can explain the missing data using the rest of the data.</li>
<li>Example: A temperature sensor is more likely to fail during hot weather, but the failure doesn’t depend on the exact temperature value it would have recorded.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Not Missing at Random (NMAR)</strong>
<ul>
<li>Meaning: Data is missing because of the value itself, it’s missing for a reason related to what’s not recorded. The missing data is biased, and you need to understand why it’s missing to deal with it.</li>
<li>Example: A temperature sensor doesn’t record very high temperatures because it shuts down when it overheats.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Mixed Mechanisms</strong>
<ul>
<li>Meaning: Missing data can be a mix of random, explainable, and biased causes.</li>
<li>Example: Some values are randomly missed due to glitches (MCAR), some during maintenance periods (MAR), and others during extreme weather (NMAR).</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>Most data I deal with is some combination of missing completely at random or not missing at random. For example there might be a months worth of revenue data missing in a system due to issues with the company’s enterprise resource planning (ERP) system. So that data is missing completely at random. A system error created the missing data. Another example is having monthly revenue for three products, where two of the products have five full years of revenue data and the other only has the last three years of data. This is due to that third product being newer and only being sold in the last three years. So that data is not missing at random but is due to a specific reason.</p>
<p>For the first two types of missing data (#1 and #2 in the list), it’s a good idea to use some sort of simple statistical model to interpolate what the missing value should be based on actual values on either side of the data. Below is a monthly time series from our example data. I removed a few months at random. We can use a statistical model that breaks down the time series by trend, seasonality, and residual. Then predict what the missing value should be based on the existing trend and seasonal components.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-26-ts-fundamentals-missing-outliers/chart1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-26-ts-fundamentals-missing-outliers/chart2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>For the third type of missing data, it’s usually a good idea to go talk to the owner of that data. Maybe missing data in a system is simply due to that observation having a value of 0, so to save memory they just don’t record that value in the system. The easy fix there is to go in and replace those values with zero. You might have some time series in your dataset that are shorter than others. For example, most of your time series could have five years of monthly data, but one may have only the recent three years of monthly data. To deal with this, you could also replace those missing values with 0. That way each time series is the same length. This becomes important later on when we want to start back testing different models to analyze forecast accuracy.</p>
<p>After you replace the missing data, it’s also a good idea to flag where missing values were originally. This can be done with a simple binary variable added to your dataset. Showing a value of 1 when the original data point was missing, and 0 when it wasn’t. This allows us to give this information to a model, and have it adapt to the changes we made in the data.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Date</th>
<th>Value</th>
<th>Missing</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2023-01-01</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2023-02-01</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2023-03-01</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2023-04-01</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2023-05-01</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2023-06-01</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2023-07-01</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2023-08-01</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2023-09-01</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2023-10-01</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2023-11-01</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2023-12-01</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="outliers" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="outliers">Outliers</h3>
<p>Outliers are values in a time series that depart from the norm. They can be extremely high or low values. Having outliers in your time series can worsen forecast accuracy. A model may try to learn the new changes in trend/seasonality caused by an outlier and carry them forward into the future forecast. We don’t want that. Instead we should identify when outliers occur and do our best at dealing with them.</p>
<p>There are a few ways we can spot outliers.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Smell Test</strong>
<ul>
<li>Use our domain knowledge to point out values that don’t make sense after inspecting the time series on a chart. For example, a temperature of 150°F in Seattle may not be physically possible. It doesn’t pass our smell test, and so we can flag it manually as an outlier.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Statistical Methods</strong>
<ul>
<li>Calculate statistical measures like Z-scores and interquartile ranges (IQR) to spot data points that are outside of standard ranges.</li>
<li>The <strong>Z-score method</strong> identifies outliers by measuring how far a data point is from the mean, in terms of standard deviations, with values typically beyond 3 considered outliers.</li>
<li>The <strong>Interquartile Range (IQR)</strong> is a measure of statistical dispersion and represents the middle 50% of the data. It is calculated as the difference between the third quartile (Q3), which is the value below which 75% of the data lies, and the first quartile (Q1), which is the value below which 25% of the data lies. The IQR method identifies outliers as data points that fall outside Q1−1.5×IQR (too low) or Q3+1.5×IQR (too high). This method works well for skewed or non-normal data because it uses the quartiles, which are less affected by extreme values than the mean or standard deviation.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Residual Methods</strong>
<ul>
<li>Residual methods, such as those used in <strong>STL decomposition</strong> (Seasonal-Trend decomposition using LOESS), identify outliers by isolating the residuals after removing trend and seasonality from a time series. STL splits a time series into three components:
<ol type="a">
<li>Trend: The long-term movement or pattern in the data.</li>
<li>Seasonal: Repeating patterns or cycles at fixed frequencies.</li>
<li>Residual: The remaining random noise or deviations after subtracting the trend and seasonal components.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Outliers are detected in the residuals, which represent the part of the data that cannot be explained by the trend or seasonal patterns. Typically, residuals that fall outside a certain threshold, such as ±3 standard deviations or another robust range, are flagged as outliers. This method is particularly effective for time series data as it accounts for both trend and seasonality, ensuring that outliers are not mistaken for normal patterns.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Machine Learning Methods</strong>
<ul>
<li>Machine learning methods identify outliers by training models to learn the normal patterns in the data and then flagging deviations from these patterns. These methods include:
<ol type="a">
<li><strong>Isolation Forest</strong>: This tree-based algorithm isolates data points by creating random partitions. Outliers are points that require fewer splits to isolate, as they differ significantly from the rest of the data.</li>
<li><strong>Autoencoders</strong>: Neural networks are trained to reconstruct the time series. Data points with high reconstruction errors (i.e., the model struggles to recreate them) are flagged as outliers.</li>
<li><strong>Clustering</strong>: Algorithms like K-Means or DBSCAN group similar data points into clusters. Outliers are points that either belong to sparse or distant clusters or are classified as noise by the algorithm.</li>
<li><strong>Probabilistic Models</strong>: Techniques like Gaussian Mixture Models (GMM) assign probabilities to data points based on how well they fit the learned distribution, flagging low-probability points as outliers.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Machine learning methods are powerful because they can handle non-linear, multi-dimensional, and non-Gaussian patterns, making them highly effective for complex time series. However, they require careful tuning and may need more data than simpler statistical approaches.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>Let’s use the residual method and see if we can spot a few outliers in our time series. First we will <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-06-ts-fundamentals-decomposition/">decompose our time series</a>, then see what residuals are 3 or more standard deviations away from the average.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-26-ts-fundamentals-missing-outliers/chart3.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-26-ts-fundamentals-missing-outliers/chart4.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>There seems to be on major outlier in mid 2020, shown as outside of the dotted upper and lower range. Which is not surprising since our smell test could have told us the same thing. COVID-19 in 2020 was most likely the cause for the sudden change in trend and seasonality for those periods around 2020. We can now confirm it with the residual method for spotting outliers. How cool is that!</p>
<p>Once we know the outliers in our data, there is a few things we can do to handle them.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Do Nothing</strong>: Leave it alone, and let its presence impact our future forecast. This is a good approach if there is a structural change in the time series that you expect to carry onward in the future. For example COVID might have caused a permanent work from home revolution, which could impact your business that relies on growth in office space. So leaving it alone would give the model insight into a change that is expected to continue in the future.</li>
<li><strong>Flag It</strong>: Similar to flagging missing values, we can add a binary variable to our dataset. A value of 1 to indicate an outlier occurred, and a 0 when it did not. This will allow our model to understand true one time events that are not expected to happen again in the future. Making it less likely for a model to learn the change in pattern. COVID-19 was truly a one off thing, so flagging the outliers could be helpful for our time series.</li>
<li><strong>Remove It</strong>: Remove the outlier, and treat it like a missing value. You can then use the methods discussed earlier to fill in the missing value with something that is more in line with future trends and seasonality. Combining this method with adding an outlier flag from #2 is a solid approach.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>
<p>Handling the presence of missing values and outliers can sometimes be more art than science, so always make sure to be adaptable in using the right approach for your use case. When done correctly, cleaning your data of missing values and outliers can help you understand your data while improving forecast accuracy.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>machine-learning</category>
  <category>time-series</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-26-ts-fundamentals-missing-outliers/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-26-ts-fundamentals-missing-outliers/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hacking My Blood Sugar With Fiber</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-15-hacking-blood-sugar/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>For years, I’d heard about continuous glucose monitors (CGMs) , mostly from health enthusiasts on podcasts. These small devices, which attach to your upper arm, measure blood glucose (blood sugar) every five minutes and send the data to your phone via Bluetooth. Originally developed for diabetics who need to monitor their blood glucose throughout the day, CGMs are now becoming popular among non-diabetics as a tool to track metabolic health.</p>
<p>Metabolic health refers to how well your body processes and manages energy from food. Good metabolic health means your body efficiently converts food into energy without putting too much strain on organs like the heart, pancreas, liver, and muscles. People with optimal metabolic health typically have stable blood sugar, good insulin sensitivity, healthy cholesterol levels, and normal blood pressure. Poor metabolic health can increase the risk of conditions like diabetes, heart disease, stroke, and obesity.</p>
<p>Key indicators of metabolic health often include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Blood sugar levels - Balanced glucose levels without spikes or drops.</li>
<li>Blood pressure - Normal range without requiring medication.</li>
<li>Cholesterol and triglycerides - Healthy levels that reduce risk of cardiovascular issues.</li>
<li>Waist circumference - Indicates abdominal fat, linked to higher risk of metabolic disorders.</li>
<li>Insulin sensitivity - Ability to regulate blood sugar without excessive insulin release.</li>
</ul>
<p>Using a CGM to track blood glucose (BG) is a great way to gauge metabolic health. When your BG stays within a healthy range (70-140 mg/dl), your body functions optimally. Repeatedly leaving that range can lead to serious consequences. <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/diabetes/communication-resources/diabetes-statistics.html#:~:text=Diabetes%201%20Diabetes%20About%2038%20million%20people%20have,health%20complications%3A%20...%205%20Common%20Types%20of%20Diabetes">Over 1/3 of Americans</a> have either diabetes or prediabetes, with many unaware of their condition. Heart disease is the <a href="https://www.healthline.com/health/leading-causes-of-death">leading cause of death</a>, accounting for 20% of all deaths in America. These illnesses, with the exception of type 1 diabetes, can be mitigated with good metabolic health, which involves maintaining stable BG throughout the day.</p>
<p>A few months back I purchased a CGM device, <a href="https://www.stelo.com/en-us">made by Dexcom</a>, to start tracking my BG. I did it for a few reasons. A family member of mine has type 1 diabetes, so I wanted to see how my own BG levels look throughout the day. While also test driving to device before recommending it to them. I also wanted to understand how certain foods impact my blood sugar. I’ve heard on podcasts that you’d be surprised what kinds of foods impact your BG. Which is different for everyone. Some foods people thought as healthy, like bananas, might send their BG spiking. Finally, if I could get a better handle on my BG, I could also get better control of my energy throughout the day. When your BG spikes above the normal range, it will eventually come crashing down. Going far lower than the normal range. This spike and fall of BG leads many people to have energy crashes throughout the day. This saps their energy, while also giving them cravings to eat more food. This is a vicious cycle. And one that I wanted to break.</p>
<p>I purchased the CGM from Dexcom and slapped it on my arm. It didn’t hurt to apply and after a few minutes I forgot it was even there. One device lasts for about 15 days so every couple of weeks you have to switch it out for a new one. I now got a stream of data every five minutes alerting me to my BG level. For a data nerd like me it was awesome. I quickly become some sort of mad scientist. Eating things at random and seeing how my BG changed in the next 60 minutes. The findings for my body were very straight forward. If I ate processed junk, my BG would spike. If I ate unprocessed whole food, my BG would stay stable. As long as I didn’t eat processed food, my BG would stay in the healthy range. There is just one problem though, I love junk food.</p>
<p>Everything in moderation, including moderation. Right? I usually try to eat clean +90% of the week. But I am human, and love to pig out every once in a while. I have been known to subscribe to the practice known as “Faturday”. Where for one day of the week I go absolutely nuts and eat everything in site. This kind of <a href="https://www.investopedia.com/articles/investing/013114/barbell-investment-strategy.asp">barbell strategy</a>, either eating 100% clean or 100% junk, has kept me in balance over the years. It keeps me on track of my health goals without being too much of a stickler. The only downside of this approach is the massive hits my BG takes on the days I let loose. Once I got the CGM I could see the roller coaster ride my BG would take on these cheat days, and I could match my mood and energy level with where my BG was at the time. This made me think more about ways I could control my BG when I wanted to treat myself, without putting myself at risk of the consequences of poor BG management.</p>
<p>There are a few tried and true ways to control your BG. The first, and most boring, is to just eat healthy unprocessed foods. A second way is to incorporate movement into your day after eating. Simply <a href="https://www.thehealthy.com/exercise/walking/blood-sugar-walking/">going on a walk after eating</a> can have a profound impact on stabilizing your blood glucose. The same goes for more intense movement like lifting weights or cardio. These two strategies are strong, but they didn’t help me when I wanted to treat myself. I quickly learned that it’s hard to outrun a donut you just ate. That’s when I came across a third way to control BG.</p>
<p>A favorite podcast of mine is called <a href="https://allin.com/">All In</a>. It features four men who are titans in Silicon Valley. From founders of Paypal to early Facebook and Google employees, these guys know their stuff. During one episode I learned about a supplement company one of the members of the podcast invested in, called <a href="https://supergut.com/">Super Gut</a>. The company is all about fiber, which sounds like the worlds most boring supplement, but in reality has countless benefits. It turns out that 95% of Americans do not consume enough fiber, which is around 30 grams a day. So we all need to look for more ways to consume more fiber.</p>
<p>Super Gut uses prebiotic fiber found in foods like green bananas, oats, and potatoes. This preobiotic fiber is the best kind of food to provide your gut microbiome, since it can’t be converted into fuel for your body like other macronutrients. Fiber is bulky, so it easily expands to fill your stomach, causing a feeling of being full. It also slows your digestion, which can prolong the feeling of being full, and has the additional benefit of regulating your BG. Finally, there have been recent findings that show consuming the right types of fiber makes your body <a href="https://supergut.com/blog/natural-glp-1-how-to-produce-satiety-hormones-without-ozempic">release hormones like GLP-1</a>. This is the main ingredient behind booming drugs like Ozempic, used for weight loss. Why pay thousands for synthetic GLP-1 when you get get more of it naturally with fiber?</p>
<p>Each serving of the Super Gut shake contains 15 grams of fiber, which is around 50% of the fiber we need each day. That’s a crap ton of fiber. To put that into perspective, you would have to eat about 5 medium sized potatoes (with skin on) to get the same amount of fiber. 10 seconds of consuming a fiber supplement compared to 20+ minutes of force feeding potatoes. The choice is easy.</p>
<p>How do I use it? First and foremost I use Super Gut to get the daily recommendation of fiber. Usually consuming a serving at the start of each day. Going from maybe 10 grams of daily fiber to 30+ is life changing in more ways then one. Bathroom trips get a lot more interesting. Any previous problems in that department gets solved immediately. What has surprised me the most is its impact on my blood sugar when I eat junk. When I treat myself on a Faturday, I first consume fiber, then eat whatever crap comes my way. Ice cream went from spiking my BG over 200 mg/dl to now only going up slightly to 130-140 mg/dl. Which is within the healthy range. That small spike is short lived, compared to previous Faturday’s where my BG would spike for hours at a time. Now when I eat pizza, my responds like I’m eating chicken and rice. I usually have a 2-3 window after consuming fiber where I can eat junk without spiking my BG. It’s truly mind blowing.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-15-hacking-blood-sugar/chart1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-15-hacking-blood-sugar/chart2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Now this doesn’t mean you should go out and eat whatever you want, as long as you consume some fiber beforehand. Don’t do that. But when you do want to treat yourself on occasion, you can do so knowing that it won’t wreck your metabolic health. Try it for yourself! I’m sure there are other supplements besides Super Gut out there that can do the same thing. Regardless of whether you’re trying to pig out or not, getting more fiber into your life will improve your life in more ways than one.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>health</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-15-hacking-blood-sugar/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-15-hacking-blood-sugar/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploratory Data Analysis: Autocorrelation</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-12-ts-fundamentals-autocorrelation/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>This post is part of the <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-03-ts-fundamentals-eda/">exploratory data analysis chapter</a> within a larger learning series around time series forecasting fundamentals. <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-25-ts-fundamentals/">Check out the main learning path</a> to see other posts in the series.</em></p>
<p><em>The example monthly data used in this series <a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/posts/2024-10-02-ts-fundamentals-whats-a-time-series/example_ts_data.csv">can be found here.</a> You can also find the <a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/notebooks/2024-11-12-ts-fundamentals-autocorrelation.ipynb">python code used in this post here.</a></em></p>
<section id="time-series-data-has-memory" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="time-series-data-has-memory">Time Series Data Has Memory</h3>
<p>The biggest factor that differentiates a time series from another form of data is order. Each observation in a time series is ordered by well, you guessed it, time. Because of this order, there are unique relationships that develop in the data. Let’s take temperature for example. If today’s temperature is 70°F, and the temperature in the previous seven days was around 65-80, what do you think the temperature tomorrow will be? Probably not below freezing. It’ll most likely be similar to the temperature today. This memory about the past is one of the most powerful concepts in time series forecasting. It’s the concept of autocorrelation.</p>
<p>Autocorrelation is when a value in a time series is related to previous values in that series. In simple terms, it measures how much the current value depends on past values. For example, if high temperatures today make it likely to have high temperatures tomorrow, the temperature series has a positive autocorrelation.</p>
</section>
<section id="calculating-autocorrelation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="calculating-autocorrelation">Calculating Autocorrelation</h3>
<p>Getting the autocorrelation is as simple as computing the correlation of the existing time series with a lagged time series. For example let’s take a time series from our example data set, shown below.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-12-ts-fundamentals-autocorrelation/chart1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We can create lags of one month, two months, and onwards. Then calculate the correlation between the original time series (with a lag of 0) and these new lagged time series. The results of that process are shown below, with a lag up to 24 months.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-12-ts-fundamentals-autocorrelation/chart2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Correlation is shown on the y-axis and the lag amount is shown on the x-axis. The chart shows high autocorrelation for a lag of 0, 1, 12, and 24 months. A lag of 0 has a perfect correlation because it’s the exact same as the original time series. These lag correlations are shown as positive values, meaning that there is a positive correlation with the original time series. There are also above the shaded blue region of the chart. This shaded region is a confidence interval. This confidence interval helps us filter out lags that are not statistically significant, meaning they don’t have a correlation due to random chance. Any lag outside of the shaded region is significant and should have a real relationship with our original time series.</p>
</section>
<section id="partial-autocorrelation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="partial-autocorrelation">Partial Autocorrelation</h3>
<p>Autocorrelation has one fatal flaw though. It can provide misleading correlations since it doesn’t account for correlations between lags. For example, there might be a very strong correlation with the original time series and lag 1 of the time series. Because of this correlation, there is a good chance that a lag 2 also shows a strong correlation. The lag 2 correlation might only be due to lag 2 having similar information to lag 1. So the end results could be misleading.</p>
<p>To account for this, partial autocorrelation was created. This process takes into account the correlations between lags. Making sure that the end correlations are only connected to the original time series. It is the preferred method of analyzing autocorrelation. So make sure it’s part of your time series tool kit. Here is the partial autocorrelation of our example time series.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-12-ts-fundamentals-autocorrelation/chart3.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="reading-the-tea-leaves" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reading-the-tea-leaves">Reading the Tea Leaves</h3>
<p>Let’s take a deeper look at the partial autocorrelation and see what insights it might provide. When looking at the partial autocorrelation chart, the biggest correlation is at lag 0. This makes sense since a lag of 0 is just the original time series, so there will be a perfect correlation of 1. Lag 1 shows a strong correlation, which makes sense, since it’s contains values closest to the original series. There are also strong correlations at lag 11, 12, and 13. This confirms our data has strong seasonality. The highest correlation is at lag 12, which means values today are highly correlated to values at the same time in the previous year (12 months ago). This information will be invaluable when we start to build models in the future.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>
<p>Having strong partial autocorrelation in your time series will always lead to more accurate future forecasts. Especially if you expect <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-04-11-time-series-past-future/">the future to be similar to the past</a>. If your data has little or no correlation with historical lags, then it will be more difficult to train accurate models to forecast the future. Calculating partial autocorrelation should always be one of the first things you do when working with time series. It’s quickest way to start building intuition about your data.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>machine-learning</category>
  <category>time-series</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-12-ts-fundamentals-autocorrelation/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-12-ts-fundamentals-autocorrelation/chart3.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="110" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Why I Cancelled All My Streaming Apps</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-08-cancelled-streaming/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Last weekend I was in Dallas for a close friend who was getting married. It was the Friday before the wedding and I had some time to kill. So I walked around Dallas for a few hours. That’s my favorite way to explore the city. I eventually got hungry and settled on a restaurant in uptown. After ordering I sat outside to enjoy the nice Texas weather. Which funny enough looked the exact same as a winter in Seattle (clouds, dark, rainy).</p>
<p>A waitress slowly walked up behind me, looking concerned. She asked what I was doing, making sure I was ok. I wasn’t doing anything crazy, just looking out across the city and thinking. It took me a while to realize that she was concerned because I wasn’t engrossed in my phone. Checking X, Instagram, or TicTok. After realizing this I told her that I was trying to stare at my phone less and was enjoying the new city. Maybe she thought I just got dumped and was looking grimly out on this cruel world. Or that I just got fired and was re-evaluating my life choices. Overall she was concerned because I was not looking at my phone to pass the time. Now that definitely concerned me.</p>
<p>Weeks before this incident I made conscious decision to unsubscribe and delete all TV/Movie streaming apps. Things like Hulu with live TV, Netflix, MAX, Paramount+. I had them all. And they all had to go. Why would I do something so crazy! The explanation is simple my dear Watson. I wanted to create more opportunities to be bored in my life. Call me crazy, but it’s working out better than I’d imagined.</p>
<p>When I was a college freshman at Kansas, circa 2012, I was part of a fraternity. As a rule, all pledges of the fraternity were not allowed to have any form of TV or video game console in their room. I like to think it was to give parents peace of mind that they would be studying more than goofing off. But the real goal was something entirely different. When 40 pledges can’t pass time by watching TV they have to do other things. Together. Instead of binge watching a show alone in your room you now have to be a real human being and get together with other pledges to pass the time. My older brother, who was two years older and in the fraternity, knew this when he bought me a dart board as a present before school started. He said I would use this more than anything else in my room. You know what? He was absolutely right. That dart board become a sort of water cooler that allowed other pledges to come to my room and pass the time by playing darts. In addition to darts, we did all sorts of crazy things to pass the time in between classes. One week it was playing cards. Another it was creating playlists on Spotify. We even created a sacred coffee ritual before we all went off to study each night. This included a special coffee blend, singing an old Folgers jingle from the 90s, and maybe a little dance if we were feeling up to it. My mom even knew what to expect when I bought a desk chair before school started. She said I needed to get the cheapest one because she knew with absolute certainty that it was going to get destroyed through activities like chair racing and playing a form of floor hockey while riding a chair. That was a common activity when my older brother was a pledge. Safe to say, that chair did not make it through my freshman year unscathed. All of those activities may sound dumb, but that’s how each pledge got to know each other. Going from strangers to brothers in a short six months.</p>
<p>Cutting out all streaming apps from my life allowed me to help recreate the kind of boredom I felt in college to do things that were actually good for me. Instead of watching a show for four hours like a zombie. There are simply too many good shows and movies out right now. All at our fingertips waiting to be watched. This creates an opportunity to always be entertained, always have something to occupy your mind. That kind of stimulation cannot be good for us, and that’s why I’m trying to remove it from my life.</p>
<p>Here are a few other reasons why I wanted to remove TV from my daily equation:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Time suck: You can easily watch TV for eight hours straight on a Saturday. That is time you just never get back. Robert Green has an idea called “alive time vs dead time”. Alive time is doing things that are creative and beneficial to your life. Things like reading, writing, painting. Dead time is essentially a waste and time you never get back. Things like watching TV or scrolling social media. Alive time gives you life, while dead time takes it away from you.</li>
<li>News is bad for you: Most news out there is about terrible things happening in the world. That’s what creates the most viewers, which bring in ad revenue to stay on air. Humans are not designed to know everything bad going on in the world at once. It’s a form of sensory overload that leaves us more anxious and pessimistic about societies future. It’s a form of entertainment junk food.</li>
<li>TV meeting your social needs: I think an unnoticed impact from TV is that it fills a lot of the socialization needs us humans crave every day. A feeling of being with friends or loved ones. Instead of going out to hang with a friend, you might just stay in and hang out with your friends that live inside a TV show. An introvert like me can only have so much social stimulation in a day, and watching too much TV leaves less opportunities to socialize with real people.</li>
<li>TV to forget problems: Ever had a bad day at the office and come home to watch a funny sitcom to relax? We’ve all done it. And in moderation it’s probably an ok thing to do. But if you’re doing that every day after work, then you are just numbing bigger problems in your life. TV won’t fix that, it just delays the problem for another time. Which can eventually blow up in your face. Taking that salve away gives us no choice but to face problems in our lives. Giving us the time to actually do something about versus just get by another day.</li>
</ol>
<p>Now my dear reader, you might still think I’m insane. What do you do with all of this newfound boredom? Aren’t people who say they don’t own a TV just pretentious do****s? Here’s how I now spend my time:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Books: When TV is out of the question, you can easily crush 2+ books a week. Books become your constant companion. I’ve recently fallen back in love with fiction books. For over a decade I’ve been strictly reading non-fiction at a clip of 1-2 books per month. Now I read multiple non-fiction and fiction books at once. And it’s amazing. You know how people say the book was better than the movie? They are usually right. What was a 2.5 hour movie is actually a 300+ page book that takes over 10 hours to read. Talk about bang for your buck.</li>
<li>Music: Sitting down to solely listen to music has been lost on me the last decade. As a teenager a good song could change my life, but in recent years I haven’t ventured out of my old favorites. Now I sit down and explore new artists, albums, and deep cuts from my top bands. This is now the most relaxing thing I do. Nothing fixes a rough day like a good playlist.</li>
<li>Sports: The biggest drawback of no TV is no live sports. I love everything soccer and Kansas City sports. So whenever I want to go watch a game I now have to get off my butt and go watch it somewhere. This now forces me to be in the company of others, most often close friends. This leads me to my next point.</li>
<li>Get out of the house: TV is the ultimate ball and chain tying you to your house. Without it I now have pressure to get out into the world and explore what’s going on in my community. Art shows. Farmers markets. Anything and everything going on in the world is now at my disposal since I literally have nothing better to do. I now can’t say no to things because if I did I would just be bored at home. This creates more serendipity in my life.</li>
<li>TV in the wild: Coming across a movie or show when I’m out and about is now a treat. I enjoy it 100x more because it doesn’t happen that often. Last weekend my Alaska Airlines flight had free movies I could watch. I chose a new Guy Ritchie movie about WW2 and it blew my mind. I wouldn’t have appreciated it in the same way if it was the third movie I watched on a lazy Sunday afternoon.</li>
</ol>
<p>Who knows, maybe in a months time I will relapse and sign back up for all of the streaming apps I quit. But so far it’s been a good experience. Maybe try it out yourself for a few weeks and see how it might improve your life. I think we all need to engineer more opportunities to be bored. Because when we’re bored, that’s when good ideas come to us and when serendipity can change your life forever.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-08-cancelled-streaming/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-08-cancelled-streaming/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploratory Data Analysis: Time Series Decomposition</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-06-ts-fundamentals-decomposition/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>This post is part of the <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-03-ts-fundamentals-eda/">exploratory data analysis chapter</a> within a larger learning series around time series forecasting fundamentals. <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-25-ts-fundamentals/">Check out the main learning path</a> to see other posts in the series.</em></p>
<p><em>The example monthly data used in this series <a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/posts/2024-10-02-ts-fundamentals-whats-a-time-series/example_ts_data.csv">can be found here.</a> You can also find the <a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/notebooks/2024-11-06-ts-fundamentals-decomposition.ipynb">python code used in this post here.</a></em></p>
<section id="your-data-is-so-trendy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="your-data-is-so-trendy">Your Data is so Trendy</h3>
<p>Every single time series you have ever seen has a trend and seasonality. If they don’t, then they are random white noise. A trend is just values steadily rising or falling over time. You could have a rising trend in some years, then a falling trend in others. Below is a chart with a strong trend but weak seasonality.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-06-ts-fundamentals-decomposition/chart1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Seasonality just means that your data has a recurring seasonal pattern. For example your data could spike during the holiday season from Oct-Dec, then fall drastically from Jan-Jun.&nbsp;Your seasonality could also change over time. Below is a chart with strong seasonality but weak trend.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-06-ts-fundamentals-decomposition/chart2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>In order to better understand the trend and seasonal patterns in your data, you need to isolate them into separate components. This is done through a process called time series decomposition. This process breaks out a time series into three separate parts: trend, seasonality, and remainder. The remainder component is just parts of your time series that can’t be explained by the trend and seasonal component. Let’s try decomposing a time series from our example data set.</p>
</section>
<section id="breaking-out-trend-and-seasonality-with-additive-decomposition" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="breaking-out-trend-and-seasonality-with-additive-decomposition">Breaking Out Trend and Seasonality with Additive Decomposition</h3>
<p>We can isolate the trend component of a time series using simple methods like moving averages (MA). These are just simple averages over a span of time. Let’s take a time series from our example revenue data and create a moving average. In the first chart below we used a <a href="https://otexts.com/fpp3/moving-averages.html#estimating-the-trend-cycle-with-seasonal-data">2x12-MA</a>. This moving average now isolates the trend of the time series. We can see a dip in trend around 2020 then a strong rebound going forward. The moving average doesn’t start and end at the same time as our time series, since we need a burn in period to start creating the averages. If we wanted to detrend the time series we can subtract the new trend series from our original revenue, shown in the second chart below.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-06-ts-fundamentals-decomposition/chart3.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-06-ts-fundamentals-decomposition/chart4.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Next we can get the seasonal component of our data. This is very straightforward. All we have to do is take our detrended series and calculate the average revenue for each month of the year. After getting the average value per month, we can divide by the total average across all months. This ensures that the seasonal values of each month add to zero. Then we repeat the final values per month across all years. The final result is shown below. Now we can see there is very strong seasonal patterns at certain times of the year. Some quarters have high sales, while others do not. This kind of repeatable pattern will be very important for us when it comes to training models.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-06-ts-fundamentals-decomposition/chart5.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Finally we can get the final piece of our decomposition, the remainder (aka residual) series. This is everything that couldn’t be explained by the trend and seasonal components. Simply take the original revenue time series, subtract the trend and seasonal components, and bam you have the remainder series.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-06-ts-fundamentals-decomposition/chart6.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="stl-decomposition" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stl-decomposition">STL Decomposition</h3>
<p>The additive decomposition approach can work very well if your data has a linear trend and stable seasonality. But if the series is growing exponentially, or has changing seasonality, then more advanced methods are needed. This is where STL decomposition comes in. STL is an acronym for “Seasonal and Trend decomposition using Loess”, while loess is a smoothing method for estimating nonlinear relationships. This smoothing process allows for changing seasonality, a more complex understanding of the trend component, and more resistance to outliers. Here is the STL process broken down step by step.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Extract Initial Seasonal Component
<ul>
<li>First, STL identifies the seasonal pattern in the data. It does this by looking at the regular repeating cycles (e.g., monthly or weekly patterns).</li>
<li>Using Loess smoothing, it calculates a rough seasonal pattern that captures these cycles.</li>
<li>This step gives an initial estimate of what the seasonal pattern looks like.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Remove Seasonality to Estimate the Trend
<ul>
<li>After finding the initial seasonal component, STL subtracts it from the data to get a rough idea of the trend (the overall up or down direction).</li>
<li>Loess smoothing is applied again to the deseasonalized data (data without seasonal patterns) to create a smooth trend line.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Refine the Seasonal and Trend Components
<ul>
<li>STL repeats the process in cycles, fine-tuning both the trend and seasonal estimates.</li>
<li>Each cycle alternates between smoothing the seasonal component and the trend component, adjusting them with each pass to better fit the data.</li>
<li>By repeating this process, STL allows the seasonal component to change over time if necessary and captures any evolving trends.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Calculate the Remainder
<ul>
<li>Once the trend and seasonal components are finalized, STL subtracts both from the original data. What’s left is the remainder component, representing the random, unpredictable part of the data.</li>
<li>This remainder is what can’t be explained by the regular trend or seasonal patterns, capturing any noise or outliers.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>Here is the output of a STL decomposition. Each component can be added together to get the original time series, just like additive decomposition.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-06-ts-fundamentals-decomposition/chart7.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="reading-the-tea-leaves" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reading-the-tea-leaves">Reading the Tea Leaves</h3>
<p>Understanding the outputs of time series decomposition can be more of an art than science. The more you do it, the more your data intuition grows about what’s happening. Looking at the results of STL decomposition tells us a few things for our time series.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>There has been mostly a stable trend over the years, except for a strange dip in 2020.</li>
<li>Seasonality is strong with repeating peaks and valleys across the years. But it does seem to be growing with each passing year.</li>
<li>Most of the residual points hover around zero, which is ideal. Having the residual component have an average of zero and a constant standard deviation over time means the data is just white noise, or things that can’t be explained. We do see a large drop in 2020 though…</li>
</ol>
<p>This analysis shows us that there is most likely an outlier in 2020 that seriously impacted our data. If you don’t have a guess as to what this might be than you might have been living under a rock the last decade. The impact is from COVID-19. Thankfully this impact can be taken care of later in our modeling process. But for now it’s good that we identify it and get the domain knowledge to know what could have caused it.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>
<p>Decomposing a time series is often one of the first things an accomplished data scientist does before training any kind of machine learning model. Breaking the time series into its components allows us to understand the potential forces that is impacting the trend of the data and if there are any outliers in the data. Knowing this allows us to change our approach when training models. Ultimately leading to more accurate forecasts down the road.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>machine-learning</category>
  <category>time-series</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-06-ts-fundamentals-decomposition/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-06-ts-fundamentals-decomposition/chart7.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="115" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Newsletters Stink</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-30-newsletters-stink/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="too-many-too-fast" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="too-many-too-fast">Too Many, Too Fast</h3>
<p>When I open my email, I cringe. I have hundreds of unread emails. Not from coworkers about important work. But instead from the many newsletters that every influential person on the internet now has. When I signed up for these newsletters, I was excited. Insights delivered right to my mailbox! What was initially 3-4 newsletter emails a week quickly turned into over two dozen. For someone who likes the practice of inbox zero this caused unneeded stress.</p>
<p>In order to offload these emails into another place for reading, I signed up for services like ReadWise. Which has a great reading app you can have newsletters automatically get sent to. This was helpful at first, but eventually turned back into email. When I look at my “feed” on the Reader app, I have 121 unseen newsletter emails. That’s insane. I cannot read all of these, nor do I want to. Something needs to change.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-newsletters-stink" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-newsletters-stink">Why Newsletters Stink</h3>
<p>Newsletters serve a good purpose. They are a way to push out content and build audiences. Which can lead lead to $ for their creators. These good intentions come with some drawbacks. Let’s call them out.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Push, no Pull</strong>: Newsletters get thrusted upon us once we sign up. Some get sent every single day. This kind of push process creates build ups of unread articles in our mailboxes. The bottleneck is us. It’s our time. We don’t have a lot and we want to make the most of it. Ideally we would instead prefer a pull approach where once we read one newsletter, we then get the next one. Instead of having 20 stacked up in our inboxes.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>New is Not Always Better</strong>: The “news” in newsletter is what makes them bad. I think we all know that consuming news is not good for us. It raises our anxiety and is a form of entertainment junk food. Instead of always getting the freshest take on business or technology today, you’d probably get more insight from articles written years ago that are timeless. Reading a Paul Graham essay on building a business written 10 years ago is probably better than getting a newsletter from someone today who has only build one business. Also there is pressure for creators to push these out on a regular cadence, which means quality goes down. Pushing 4 newsletters out a month will most likely lead to less quality then taking the time to write one newsletter over 1-2 months. New and more is not always better. We need more evergreen content.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Archives Are Graveyards</strong>: Have you ever gone looking through old newsletters from your favorite creator? Probably not. Only the brave of heart dive into the dumpster of a creators website and dig around for little nuggets of gold. There might be a newsletter from five years ago that could change your life, but to find it you might have to dig through dozens of others about the NFT market in 2021 that no one cares about anymore. Again, see my point ini #2. We need a better way of finding the best evergreen content.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>No Personalization</strong>: Once you sign up for a newsletter, you are at the mercy of reading all of them. Regardless of the content in each one. This might be ok if the newsletter author writes about one thing, but a disaster when they are wide ranging. For example, let’s say Joe Rogan had a newsletter (he doesn’t but let’s pretend). You might love all of the content around culture, politics, and comedy but absolutely hate it every time he talks about the UFC. Maybe you don’t like MMA, and could care less who Connor McGregor may fight next. We need a better way of finding the best content relevant to our interests.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>They Replaced Blogs</strong>: People that used to write blogs now write newsletters. What a shame! You could in theory just take the posts you used to publish to your blog and now just send out via newsletter. But people don’t do that anymore. What a bummer. We need more blogs and less newsletters.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="who-does-things-right" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="who-does-things-right">Who Does Things Right</h3>
<p>You know who does things right? YouTube. They have it all figured out. Instead of seeing a list of videos in chronological order, they show you what videos you might be most interested in. Not just from channels you follow but for any channel. You can interact with videos you like by watching them multiple times, liking the video, or subscribing to the channel. This ensures you see more content like it. Or if you hate the video you can give the thumbs down, click on “show me less of this”, or even block the channel entirely. With a few smart features they fixed every thing that is wrong with other forms of content like newsletters and blogs.</p>
<p>When I open up my YouTube homepage on the app, I see a sea of great options. The first video recommended on the page is for a podcast I like that just posted a new video two hours ago. As I scroll I see content from last week, last month, even as far back as two years ago. These are all things that interest me, not just the latest content from channels I follow. I even see content from channels I’ve never heard about, but is chosen based on my interest in other liked videos. This is why YouTube dominates.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-30-newsletters-stink/image2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><a href="https://variety.com/vip/netflix-vs-youtube-post-streaming-wars-1236143341/">Source - Variety</a></p>
</section>
<section id="make-blogs-great-again" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="make-blogs-great-again">Make Blogs Great Again</h3>
<p>Ideally there should be a service that is like YouTube but for blogs. Anyone who has a blog can connect their site to the service, and posts are algorithmically provided to the user based on what the user likes. It won’t be what causes the most outrage or reactions, but instead what makes them entertained or more informed. The site would have no news, just evergreen content that’s just as relevant next year as it is now. Sites like Medium try to do this today, but their biggest flaw is that they live behind a walled garden. Meaning a blog owner has to only post their stuff to Medium and not on their own site. This is not ideal. Since you now have to play by Mediums rules and all of your content now lives on a platform you don’t control. You could argue YouTube is the same but YouTube is the only way people consume user submitted video content today. There is no second choice. Compared to blogs where anyone can host their own for free via GitHub (that’s what I do).</p>
<p>There could also be amazing AI features built into this new blog recommendation service. What if all blog posts on the site were indexed and you could ask questions about the blog via GenAI? Imagine having a conversation with Paul Graham, powered by every piece of advice he has ever written about building businesses or technology. It would basically be a mentor on demand. Always ready to bounce ideas off of or think through hard problems.</p>
<p>The world has too many new(s) things. We need to make old things, like blogs, new again.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>machine-learning</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-30-newsletters-stink/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-30-newsletters-stink/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploratory Data Analysis: Shape of the Data</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-15-ts-fundamentals-eda-data-shape/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<style>
.figure {
    text-align: center;
}

.figure figcaption {
    text-align: center;
}
</style>
<p><em>This post is part of the <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-03-ts-fundamentals-eda/">exploratory data analysis chapter</a> within a larger learning series around time series forecasting fundamentals. <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-25-ts-fundamentals/">Check out the main learning path</a> to see other posts in the series.</em></p>
<p>The example data used in this series <a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/posts/2024-10-02-ts-fundamentals-whats-a-time-series/example_ts_data.csv">can be found here.</a></p>
<section id="initial-data-smell-test" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="initial-data-smell-test">Initial Data Smell Test</h3>
<p>The first step of exploratory data analysis for time series is getting a feel for the data at a high level. This doesn’t involve complex statistical analysis. Just simple charts to see how things look. When analyzing these charts we’ll use the most underrated concept in machine learning. The human smell test. This involves using your eye balls to look at the data and understand what could be going on based on your <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-04-02-time-series-domain-expertise/">domain experience</a>. Let’s chart the time series in a few ways and give it a smell test.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-15-ts-fundamentals-eda-data-shape/chart1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Total revenue by month</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Looking at the data all up shows a pretty stable upward trend with a few bumps in the data. Right now it’s hard to tell if those bumps in 2019 and 2021 are outliers or not. We would have to dig deeper into the data. The trend seems to be growing exponentially. Meaning it’s not a straight line but instead one that seems to grow faster each year. This kind of hockey stick growth is what all businesses aspire to. Lastly it’s hard to tell if there is any strong seasonality.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-15-ts-fundamentals-eda-data-shape/chart2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Total country revenue by month</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Breaking out the data by each country gives us a better picture of what’s going on in our monthly sales. Canada is the country with the exponential growth, combined with a few spikes in some months. These spikes could be one off events that are unpredictable, or something happened in those months that can be quantified in data.</p>
<p>Revenue in the United States has more of a linear upward trend with strong seasonality. There is something strange going on in 2020 though. Any guesses on what that could be?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-15-ts-fundamentals-eda-data-shape/chart3.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Total product revenue by month</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Looking at revenue by product tells a similar story as revenue by country. Cookie sales seem to be a lot more bumpier than ice cream, which is more stable and growing fast.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-15-ts-fundamentals-eda-data-shape/chart4.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Revenue for each individual time series by month</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Finally we can view each time series individually. Our initial hunches at higher aggregations are now confirmed. We can see Canada cookie sales have those crazy spikes. After talking to our sales and marketing teams, we learn that the spikes are caused by new cookie product launches. Ice cream sales in Canada is the one series with the exponential growth. Both don’t have much seasonality.</p>
<p>Revenue in the United States is all about seasonality. Cookie sales show an interesting dip in 2020 but seem to rebound in 2021. This could be caused by the impact of COVID. Ice cream sales has both strong trend and seasonality. This will make it easy to forecast going forward. The more stable the trends and seasonality in your time series, the easier it is to create an accurate future forecast. <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-04-11-time-series-past-future/">The future should always resemble the past.</a></p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>
<p>We have now completed our initial smell test of the historical data. Based on our domain knowledge of the business we can start to understand what happened in the past, and use that information to help us create a better future forecast. The smell test was easy on this dataset since there are only four time series. You might be working with thousands of time series at your company, so higher level smell checks might be the only thing you can do. There are more automated ways at analyzing the data, and will be explored more in future posts.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>machine-learning</category>
  <category>time-series</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-15-ts-fundamentals-eda-data-shape/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-15-ts-fundamentals-eda-data-shape/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploratory Data Analysis For Time Series</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-03-ts-fundamentals-eda/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>This post is part of a larger learning series around time series forecasting fundamentals. <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-25-ts-fundamentals/">Check out the learning path</a> to see other posts in the series.</em></p>
<section id="exploratory-data-analysis-overview" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exploratory-data-analysis-overview">Exploratory Data Analysis Overview</h3>
<p>Exploratory data analysis, or EDA, is the process of understanding the patterns in your data before you train any machine learning model. It’s the first step in the data science lifecycle. Blindly throwing your data into a model before understanding it yourself is a recipe for disaster. If your data is garbage, you will create a garbage forecast. <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-04-08-time-series-garbage/">Gargbage in, garbage out.</a></p>
</section>
<section id="eda-for-time-series" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="eda-for-time-series">EDA for Time Series</h3>
<p>Applying EDA to time series data is a unique process, different from every other kind of data used in machine learning. Here are the building blocks of good time series EDA. Click on each to explore further.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-15-ts-fundamentals-eda-data-shape/">Shape of the Data</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-06-ts-fundamentals-decomposition/">Time Series Decomposition</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-12-ts-fundamentals-autocorrelation/">Autocorrelation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-26-ts-fundamentals-missing-outliers/">Missing Values, Outliers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-24-ts-fundamentals-eda-xregs/">External Regressors</a></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>machine-learning</category>
  <category>time-series</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-03-ts-fundamentals-eda/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-03-ts-fundamentals-eda/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What’s A Time Series?</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-02-ts-fundamentals-whats-a-time-series/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>This post is part of a larger learning series around time series forecasting fundamentals. <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-25-ts-fundamentals/">Check out the learning path</a> to see other posts in the series.</em></p>
<section id="ais-are-like-onions-we-both-have-layers" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ais-are-like-onions-we-both-have-layers">AI’s Are Like Onions, We Both Have Layers</h3>
<p>There’s a lot of terminology in the world of artificial intelligence. With a lot of layers to it. The practice of time series forecasting is many layers down. How deep? Let’s start peeling back the layers.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-02-ts-fundamentals-whats-a-time-series/image2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="artificial-intelligence" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="artificial-intelligence">Artificial Intelligence</h4>
<p>Artificial Intelligence, or AI, can be described as the ability for machines to learn and think like humans. It’s as simple as that. While that’s an easy thing to say, it’s a hard thing to do. AI has been around since the mid 20th century, with a lot of ups and downs. There are multiple subdisciplines of AI. Things like robotics and expert systems. But the biggest and most important is machine learning.</p>
</section>
<section id="machine-learning" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="machine-learning">Machine Learning</h4>
<p>Machine Learning, or ML, is all about creating algorithms learn on their own from data. ML turns the idea of traditional programming on its head. Traditional programming is all about writing out explicit instructions or rules, in the form of code, that tell a computer what to do. ML on the other hand is code in the form of an algorithm where the rules are learned from training data. It’s a unique paradigm shift that has unlocked countless advancements in computing. Self-driving cars, human genome sequencing, and yes even forecasting has all been driven by these algorithms that can learn. Similar to AI, the world of ML has multiple disciplines. The one we’re interested in is supervised learning.</p>
<div class="text-center">
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-02-ts-fundamentals-whats-a-time-series/image3.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div>
<p><a href="https://contenteratechspace.com/how-different-are-conventional-programming-and-machine-learning/">image source</a></p>
</section>
<section id="supervised-learning" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="supervised-learning">Supervised Learning</h4>
<p>Supervised learning is a type of machine learning where you teach a computer to make predictions or decisions using examples. It’s like teaching a child to identify animals by showing them pictures of different animals and telling them what each one is. In supervised learning, you give the computer a bunch of “input” data (like pictures of animals) and the correct “output” (the names of the animals). The computer learns from these examples, and over time it gets better at predicting the outputs based on new inputs it hasn’t seen before. There are a few different flavors of supervised learning, but in this learning series we care about regression.</p>
</section>
<section id="regression" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="regression">Regression</h4>
<p>Regression is a type of supervised learning method that helps predict a numerical value based on past data. Imagine you want to predict the price of a house based on its size, location, and number of rooms. Regression analyzes the historical data of house prices and their characteristics to find a relationship. Once this relationship is understood, you can input the characteristics of any house and the regression model will predict its price.</p>
<p>Traditional regression modeling usually doesn’t have a time component, but when you need to predict a number over time, that’s when we enter the crazy world of time series.</p>
</section>
<section id="time-series" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="time-series">Time Series</h4>
<p>A time series is a series of numerical data points recorded at regular intervals. For example the highest temperature each day over the last 10 years can be thought of as one time series. If we have that temperature data for 50 cities, then we have 50 time series in our dataset. A time series can be at any kind of time interval. Yearly, quarterly, monthly, daily, hourly, etc. You get the idea.</p>
<p>The art of forecasting is just taking historical time series data, and feeding it into a model that can learn from historical trends and seasonality patterns. Ultimately creating a future prediction for the next few periods of time.</p>
<p>Most regression models in machine learning can be turned into a time series forecast model by the process of incorporating time dependant data as features through a process called feature engineering. A feature is just a variable in your dataset that can be used to help predict your target variable. The process of creating features before you train a model is called feature engineering. The target variable is what you want to predict going forward. These machine learning regression models can be thought of as multivariate models, since they can incorporate many different variables or features into a model.</p>
<p>Let’s apply this to a quick example. For a monthly revenue time series forecast, our target variable will be the revenue variable in our dataset. And we can create features like month of the year, how much money we made in the same month last year, etc. to help predict revenue.</p>
<p>There are also models that only exist in the world of time series forecasting. These are more statistical models and less machine learning models. Meaning they operate like equations that can applied to your data compared to a machine learning model that tries to learn the patterns underlying the data. These models are often univariate, which means that you only need the historical target variable values accompanied by a timestamp (list of dates) to train these models. While they might be simple in nature, they are still very useful even today. Often beating more complex models like deep learning.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="time-series-example" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="time-series-example">Time Series Example</h3>
<p>Now that we’ve peeled back all of the layers on time series forecasting, let’s take a look at some data. In this learning series I will be using the most common time series that applies to every company in the world, historical revenue. The data we’ll use is completely made up, but created in a way to illustrate a lot of the learning concepts throughout the series. The sales data is recoded at a monthly level, broken out by countries our hypothetical company operates in and what products it sells. Let’s take a quick look at the data.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/posts/2024-10-02-ts-fundamentals-whats-a-time-series/example_ts_data.csv">You can find the raw data here.</a></p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-02-ts-fundamentals-whats-a-time-series/chart1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>In the data there are sales for two countries across two products. This means we have four unique time series we can forecast. One for each unique combination of country and product. Throughout this learning series we will use this data as an example as we work through different time series concepts.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>
<p>Time series is a very niche corner in the AI universe. It may seem small but in reality every company in the world deals with time series. They make up most financial data like sales and are top of mind for every leader in the C-suite. You should now know what a time series is and understand more of the common terms you will hear around machine learning. Now that we have a good foundation of terminology, lets explore the data even more in the next post.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>machine-learning</category>
  <category>time-series</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-02-ts-fundamentals-whats-a-time-series/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-02-ts-fundamentals-whats-a-time-series/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Thoughts On Time Series Forecasting Fundamentals</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-25-ts-fundamentals/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The ability to create forecasts about the future is a superpower. Machine learning (ML) models take this to another level by increasing forecast accuracy while reducing the time spent creating the forecast. Using ML might seem a little scary at first. You may not know where to start. Type “intro ML course” into Bing and you’ll probably get millions of links. Which ones are good? Why do they cost $5,000? That’s why I wanted to create a gentle introduction to time series forecasting with ML. Where I start from first principles and work our way up to shipping forecasts in production. The intent is to cover the core theory of ML forecasting, and less on the code itself. The code can come later, but anyone who consumes the outputs from ML or helps train ML models needs a strong understanding of how this process works.</p>
<p>The sequence of what you learn is just as important as what content you learn. I have developed a learning path that takes you from absolute beginner and slowly adds new concepts until you’re a forecasting master! Please click on each link in order to get up to speed, or skip around to any topic you want to dive into again. Don’t try to read this all in a day, take your time, take notes, and maybe even paste some of the posts into your favorite AI tool to quiz yourself on the topics. Happy learning!</p>
<section id="our-learning-journey" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="our-learning-journey">Our Learning Journey</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-02-ts-fundamentals-whats-a-time-series/">What’s a time series?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-03-ts-fundamentals-eda/">Exploratory Data Analysis</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-15-ts-fundamentals-eda-data-shape/">Shape of the Data</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-06-ts-fundamentals-decomposition/">Time Series Decomposition</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-12-ts-fundamentals-autocorrelation/">Autocorrelation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-26-ts-fundamentals-missing-outliers/">Missing Values, Outliers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-24-ts-fundamentals-eda-xregs/">External Regressors</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Data Cleaning
<ul>
<li>Missing Values (in progress)</li>
<li>Outliers</li>
<li>Box Cox Transformation</li>
<li>Stationary</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Univariate Models
<ul>
<li>ARIMA</li>
<li>Exponential Smoothing</li>
<li>Simple Benchmark Models</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Evaluation Metrics</li>
<li>Feature Engineering
<ul>
<li>Date</li>
<li>Target Variable</li>
<li>External Regressors</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Multivariate Models
<ul>
<li>Local Models</li>
<li>Global Models</li>
<li>Hyperparameter Tuning</li>
<li>Linear Regression</li>
<li>Decision Trees</li>
<li>Random Forest</li>
<li>Gradient Boosting (XGBoost, LightGBM)</li>
<li>Feature Selection</li>
<li>Mutlistep Horizon, Autoregressive</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Model Training Lifecycle
<ul>
<li>Train/Test Splits</li>
<li>Time Series Cross Validation</li>
<li>Evaluation Metrics</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Hierarchical Forecasting
<ul>
<li>Standard Hierarchy</li>
<li>Grouped Hierarchy</li>
<li>Clustering</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Combining Models
<ul>
<li>Simple Averages</li>
<li>Weighted Averaged</li>
<li>Ensemble Models</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Prediction Intervals</li>
<li>Model Interpretability
<ul>
<li>Model Specific</li>
<li>Model Agnostic
<ul>
<li>Global Methods</li>
<li>Local Methods</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Forecasts in Production
<ul>
<li>Parallel Computing</li>
<li>Model Training and Serving</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Appendix
<ul>
<li>ML Term Glossary</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>machine-learning</category>
  <category>time-series</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-25-ts-fundamentals/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-25-ts-fundamentals/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My Path from Finance Intern to Senior Software Engineer at Microsoft</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-04-sde-career-path/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-04-sde-career-path/image.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>I write code every day as a senior software engineer at Microsoft. But I didn’t use to. When I came to Microsoft as an intern in summer 2015, I was just your ordinary finance intern. The only code I knew was excel formulas. During the summer I realized the power of data+code and made it my mission to figure it out.</p>
<p>I have previously written about my journey in <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-02-19-frp-journey/">Microsoft’s Finance Rotation Program (FRP)</a>. That details the first half of my career and how I got my first engineering job, but not what I do today as a senior software engineer. Most of my time is spent on building and operating machine learning systems used by others across the finance organization. It’s been a hard journey, but also a fun one. If you’re like me and are interested in making the switch, here are some pieces of advice that might help you. Like all advice, take it with a grain of salt. Advice is like getting last years winning lottery numbers. They might have worked for that person in the past, but it may not work for you. Anyways I hope you find it helpful.</p>
<section id="focus-on-slope-over-intercept" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="focus-on-slope-over-intercept">Focus on Slope over Intercept</h3>
<p>When I came back as a full time employee after my internship, I kept seeing these new signs everywhere talking about something called a <a href="https://hbr.org/2016/01/what-having-a-growth-mindset-actually-means">“growth mindset”</a>. During my internship these words were never mentioned. Now they are taped to every blank wall on campus. What’s going on? Microsoft’s CEO, Satya Nadella, was in the midst of working on a culture shift at the company. Trying to go from employees that were “know it alls” to a more improved “learn it all”. This new attitude was perfect for me because I knew jack squat about coding, and I wanted to learn.</p>
<p>If you want to pivot your career into software engineering, there are two ways to go about it. The first and most common is to go to school and get a degree. The second is to figure it out on your own, aka the learn it yourself path. Both paths have their pros and cons. Going to school is the more direct path, but self-learning may have a different kind of benefit. If you’ve only ever learned how to code on your own, then you are setting yourself up for lifelong learning. As opposed to someone who went to school, who is used to classroom learning. The learning never stops once you start coding for money, so having the skill to learn proactively and not on a predetermined schedule is a super power.</p>
<p>Having technical knowledge from school puts you ahead of someone else who is just starting to learn on their own. But if that self-taught person is learning at a pace higher than the school smart person, eventually their trajectories will cross and the self-taught coder will surpass them. Think of it like a graph. Where school knowledge gives you a high Y intercept, a good starting point, but the rate of your learning every day after is the slope. The most important thing is to focus on the slope over the intercept.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-04-sde-career-path/image2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The learning never stops. In fact it only get’s harder. Not the learning itself (maybe it does), but taking the time to learn. Build the habit now, stay curious. The biggest trap is getting into the mindset of “I’ll start learning new things again once current xyz thing cools down”. That thing might be a new job, getting married, having a kid. As your responsibilities grow in life, your free time shrinks in proportion. Make sure learning stays a priority.</p>
<p>A good way to learn on your own while having an existing job is to make the learning part of your job. If you want to learn more about AI technology, go tell your boss that you want to work on a project with AI that could help the team. I’m 100% positive you’re boss will say yes. Getting free engineering help is usually not turned down by anyone. We all need better software in our lives. Once your boss expects you to deliver on something, with a deadline, then that’s the healthy pressure needed to go out and learn the damn thing. In addition to signing up for project work you can also do the same for traditional learning through books, courses, and certifications. For me back in the day I told my boss I was going to finish a Microsoft sponsored course in data science by xyz date. Each month I would provide her updates on my progress. Finishing that course become one of my deliverables in my job. That allowed me to spend some time each day at work on learning, without feeling guilty because it was actually part of my job to learn. Make it part of your job and things become a lot easier. Compared to squeezing in a few minutes before or after work without telling anyone. If your upcoming performance review is tied to reading a few books and building a new thing for your team, you will have all the motivation you need to get it done.</p>
<p>If you can’t find any good projects on your team, look elsewhere. You could go help another team at your company that might need some coding help, or a local charity or organization you care about. Towards the end of my time in the FRP, I stumbled across a team at Microsoft called the <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/corporate-responsibility/airband-initiative?msockid=0aa1dafa17d06b740264ce5816656a0b">Airband Initiative</a>. This team is focused on growing internet access to communities all around the world. They needed some help crunching data from policy documents and with zero experience I was able to come join the team as a temporary resource to help them with this analytics project. I was free labor so they didn’t have anything to lose, but I had everything to gain. I got good experience with natural language processing and working with unstructured data. Eventually the project grew. I ended up presenting the whole thing to Microsoft’s chief data scientist and even got to showcase the work at the 2019 Internet Governance Forum in Berlin. Where all my expenses were paid. All because I spoke up and offered to help. The Airband team got help, I learned a ton, and become an international data traveler. Talk about a win-win-win.</p>
<p>Maybe you’re still in school, but want to pick up some coding skills. Go see if any student organizations need help analyzing data or updating their website. Maybe the Football team could use another hand at analyzing what plays work best on third down, or if the basketball team needs to play a smaller lineup to score more points. The coffee shop in your business school might need some help on seeing what kind of sales promotions bring in the most revenue. The opportunities are endless. And because you’re offering your services for free they will not turn you down.</p>
<p>Last thing I’ll say about learning is that I’ve seen too many people get a masters in data analytics, AI, computer science, etc. only to get a job post-school that does none of that. It’s a shame. Don’t settle. Don’t give up. Keep learning.</p>
</section>
<section id="real-coders-ship" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="real-coders-ship">Real Coders Ship</h3>
<p>Real coders don’t just take classes and read books. They ship, meaning they build stuff and put it out into the universe. My learning only started when I put the books down and started pulling real data and training real machine learning models. Projects that actually helped my team in my current job, even if that job wasn’t software engineering. Shipping 10 projects is more impressive than acing 10 classes.</p>
<p>Some people create a “portfolio” of projects and have it live on their GitHub. I don’t think that’s a good idea. Real work is messy, and is the best indicator of future performance to an employer. Projects in a portfolio allow you to control all the variables, which is not how the real world works.</p>
<p>You can have public GitHub repos that show as samples of your work. But they should not be sample projects. They should either be pieces of work that you applied in your real job made open source and accessible to others. Or side projects where you wanted to build something cool to help you in your personal life or another organization. For example if you built your own website for your wedding, and had the code in a GitHub repo for hiring managers to see your coding chops. Or you built a bot that constantly analyzes your fantasy football league’s waiver wire and automatically picks up the best players for you based on AI powered analysis. There are endless ideas. Get building. Go out and ship.</p>
</section>
<section id="ai-is-your-friend" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ai-is-your-friend">AI is Your Friend</h3>
<p>In this post ChatGPT era, all technical work becomes 100x easier to learn. You don’t need school, or even books. You can, for free, start using a large language model (LLM) to learn coding concepts and even have it ask you technical questions to test your learning.</p>
<p>ChatGPT and other tools like GitHub Copilot now become your coding buddy, always there to help you when you get stuck or don’t know how to do something. Any new kid on the coding block can now get up to speed on languages like Python quickly because they have a personal AI tutor available 24/7. Go pay for a few of these AI services, and use them every day.</p>
</section>
<section id="use-your-competitive-advantage" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="use-your-competitive-advantage">Use Your Competitive Advantage</h3>
<p>Some people feel like coming into software engineering from a nontechnical discipline is a major handicap. I actually think it’s a superpower. If you come from a business background you actually have something other engineers do not. Business domain knowledge combined with technical knowledge is a deadly combination. You now understand both sides of the coin. You know how to make decisions about the business (through the lens of marketing, finance, sales) and can now go and build things that improve how the business serves customers.</p>
<p>For me having a finance background first, then learning coding second was a good combination. It created a lot of skills that are now invaluable. For example the skill of communicating things in simple terms. When I was building machine learning solutions for finance users, no one cared about the sophistication about my model or how much feature engineering I applied to the data. They just wanted to know how the solution ran at a high level and if it actually worked by showing improvements in a certain metric. For example, creating a more accurate revenue forecast for a Microsoft product. I’ve seen traditional data scientists/engineers try to explain their work to regular people and it can sometimes be like nails on a chalkboard. It’s painful to watch because they cannot explain themselves in plain english. And if the end user can’t understand how something works, then they won’t trust it, which means they won’t use it.</p>
<p>Usually being 80% competent at two skills can create more impact than being 99% competent in a single skill. Focus on <a href="https://personalexcellence.co/blog/talent-stack/">combining skills</a>. If you can build and you can sell, you will be unstoppable.</p>
</section>
<section id="baby-steps-not-one-giant-leap" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="baby-steps-not-one-giant-leap">Baby Steps, Not One Giant Leap</h3>
<p>Don’t go and build the next social networking app on your first coding project. Crawl, walk, then run with new technology. Here is a good workflow for learning progression.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Crawl: Get some code working on your computer.</li>
<li>Walk: Move that code up into the cloud and have it run on a different machine that’s not yours.</li>
<li>Run: Build a production ready system with proper CI/CD, unit testing, version control, etc.</li>
</ol>
<p>Those steps can take years, and that’s ok. You might even get a software engineering job with just knowledge of #1. But as you progress you will eventually figure out #2 and #3. The same can be said for the actual job progression.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Business Partner: You are the business person who works with the engineers.</li>
<li>Program Manager: Now you are the person in the middle between the business partner and the software engineer. This is an engineering role, and in some companies like Microsoft your compensation will be the same as a software engineer.</li>
<li>Software Engineer: You now build things, in collaboration with the program manager who tells you what the business partner needs.</li>
</ol>
<p>Going from business partner, to program manager, to software engineer is a lot easier than skipping directly to software engineer. When I graduated the FRP my first role title was “IT Solution Manager”. I still don’t know what that means. Overall I was basically a program manager that coded on the side when no one was looking. Eventually that side coding turned into real solutions I pitched to my manager and got into production. Which eventually led me to working solely on building things. Then I finally got the title of software engineer. It didn’t happen overnight, but it was possible.</p>
</section>
<section id="getting-promoted" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="getting-promoted">Getting Promoted</h3>
<p>Ok so maybe you now have a sweet engineering gig. Now what? How do you grow your career? Let’s talk about getting promoted.</p>
<p>You get promoted when what you build has impact. Not just for building cool or complex things. Most impact with technology can boil down to a few things.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Time savings</li>
<li>Money savings</li>
<li>Increasing revenue</li>
</ol>
<p>You work needs to boil down to numbers. Not what you shipped but what happened after you shipped it. Most impact is money and time. Either saving it or getting more of it. <strong>What gets measured gets managed. What gets measured gets promoted.</strong> Training a deep learning model is cool but shipping a simple linear regression in half the time might get you promoted twice as fast. Everyone is in sales. Once you build it, you have to sell it. If you can build and sell, you will be unstoppable. Ask your boss what you need to do this year to get promoted, then do those things. Ruthlessly prioritize and execute. Ignore everything else.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>
<p>Learning to code is important. Life is all about leverage. The best types of leverage in the world are permissionless leverage. They have no marginal costs of replication. These are things like code and content (podcasts, blog posts, etc.). Why do you think I wrote this? Because this kind of content has leverage, meaning it can scale. It’s easier to write this once then to give the same advice to 100 people who ask for it. Save your keystrokes folks. That’s why this personal blog exists. Hopefully it’s helpful to you my dear reader 😊.</p>
<p>Pretty soon everyone will be a manager, just not managing people. You will manage AI people, or bots/agents, who will do your work for you. Knowing how technology works will help you grow your leverage, whether you’re a software engineer or not. Most things 50 years from now will boil down to AI doing the thinking plus executing digital tasks, and robots executing physical tasks. What do you think those run on? You guessed it, code. Software will eat the entire world, it’s just a matter of time. I’d rather be giving our robot overlords instructions then taking instructions from them. Everyone will have a choice. Take the red pill. Go all the way down the rabbit hole. Learn some code.</p>
<p>Last thing I’ll say is that it takes guts to move to a new field. People who only do what their boss tells them to do will never have the guts to do it. It takes a certain amount of high agency to do it. If you’re considering or are already in the process of doing it, I salute you. The world needs more people like you. Good luck!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>finance</category>
  <category>career</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-04-sde-career-path/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-04-sde-career-path/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
