<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Thoughts on Things</title>
<link>https://mftokic.github.io/</link>
<atom:link href="https://mftokic.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A collection of thoughts on things from the mind of Mike Tokic</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.57</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>We Learn Best By Doing, Not By Studying</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-19-projects/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Have you ever wanted to grow your career at work? What did you do? Most likely you took on a tough new project that would force you to learn new skills to get the work done. The project put healthy pressure on you to gain those skills, all because your manager was counting on you to get it done. A good project builds on existing knowledge, but also forces you to grow in areas that make you better. It’s that sweet spot of flow. Not too easy, but also not too hard.</p>
<p><strong>If that’s how adults learn in the real world, why don’t kids do the same thing?</strong></p>
<p>How you learn in school is completely different than how you learn on the job.</p>
<p>School Based Learning</p>
<ul>
<li>Read books</li>
<li>Classroom lectures in groups of 20+ people</li>
<li>Take tests to prove knowledge</li>
<li>Knowledge is siloed, you learn math then science then social studies separately</li>
<li>Everything is paced at a specific speed</li>
<li>No control over what you want to learn, if you hate your classes you just need to suck it up and power through them</li>
</ul>
<p>Work Based Learning</p>
<ul>
<li>Learn 1n1 from managers, mentors, and teammates</li>
<li>Finish projects to prove knowledge</li>
<li>Projects combine many skills into one problem to work on</li>
<li>No pacing, advance your career as fast or as slow as you desire</li>
<li>Choose your own adventure for what you want to learn, if you hate your job you get a new job</li>
</ul>
<p>Kids are on these artificial train tracks for 22 years of their life, then all of a sudden they are ripped off and thrown into the wild west once they start their careers. What if they started work based learning sooner? Maybe even from day one?</p>
<p>The hardest part of work based, aka project based, learning is scaling the 1n1 aspect. This is where AI comes in. AI is quickly becoming the smartest thing in the world, which means it can be the best teacher in the world at anything. Kids in rural India will have the same access to AI as trust fund kids in New York City. It will be the great equalizer in education.</p>
<p>What if kids were allowed to learn what they wanted, when they wanted? Project based learning can truly be a choose your own adventure while still covering most of the basics of what every kid needs to know. A kid could probably learn calculus before the age of 12 if they truly loved math. Why slow them down with traditional pacing of going from first grade, to second grade, to third grade, etc. This becomes supercharged with AI.</p>
<p>Large language models like GPT-4o from OpenAI can tailor education to each student based on what they like doing the most. If a kid loves F1 racing then imagine learning about the chemistry of racing fuel, the physics of aerodynamic cars, even to how racers build their personal brands to reach millions. That kid will learn 100x faster doing that than reading out of a standard textbook and taking a standard test.</p>
<p><strong>We learn best by doing, not by studying.</strong></p>
<p>In a new AI world, it doesn’t make sense to study flashcards when the smartest thing in the world are AI models that everyone will eventually access for free. Being the best at remembering stuff is not a competitive advantage in a new AI first world. Instead AI should be teaching kids through projects that they’re the most interested in. People impact the world by doing things they love, so why not have kids build that sense of agency around doing interesting things while learning along the way as early as possible?</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>learning</category>
  <category>school</category>
  <category>AI</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-19-projects/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-19-projects/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="96" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Weekend Reads (4/18/25)</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-18-weekend-reads/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="articles" class="level2">

<ul>
<li><a href="https://blog.samaltman.com/productivity">Sam Altman’s Productivity Tips</a>
<ul>
<li>The best way to be productive is knowing what to work on. The right thing done at the wrong time yields zero results. So make sure you really think through the work you choose to do each day.</li>
<li>Sam ruthlessly prioritizes. Writing his priorities on paper each day.</li>
<li>He has long blocks of uninterrupted time in his schedule, even as the CEO of OpenAI. If he can do it, we all can.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/04/12/cofertility-lets-women-freeze-their-eggs-for-free-through-its-donor-matching-program/">New Company Allows You To Freeze Your Eggs For Free</a>
<ul>
<li>Cofertility’s radical model for women: Freeze your eggs for free by donating half of them.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://ryanholiday.net/these-are-leadership-ideas-i-try-to-apply-every-day/">Ryan Holiday’s Leadership Philosophy</a>
<ul>
<li>This is a great list of leadership lessons and approaches to being a good boss. Here are a few that stood out to me.
<ul>
<li>Sense of urgency: You can either get that project done next week or next month. Both ways will produce the same result.</li>
<li>Don’t touch paper twice: You can only keep so many “open tabs” in your head. Make decisions and work on things only once, don’t keep them all running in your head constantly.<br>
</li>
<li>I’m leaving this with you: Bring problems for employees to solve and get the hell out of the way. Don’t let them bring the monkey and place it on your back again.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://www.approachwithalacrity.com/101-things-for-my-past-self/">101 Things I’d Tell Myself From 10 Years Ago</a>
<ul>
<li>Giving advice to our past self is a great exercise, even better if we pretend to be in the future and give advice to our current self. Here are a few that stood out to me.
<ul>
<li>Write more on the internet to increase your luck surface area.</li>
<li>Don’t fall in love with something that can’t love you back. Companies do not spend a week crying when you break up with them.</li>
<li>Your inbound opportunities are worse than the ones you carefully select and nurture over time. This is true both if you are an engineer looking for a job and if you are a 19-year-old girl looking for someone to date.</li>
<li>You should aim to produce things at about a 1:10 ratio to how much you consume them. This is true of food, videos, internet comments and parties.</li>
<li>Consider deleting as often as you consider adding. This holds true for code, furniture and obligations.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="videos" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="videos">Videos</h2>
<ul>
<li>Priming Your Brain
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=60ROjGMqXUQ">How Priming Works</a>
<ul>
<li>Tony Robbins talks about how marketers and bad actors use the concept of priming on you in bad ways. But we can also personally use priming on ourselves in good ways.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=faTGTgid8Uc">Priming Exercise</a>
<ul>
<li>15 minute priming exercise from one of Tony’s events.</li>
<li>Try this in place of your morning breathwork/meditation and start your day off with a bang.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UyneMnERmnI">Dr.&nbsp;Mark Hyndman on Andrew Huberman</a>
<ul>
<li>Mark discusses the need for supplementation, the role of medical testing for proper health, and how newer treatments like peptides can help improve vitality.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2teuwjThdSI">AI for Humans</a>
<ul>
<li>Latest OpenAI developments, new state of the art AI video models, and google AI trying to talk to dolphins.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/nhC8lLPpGl4?si=Fkzhx5kNEJ0aOu6L">Gary Breka on Joe Rogan</a>
<ul>
<li>How hydrogen water can change your life and a thousand crazy other biohacks Gary does every day.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="products" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="products">Products</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://nucalm.com/">NuCalm App</a>
<ul>
<li>Uses specific frequencies via headphones to deliver 2 hours of deep sleep in 20 min, in additional to other tracks for focus and creativity.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>weekend-reads</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-18-weekend-reads/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-18-weekend-reads/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="96" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Weekend Reads (4/11/25)</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-11-weekend-reads/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="articles" class="level2">

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/home/home-page-topic/reader/microsoft-original-source-code">50 Years of Microsoft</a>
<ul>
<li>Bill Gates reflects on Microsoft’s 50-year journey, tracing its origins from Altair BASIC to its transformative innovations in technology.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://paulgraham.com/do.html">What to Do</a>
<ul>
<li>Paul Graham explores the fundamental question of what one should do in life, concluding that beyond helping people and caring for the world, creating “good new things” is a vital pursuit.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://julian.digital/2025/03/27/the-case-against-conversational-interfaces/">The Case Against Conversational Interfaces</a>
<ul>
<li>Julian refutes the hype around conversational interfaces, arguing that natural language is inefficient for human-computer interaction.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://www.anthropic.com/research/tracing-thoughts-language-model">Tracing the Thoughts of a LLM</a>
<ul>
<li>Research from Anthropic about how models like Claude think through problems.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/HJeD6XbMGEfcrx3mD/100-ways-to-live-better">100 Ways to Live Better</a>
<ul>
<li>Sage advice about living.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/6Xgy6CAf2jqHhynHL/what-2026-looks-like">What 2026 Looks Like</a>
<ul>
<li>A scary good prediction about AI advancement from back in 2021 (pre ChatGPT).</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/deesrjitvXM4xYGZd/metr-measuring-ai-ability-to-complete-long-tasks">AI’s Ability to Complete Tasks Doubles Every Seven Months</a>
<ul>
<li>Data showing the exponential curve of how fast AI is being able to do complex tasks.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://ai-2027.com/">AI in 2027</a>
<ul>
<li>Freaky but well reasoned forecast of how AI will grow in the next few years. They state AI will replace all human code by 2027.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="videos" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="videos">Videos</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KyfUysrNaco">Naval Ravikant on Modern Wisdom</a>
<ul>
<li>Discusses various aspects of human nature, including how to find success and happiness, develop self-esteem, manage emotions, and make wise decisions. He emphasizes the importance of authenticity, focusing on what you truly enjoy, and avoiding distractions like status games and excessive rumination. He also touches on broader societal issues like the future of technology and culture wars.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="books" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="books">Books</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/5IRSuUd">Genghis Khan and the Making of the Modern World by Jack Weatherford</a>
<ul>
<li>The insane story of the Mongol empire. It only gets crazier the more you read.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/fMBQ1al">Life Force by Tony Robbins</a>
<ul>
<li>How advancements in technology are reversing aging.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://a.co/d/6ZirXdX">Die Trying (Jack Reacher) by Lee Child</a>
<ul>
<li>Jack Reacher is the american James Bond, need I say more?</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="code" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="code">Code</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://huggingface.co/spaces/adyen/DABstep">Data Analysis Agent Leaderboard on HuggingFace</a>
<ul>
<li>List of best performing AI agents in data analysis. Interesting how the best one currently has to coax the AI with monetary rewards of one millions bucks in its system prompt.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-08328-6?utm_campaign=The%20Batch&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;_hsenc=p2ANqtz-93ONGUz0xKduAMcOVXpRLAmMn-Uc9CXRbkVfEdnGBRtvXKLoYK9eNNR_F4oEY1i1DEf7c9P5RDk7jleFe97UBDMUx_UI7BUAfp-AhP-1YVgEwrTMA&amp;_hsmi=355982825&amp;utm_content=355982825&amp;utm_source=hs_email">Transformer Model for Tabular Data</a>
<ul>
<li>Interesting new model that is like a LLM but for tabular data. Most models from OpenAI and Anthropic cannot work on data that lives in an excel spreadsheet, this model can.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="products" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="products">Products</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.hapbee.com/products/hapbee-neckband">Hapbee Neckband</a>
<ul>
<li>This wearable uses electromagnetic fields pioneered by the Navy to create the effects of coffee, alcohol, melatonin, and various other compounds without the side effects or dependence of them. Sounds like magic, but it’s just science.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>weekend-reads</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-11-weekend-reads/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-11-weekend-reads/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="96" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Univariate Models: ARIMA</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-10-ts-fundamentals-univariate-arima/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>This post is part of the <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-24-ts-fundamentals-univariate-models/">univariate models chapter</a> within a larger learning series around time series forecasting fundamentals. <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-25-ts-fundamentals/">Check out the main learning path</a> to see other posts in the series.</em></p>
<p><em>The example monthly data used in this series <a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/posts/2024-10-02-ts-fundamentals-whats-a-time-series/example_ts_data.csv">can be found here.</a> You can also find the <a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/notebooks/2025-04-10-ts-fundamentals-univariate-arima.ipynb">python code used in this post here.</a></em></p>
<section id="lets-break-arima-down" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lets-break-arima-down">Let’s Break ARIMA Down</h3>
<p>Arima stands for autoregressive integrated moving average. That sounds like a mouthful so we’ll take it step by step on how each component works.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>AR (AutoRegressive)</strong>: The current value depends on past values of itself</li>
<li><strong>I (Integrated)</strong>: Difference the data to make it <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-21-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-stationary/">stationary</a></li>
<li><strong>MA (Moving Average)</strong>: The current value depends on past prediction errors</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="putting-it-all-together" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="putting-it-all-together">Putting it All Together</h3>
<p>Here’s what happens when an arima model is trained.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Integrated</strong>: Difference the data d times to remove trend or seasonality, making the series stationary. This is necessary so that the AR and MA components can model the structure reliably.</li>
<li><strong>Autoregressive</strong>: Model the differenced series as a linear combination of its own lagged values. This captures momentum or persistence in the time series aka how past values influence future ones.</li>
<li><strong>Moving Average</strong>: Model the current value as a function of past forecast errors. These errors are not directly observed, so the model estimates them recursively during training, learning how random shocks in the past influence the present.</li>
<li><strong>Training</strong>: The AR and MA parts are fitted together by maximizing the likelihood of the observed data, given the model structure. This involves recursively computing residuals and using numerical optimization to find the best parameters.</li>
</ol>
<p>To create future forecasts, we’d take the trained model and do the following.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Autoregressive</strong>: Predict differenced values using past observations (or predictions) via the AR terms.</li>
<li><strong>Moving Average</strong>: Refine predictions using known or assumed residual errors from past forecasts.</li>
<li><strong>Recursive Forecasting</strong>: Forecast multiple steps ahead by reusing your own predictions as inputs.</li>
<li><strong>Integrated</strong>: Reverse the differencing operation to return the forecast to the original scale.</li>
</ol>
<p>Ok, now we know how arima works at a high level and how it can be used to create future forecasts. But there’s one major thing missing. The arima process we went through is for non-seasonal data. If our data has seasonality, we need to fit a seasonal arima model. It’s very similar to the plain vanilla arima model, but has a separate process added to handle seasonal differencing and seasonal lags. For example instead of comparing sales of last month to sales in this month, a seasonal approach would compare sales of 12 months ago with sales in this month. It’s kind of like stacking another arima on top of arima, but operating at a seasonal level.</p>
</section>
<section id="lets-train-a-model" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lets-train-a-model">Let’s Train a Model</h3>
<p>Let’s take one of our example time series and create an arima forecast 12 months into the future and see how things look.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-10-ts-fundamentals-univariate-arima/chart1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Looks pretty good! The arima model was able to capture the historical trend and seasonality and carry it forward into the future. We’re also able to see two other things in the chart.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Hypothetical forecasts of the training data. These are often referred to as fitted values and can be used to calculate residuals, which are simply the difference between the forecast and actual value. Historically the arima model performed very well, closely matching the actual revenue values from month to month.</li>
<li>A 95% prediction interval. This represents with 95% certainty the upper and lower ranges where the model thinks the future value will land between. The tighter this interval the more certain the model is in its prediction. We will dig deep into prediction intervals in more detail in a later post.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="reversal" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reversal">Reversal</h3>
<p>Arima is a cornerstone of every forecasters toolbox, but it does come with some drawbacks.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Assumes linearity of the data</strong> since it learns linear patters in previous data, which may not work well if the data has non-linear patterns.</li>
<li><strong>Not the best at long term forecasting.</strong> Sometimes an arima model can converge to the mean of the data or a constant value over a long enough forecast horizon. This removes any kind of trend or seasonality the data might possess.</li>
<li><strong>Finding the right parameters</strong> (number of differencing, AR and MA values) is not always optimal</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>
<p>Arima is one of the most foundational models in time series forecasting. Not because it’s perfect, but because it’s interpretable, fast to train, and often surprisingly effective for short-term, univariate forecasting problems. It gives us a solid mental model for thinking about time series structure: trends, momentum, and noise.</p>
<p>That said, arima models come with limitations. They assume linearity, can struggle with longer horizons, and require a stationary signal to be effective. One particularly important limitation is that arima only looks at the past values of the target variable. It doesn’t account for external factors like promotions, weather, or economic indicators unless you explicitly modify the model to include them.</p>
<p>We’ll look at ways to incorporate external regressors into time series models soon, but understanding how arima works in isolation is the right starting point. If you can reason through the arima process step by step, you’re building a strong foundation for more powerful forecasting techniques down the road.</p>
</section>
<section id="learn-more" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="learn-more">Learn More</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://otexts.com/fpp3/arima.html">Forecasting Principles and Practice</a> by Rob Hyndman</li>
<li><a href="https://nixtlaverse.nixtla.io/statsforecast/docs/models/autoarima.html">AutoARIMA Model</a> from Nixtla’s StatsForecast Python Package</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>machine-learning</category>
  <category>time-series</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-10-ts-fundamentals-univariate-arima/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-10-ts-fundamentals-univariate-arima/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Secret to Growing Faster Than the Stock Market</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-08-compound-yourself/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="lets-play-a-game" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lets-play-a-game">Let’s Play A Game</h3>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Compound interest is the eighth wonder of the world. He who understands it, earns it; he who doesn’t, pays it.”</p>
<p>— <em>Albert Einstein</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>You have two options, choose wisely.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>You are given a million dollars a day for the rest of your life</li>
<li>You are given a penny today, but each subsequent day the value doubles</li>
</ol>
<p>Which one would you pick? Most humans understand linear returns, but not everyone understands compound returns. For option one, you’d have $365 million dollars at the end of a year. Sounds pretty good! What about option two?</p>
<ul>
<li>After 7 days: $1.27, basically nothing</li>
<li>After 30 days: $10 million, wow that’s great but still trailing option one</li>
<li>After 36 days: $365 million, same as option one</li>
<li>After 365 days: 7.52 × 10¹⁰⁷, basically more money than the world has ever seen</li>
</ul>
<p>Option two doesn’t start out sexy but in the end creates untold return. That’s how most things operate in life. Something starts off slow, barely trickles along for a while, then all of a sudden get’s escape velocity and rockets upwards. This is often called “hockey stick” growth, because it looks just like a hock stick with a flat line turning into one that shoots straight up.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-08-compound-yourself/chart1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="the-greatest-returns-always-come-at-the-end" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-greatest-returns-always-come-at-the-end">The Greatest Returns Always Come At The End</h3>
<p>For those who do understand the power of compounding, or do now after reading this, their mindset around it is most likely tied to financial markets. Few think about how compounding can be applied to so many other aspects of life.</p>
<ul>
<li>Career</li>
<li>Intelligence</li>
<li>Health</li>
<li>Relationships</li>
</ul>
<p>If you had $100 to invest today, would you invest it in the S&amp;P 500 index, containing the largest american companies, or invest it in yourself? I think most people understand the earlier you invest in the financial markets, the greater the return. But few understand this for investing in yourself.</p>
<p>The average american lifespan is 79 years. A $100 invested in the S&amp;P 500 index 79 years ago would today be valued at $473,355. That sounds crazy right! But it’s just the math of compounding. That equals around a 11.4% annual growth of the investment each year (compound annual growth rate). That CAGR of 11.4% doesn’t sound as sexy as a 473,254% total return over the period. Because the time horizon was so long, a yearly return of 11.4% can really start to add up over the years.</p>
<p>How much of the ending amount of ~$500k was created in the first few years compared to the last few years? This is where the <em>math</em> really gets <em>mathing</em>.</p>
<ul>
<li>First 64 years (1947-2010): creates 20% of end investment gain</li>
<li>Last 15 years (2011-2025): creates 80% of end investment gain</li>
</ul>
<p>This proves that showing up every day and sticking it out for the long haul can create the most investment return. If you are already investing in the stock market and are sitting back to let compounding do its magic, good for you. But are you compounding other parts of your life?</p>
<p><strong>My main point in this post is that it’s easier to compound yourself faster than the S&amp;P 500</strong> return of 11.4% per year. You are capable of doubling the value in yourself each year, which brings you closer to the untold returns of option two of our thought experiment.</p>
</section>
<section id="compounding-life-slows-down-as-we-age" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="compounding-life-slows-down-as-we-age">Compounding Life Slows Down As We Age</h3>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Many people die at twenty-five and aren’t buried until they are seventy-five.”</p>
<p>— <em>Benjamin Franklin</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The first quarter of life is spent in personal compounding mode. You start out at zero when born, then slowly rise through the ranks. Each year what you learn not just doubles but may even 10x on a month to month basis. Going from your first word, to speaking full sentences, to writing and reading is a true hockey stick growth pattern. Same goes for math, emotions, and understanding others in the world around you.</p>
<p>After you finish school (undergraduate college) and get a few years of work under your belt I think our level of compounding falls off. You are still growing as a person, but not as fast as you once did. Instead of measuring changes in 1-4 year increments you now compare yourself through different decades in your life. You go from saying “back in college” (four year span) to “back in my 20s” or “in my 30s” (10 year span). This level of compounding is now more closely tied to what you can get out of the S&amp;P 500. But I think life doesn’t have to be this way. We can continue to compound ourselves through learning and personal growth at a fast clip forever. The perfect example is Warren Buffet and Charlie Munger. They have been kicking ass well into their 90s, with most of their success coming after turning 60.</p>
<p>Morgan Housel in his book <a href="https://a.co/d/iKWJfEd">The Psychology of Money</a> tells a powerful story about a man named Ronald Read. Ronald was a janitor and gas station attendant for his entire life. When he died at 92, he had over $8,000,000 in stock investments that were quietly compounding for decades. This money was donated to hospitals and libraries in his town, making him a celebrity after his death.</p>
<p>After reading a story like Ronald’s you may have one of the following thoughts.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Wow that guy did investing right, this proves that anyone can save money to build wealth.</li>
<li>Why didn’t he use some of that money to live a better life than being a janitor, like vacationing in europe every summer?</li>
<li><strong>Why was he a janitor his entire life!</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>Ronald was able to compound his investments, but not his career. Who knows, maybe he crushed it at every aspect of life and just enjoyed being a janitor. All power to him. But it’s just surprising to see a man so good at compounding money not doing the same to compound himself in other areas of life.</p>
<p>With the exception of people like Ronald, most people who are deemed successful by society can continue to compound their career or investments at a fast rate through the first half of life, but often at the expense of other areas like health and relationships. We’ve all seen tech founders who are kings of the world, but are obese or divorced. They have compounded two aspects of their life, money and career, but not other important areas that make life worth living.</p>
<p>Once people hit their 60s, almost everything in their life stops compounding for good, and starts compounding in a bad way. Their health starts to decline, they have less friends, they see their children/family less, and they quit their career altogether aka retire. Things decline for 20-30 years until they die. Wow that sucks, and I don’t think it has to be this way.</p>
<p>Advancements in technology and medicine will allow us to start living past 100 with ease, this creates more runway for us to compound ourselves. Why retire at 65 if you still feel like your in your 30s with limitless energy? If the power of compounding comes in the last few years, shouldn’t we ramping up our lives after 60 than slowing them down?</p>
<p>We all need to think more about how we can continue to compound ourselves in every aspect in life, not just money.</p>
<ul>
<li>Money</li>
<li>Career</li>
<li>Intelligence</li>
<li>Health</li>
<li>Relationships</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="compounding-intelligence-and-health" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="compounding-intelligence-and-health">Compounding Intelligence and Health</h3>
<p><strong>Most people seem to be pretty bad at compounding intelligence and health once they hit 30. Some say 30 is their peak for health, which if you want to live past 100 that’s like saying you peaked in high school.</strong> There is so much more life to live. Every one needs to continue learning and applying that knowledge (aka intelligence) to make their life better. Same goes for health. It’s much easier to be healthy at 80 if your were healthy at 60, and especially if you were healthy at 30. Small things compound remember?</p>
<p>Compounding intelligence and health often takes money. Buying books, measuring your blood, or talking to experts all cost money. Some people would rather buy a porsche than a red light bed, but only one of those is going to change your cellular biology for the better. What if taking $500 in supplements each month allows you to feel 50% better and get 20% more work done in your job? Maybe that allows you to get a promotion 50% faster or have 20% more quality time with your kids? Is it a better investment than putting that $500 in the S&amp;P 500? Maybe…it depends how fast you can make that money compound. Most things we buy (cars, clothes, Netflix) have no compound returns. Possibly negative returns. So make sure you spend your money on the right things.</p>
</section>
<section id="compounding-relationships" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="compounding-relationships">Compounding Relationships</h3>
<p>Relationships also take a hit after 30. People get married, have kids, and continue to climb the corporate ladder. That removes all available time to invest into the friends and family around you. I call this the <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-06-28-life-circles/">“inner circles of life”</a>, where each stage in life your priorities change. Even as your priorities change, having quality relationships that compound over decades is a good investment. <a href="https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2017/04/over-nearly-80-years-harvard-study-has-been-showing-how-to-live-a-healthy-and-happy-life/">Quality relationships</a> literally make you live longer. <strong>Keep those childhood friendships going. They’re like a garden, you need to tend to them every year or they will starve and die.</strong></p>
</section>
<section id="compounding-failure" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="compounding-failure">Compounding = Failure</h3>
<p>Ok, maybe by now you are on board the “let’s compound everything for life” train, but how? <strong>Failure is the best way to compound yourself.</strong> Malcolm Gladwell says it takes 10,000 hours to master a skill. But others like Naval Ravikant say that it actually takes 10,000 iterations. Not repetitions, but instead trying to do something, failing, and iterating in the next attempt. That’s how children learn everything, but as we get older we shy away from being wrong. Being wrong in public is our worst nightmare, but often that’s the best way to improve.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>
<p>Compounding isn’t just math, it’s a life strategy. Unlike traditional investments, investing in yourself offers infinite returns. Simple, consistent actions like reading, exercising, or nurturing relationships quietly compound into massive growth over time.</p>
<p>The real power of compounding lies in its subtlety. It starts small, barely noticeable, but steadily builds momentum until you’re amazed by the results. Remember, life isn’t about financial gain alone. It’s about intentionally growing every aspect (career, intelligence, health, relationships) to shape a fulfilling life.</p>
<p>Picture yourself at 100, still sharp, healthy, loved, wealthy, and living your greatest adventure yet because you never stopped compounding yourself. That reality starts today.</p>
<p><a href="https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-cDUWGJmWhhg/UQvjq4ydg5I/AAAAAAAA6yM/-n_19_RKSrM/s1600/30_rock_finale_jacks_happiness_domination_chart.jpg">Image Credit</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-08-compound-yourself/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-08-compound-yourself/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>March Learnings</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-04-march-learnings/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I love reading books, watching YouTube videos, listening to podcasts, you name it. Anything learning related is my jam. But I realized that if I don’t take notes on what I’m learning, I will probably forget everything. Now when I hear something interesting, I write it down in an Apple note for that month. Below are some of the learnings I jotted down in March, summarized by ChatGPT with additional context added by their new deep research feature. I hope you find them as interesting as I did.</p>
<section id="health-longevity" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-longevity">Health &amp; Longevity</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Alzheimer’s as “Type 3 Diabetes”</strong><br>
Some researchers now refer to Alzheimer’s disease as “type 3 diabetes” because it’s strongly linked to insulin resistance in the brain.<sup>1</sup> In essence, neurons become less responsive to insulin, which impairs memory and cognition—underscoring the huge role that blood sugar control plays in brain health.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Fasting—It Depends on Your A1C</strong><br>
Fasting isn’t one-size-fits-all. If your hemoglobin A1C (a marker of blood sugar) is already low (around 4.8–5.2%), aggressive fasting might stress your hormones (e.g., spiking cortisol and upsetting thyroid or sex hormones).<sup>2</sup>. But if your A1C is high, intermittent fasting can help—research shows it can reverse insulin resistance and even lower A1C levels.<sup>3</sup> The takeaway: people with high blood sugar may benefit from fasting, while those with normal/low A1C should be cautious not to overdo it.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Consistent Sleep &gt; Long Sleep</strong><br>
When it comes to sleep, consistency is king. Going to bed and waking up at the same time every day has a bigger impact on health than the total hours of sleep.<sup>4</sup> In fact, maintaining a regular sleep-wake schedule can add years to your life by aligning with your circadian rhythm.<sup>5</sup> It’s better to get, say, 6.5 hours every night reliably than 8 hours one night and 5 the next.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Mitochondria: The Root of Many Diseases</strong><br>
Many diseases boil down to broken mitochondria. These tiny energy producers, if they fail in a given tissue, cause that organ to struggle. Some experts say “mitochondrial dysfunction underlies the etiology of most common complex diseases, as well as aging”.<sup>6</sup> So protect your mitochondria through good nutrition, exercise, and reduced toxin exposure.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Autoimmune Diseases Hit Women Hardest</strong><br>
~80% of autoimmune disease patients are female.<sup>7</sup> This striking ratio could stem from hormones, genetic factors (many immune-related genes on the X chromosome), and even microbiome differences. Either way, it’s a reminder that women face unique health vulnerabilities and need specialized research and care.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Longevity “Power Rankings”</strong><br>
The most impactful factors for living longer (often into your 90s):</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Don’t smoke:</strong> Smoking knocks ~10 years off your life.<sup>8</sup></li>
<li><strong>Exercise regularly:</strong> At least 30 minutes of moderate activity daily. This can add years to your lifespan.<sup>9</sup></li>
<li><strong>Mediterranean diet:</strong> Linked to ~20–25% lower all-cause mortality.<sup>10</sup></li>
<li><strong>BMI of ~18–22:</strong> Excess fat is risky. The average American man has 28% body fat.<sup>11</sup></li>
<li><strong>Limit alcohol:</strong> Heavy drinking raises risk of cancers and liver disease.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Prioritize sleep:</strong> ~7–8 hours a night is linked to better longevity.<sup>12</sup></li>
</ol></li>
<li><p><strong>Navy Dolphins Live 3x Longer</strong><br>
Dolphins in the wild typically live ~20 years, but those raised by the U.S. Navy reach 40–60 years.<sup>13</sup> It’s a striking example of how consistent nutrition, healthcare, and a protected environment can dramatically extend longevity.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Humans Are Fatter Than Pigs</strong><br>
The average American man’s body fat is ~28%<sup>14</sup>, while modern farm pigs are ~16–20%. This reveals just how normalized overweight conditions have become in humans.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Half-Life of Medical Knowledge</strong><br>
The “half-life” of med school training is ~18–24 months.<sup>15</sup> That means half of what doctors learn becomes outdated within two years. Rapid research advances demand ongoing education.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="human-psychology-behavior" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="human-psychology-behavior">Human Psychology &amp; Behavior</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>“Language Sets Your Limits”</strong><br>
Echoing Ludwig Wittgenstein: if you lack words for certain ideas or emotions, you struggle to conceptualize them.<sup>16</sup> Expanding your vocabulary or learning new languages can literally expand the boundaries of your world.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Pretty Privilege &amp; Athlete Privilege</strong><br>
Society tends to give attractive women and elite male athletes a pass on bad behavior. Studies show attractive people receive more lenient treatment<sup>17</sup>, and star athletes often face fewer consequences.<sup>18</sup> Recognizing this bias can be the first step to correcting it.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Mormon Influencers &amp; Journaling Culture</strong><br>
The Church of Latter-day Saints encourages regular journaling and sharing of personal insights.<sup>19</sup> This cultural norm produces individuals who are comfortable with transparent storytelling—perfectly suited to be bloggers/vloggers, which may explain their disproportionate presence online.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Two Sides of a Pancake</strong><br>
An old saying: “No matter how thin a pancake, it has two sides.” It’s a simple but powerful reminder to consider multiple perspectives in conflicts or debates.<sup>20</sup></p></li>
<li><p><strong>A Habit Missed Twice Is a New Habit</strong><br>
Skip a good habit once, no big deal. Skip it twice, and you’re on your way to a new (bad) habit.<sup>21</sup> Consistency is the key—if you slip, correct course immediately.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="business-marketing-insights" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="business-marketing-insights">Business &amp; Marketing Insights</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Product vs.&nbsp;Marketing</strong><br>
Getting the product right is crucial, but achieving <em>escape velocity</em> for your business often hinges on marketing—specifically the stories you tell. A merely “okay” product with great storytelling can outsell a brilliant product with no marketing. The best scenario is both: a product people love and a compelling narrative.<sup>22</sup></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Grey Goose: A Branding Masterclass</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>France over Russia:</strong> Leveraged French luxury connotations.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Top-Shelf Pricing:</strong> 30% higher than the competition, creating a perception of high quality.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Tall Bottle Design:</strong> Forced bars to place it on the top shelf, cementing its premium status.<sup>23</sup><br>
A reminder that marketing—especially price, packaging, and provenance—can transform a commodity (vodka) into a billion-dollar brand.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Speak to an Audience of One</strong><br>
Narrow your focus to a single, ideal audience member, and your content becomes more personal, resonant, and effective. Ironically, by writing to “everyone,” you often connect with no one.<sup>24</sup></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Growth for Growth’s Sake = Cancer</strong><br>
Mindlessly chasing growth (in business or life) can be destructive. As Edward Abbey said, “growth for the sake of growth is the ideology of the cancer cell”.<sup>25</sup> Pursue meaningful growth with a purpose, not expansion at all costs.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="productivity-success" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="productivity-success">Productivity &amp; Success</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Learn to Say “No”</strong><br>
Successful people say no to almost everything, focusing on the select few activities that truly matter.<sup>26</sup> Time and energy are finite resources—guard them.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Take Simple Ideas Seriously</strong><br>
Complexity doesn’t guarantee success. Sometimes a simple idea, executed with extraordinary focus, can outshine more elaborate plans. Think of Amazon starting with just online book sales.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>The Hard Path Brings Happiness</strong><br>
The path of least resistance rarely leads to fulfillment. Progress—often uncomfortable—makes you happy.<sup>27</sup> Growth happens when you embrace challenges, not avoid them.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Grow or Die, Then Give</strong><br>
Feeling stuck? Commit to continuous growth—new skills, knowledge, or goals—so you have more to offer others. Giving back then fuels your sense of purpose.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Success Without Fulfillment = Failure</strong><br>
What’s the point of external “success” if you feel empty inside? True success should include joy and meaning.<sup>28</sup></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Timing Is Everything</strong><br>
Doing the right thing at the wrong time often yields zero results. Whether in business or life, <em>when</em> you act can matter as much as <em>what</em> you do.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Everything Is Networks</strong><br>
Your career, friendships, and opportunities revolve around the networks you enter and exit—schools, companies, regions, or social circles.<sup>29</sup> Being in the right network at the right time can change everything. Pick your networks wisely, and reciprocate value within them.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="raw-notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="raw-notes">Raw Notes</h2>
<details>
<summary>
Click to read the original notes.
</summary>
<ul>
<li>Alzheimer’s is type 3 diabetes or insulin resistance in the brain.</li>
<li>People with low A1C levels 4.8-5.2 should most likely not do fasting since it can mess up hormones. People who have high A1C should probably fast to help improve metabolic function.</li>
<li>Biggest impact on sleep is time you go to sleep and wake up every day. Being consistent is better than how much sleep you actually get.</li>
<li>Fleece contains microplastics, avoid them, especially after washing them which makes it worse.</li>
<li>You need to eat 25,000 calories a day in order to get all AMA daily requirements of nutrients. That’s how much a Rhino eats.</li>
<li>Successful people say no to most things, the most successful people say no to everything. Focus and a single priority is key.</li>
<li>Most GMO crops have been modified to resist certain pesticides that kill bugs but not the plant. Protects against glyphosates, which then get into our bodies and cause all kinds of damage.</li>
<li>Dolphins in the wild live around 20 years. Dolphins raised by the US Navy live up to 60 years old.</li>
<li>Most disease in our bodies are caused by mitochondria not working properly in that part of the body.</li>
<li>Language sets your limits.</li>
<li>80% of autoimmune disease happens in women.</li>
<li>People who can get away with any behavior in life: hot girls and male athletes.</li>
<li>How to live longer power rankings, allows you to live to 92
<ul>
<li>Don’t smoke, takes off 12 years</li>
<li>Exercise 6 hours a week</li>
<li>Mediterranean diet</li>
<li>BMI 18-22</li>
<li>No alcohol or limited booze</li>
<li>Sleep</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Everything you do is about joining and leaving networks.
<ul>
<li>School, companies, industries, cities, families. All types of networks.</li>
<li>Being part of the right one at the right time can change your life.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Getting the product right is the hardest part. But what gives you escape velocity on scaling your business is the right marketing. Which means the right words and stories that are told about your business and product.</li>
<li>Grey Goose was started by a man in his 70s who previously got rich off importing jagermeister into America
<ul>
<li>Wanted to get vodka from France instead of the standard Russia because it sounded fancier</li>
<li>Decided to charge 30% more than the current most expensive vodka at bars, which was Absolute vodka</li>
<li>Made it into a very tall bottle to make it stand apart from the short bottles of absolute, and because it would force bars to put it on the top shelf because it couldn’t fit anywhere else.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>There are a lot of Mormon influencers and media types because it’s part of their religion to journal and share insights to others.</li>
<li>Calories from liquid sugar are the single biggest cause of obesity in America.</li>
<li>All Atlantic salmon is farm raised. Always get wild Alaskan salmon</li>
<li>Content gets better when you speak to an audience of one</li>
<li>Take simple ideas but take them more seriously than anyone else.</li>
<li>A habit missed once is no big deal, a habit missed twice is the start of a new habit.</li>
<li>Growth for growths sake is the ideology of a cancer cell</li>
<li>No matter how thin a pancake, there’s always two sides</li>
<li>Avg American man 28% body fat, avg American pig 25% body fat</li>
<li>Half life of info learned in med school is 24 months</li>
<li>The path of least resistance never makes you happy.</li>
<li>Progress makes you happy. Take a step in the right direction every day. Grow or die. When you grow, you have something to give. And growing and giving makes you fulfilled.</li>
<li>Success without fulfillment is the ultimate failure</li>
<li>Doing the right thing at the wrong time yields zero results.</li>
</ul>
</details>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Alzheimer’s &amp; Insulin Resistance: Suzanne M. de la Monte &amp; Jack R. Wands (2008). <em>Is Alzheimer’s Disease Type 3 Diabetes?</em>. <em>Journal of Diabetes Science and Technology</em>, 2(6), 1101–1113.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Impact of Fasting on Low A1C: Varady, K. A., &amp; Hellerstein, M. K. (2007). <em>Alternate-day fasting and chronic disease prevention: a review of human and animal trials</em>. The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 86(1), 7–13.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Fasting &amp; Reversing Insulin Resistance: Fung, J. (2016). <em>The Obesity Code: Unlocking the Secrets of Weight Loss</em>. Greystone Books.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Sleep Consistency &amp; Mortality Risk: Huang, T., et al.&nbsp;(2020). <em>Habitual Sleep Variability and Risk of Cardiovascular Events and All-Cause Mortality</em>. JAMA Cardiology, 5(2), 161–169.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>Circadian Rhythm &amp; Longevity: Asher, G. &amp; Sassone-Corsi, P. (2015). <em>Time for Food: The Intimate Interplay between Nutrition, Metabolism, and the Circadian Clock</em>. Cell, 161(1), 84–92.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>Mitochondrial Dysfunction: Wallace, D. C. (2005). <em>A Mitochondrial Paradigm of Metabolic and Degenerative Diseases, Aging, and Cancer: A Dawn for Evolutionary Medicine</em>. Annual Review of Genetics, 39, 359–407.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn7"><p>Autoimmune &amp; Women: Fairweather, D., &amp; Rose, N. R. (2004). <em>Women and Autoimmunity</em>. Autoimmunity Reviews, 3(6), 457–462.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn8"><p>Smoking &amp; Reduced Lifespan: Jha, P., et al.&nbsp;(2013). <em>21st-Century Hazards of Smoking and Benefits of Cessation in the United States</em>. New England Journal of Medicine, 368, 341–350.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn9"><p>Exercise &amp; Lifespan: Lee, I., et al.&nbsp;(2012). <em>Effect of physical inactivity on major non-communicable diseases worldwide: an analysis of burden of disease and life expectancy</em>. Lancet, 380(9838), 219–229.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn10"><p>Mediterranean Diet Benefits: Sofi, F., et al.&nbsp;(2014). <em>Adherence to Mediterranean diet and health status: meta-analysis</em>. BMJ, 337, a1344.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn11"><p>Average American Body Fat: Fryar, C. D., Carroll, M. D., &amp; Ogden, C. L. (2012). <em>Prevalence of Overweight, Obesity, and Extreme Obesity Among Adults: United States, Trends 1960–1962 Through 2009–2010</em>. NCHS Health E-Stats.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn12"><p>Sleep &amp; Mortality: Cappuccio, F. P., et al.&nbsp;(2010). <em>Sleep duration and all-cause mortality: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective studies</em>. Sleep, 33(5), 585–592.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn13"><p>Navy Dolphins: Houser, D. S., &amp; Finneran, J. J. (2006). <em>A history of US Navy marine mammal program</em>. Aquatic Mammals, 32(2), 279–288.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn14"><p>Pig vs.&nbsp;Human Fat: Ellis, M., et al.&nbsp;(1996). <em>The Growth of Farm Animals</em>. CAB International.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn15"><p>Half-Life of Med School Knowledge: Densen, P. (2011). <em>Challenges and Opportunities Facing Medical Education</em>. Transactions of the American Clinical and Climatological Association, 122, 48–58.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn16"><p>Language &amp; Thought: Wittgenstein, L. (1922). <em>Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus</em>. London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn17"><p>Attractiveness Bias: Mazzella, R., &amp; Feingold, A. (1994). <em>The effects of physical attractiveness, race, socioeconomic status, and gender of defendants and victims on judgments of mock jurors: A meta-analysis</em>. Journal of Applied Social Psychology, 24(15), 1315–1338.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn18"><p>Athlete Privilege: Benedict, J. (2004). <em>Public Heroes, Private Felons: Athletes and Crimes Against Women</em>. Northeastern University Press.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn19"><p>LDS Journaling &amp; Influencers: Walker, S. (2019). <em>From Journals to YouTube: The Mormon Influence on Lifestyle Content Creation</em>. Religious Communication Today, 45(2), 25–47.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn20"><p>Two Sides of a Pancake: Common folk saying, referenced in conflict resolution literature.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn21"><p>Habit Formation: Clear, J. (2018). <em>Atomic Habits</em>. Avery.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn22"><p>Product vs.&nbsp;Marketing: Ries, E., (2011). <em>The Lean Startup</em>. Crown Business.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn23"><p>Grey Goose Branding: Barro, J. (2014). “The Dark Magic of Sidney Frank”. NYT Magazine.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn24"><p>Audience of One: Godin, S. (2008). <em>Tribes: We Need You to Lead Us</em>. Portfolio.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn25"><p>Growth for Growth’s Sake: Edward Abbey, <em>The Journey Home: Some Words in Defense of the American West</em>.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn26"><p>Warren Buffett &amp; Focus: Buffett, W. in Lowe, J. (2007). <em>Damn Right! Behind the Scenes with Berkshire Hathaway Billionaire Charlie Munger</em>.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn27"><p>Progress &amp; Happiness: Robbins, T. (2014). <em>Money: Master the Game</em>. Simon &amp; Schuster.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn28"><p>Success Without Fulfillment: Robbins, T. (2017). <em>Unshakeable</em>. Simon &amp; Schuster.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn29"><p>Everything Is Networks: Hoffman, R. (2015). <em>The Alliance: Managing Talent in the Networked Age</em>. Harvard Business Press.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-04-march-learnings/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-04-march-learnings/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Univariate Models For Time Series</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-24-ts-fundamentals-univariate-models/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>This post is part of a larger learning series around time series forecasting fundamentals. <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-25-ts-fundamentals/">Check out the learning path</a> to see other posts in the series.</em></p>
<section id="whats-a-univariate-model" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-a-univariate-model">What’s a Univariate Model?</h3>
<p>The simplest, yet often most powerful, models in time series forecasting are the oldest. These models are univariate approaches that are more statistics than new age machine learning. Univariate means that they only rely on previous values of the target variable to predict future values of that target variable. Just a timestamp and a target variable is all you need to get off the ground with univariate models.</p>
<p>This might sound too simple, but often it’s <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-05-03-time-series-simple-models/">the simplest models that can create the best forecasts</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="types-of-univariate-models" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="types-of-univariate-models">Types of Univariate Models</h3>
<p>There are countless univariate models we could cover, but instead we will keep things simple and discuss some of the most common models that provide the biggest bang for buck.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-04-10-ts-fundamentals-univariate-arima/">ARIMA</a></li>
<li>Exponential Smoothing (in progress)</li>
<li>Simple Benchmark Models</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>machine-learning</category>
  <category>time-series</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-24-ts-fundamentals-univariate-models/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-24-ts-fundamentals-univariate-models/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Data Cleaning: Stationary</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-21-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-stationary/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>This post is part of the <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-03-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning">data cleaning chapter</a> within a larger learning series around time series forecasting fundamentals. <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-25-ts-fundamentals/">Check out the main learning path</a> to see other posts in the series.</em></p>
<p><em>The example monthly data used in this series <a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/posts/2024-10-02-ts-fundamentals-whats-a-time-series/example_ts_data.csv">can be found here.</a> You can also find the <a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/notebooks/2025-03-21-ts-fundamentals-data-stationary.ipynb">python code used in this post here.</a></em></p>
<section id="trends-are-hard" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="trends-are-hard">Trends Are Hard</h3>
<p>In the world of forecasting, many models need the trend component to be removed in order to learn the right signal from the data. The process of removing a trend (and sometimes seasonality) is called differencing, which can make a time series become stationary.</p>
<p>Stationary just means that the time series has a constant mean and variance over time. Put simpler, it’s a time series that looks kind of random with no discernable trend or repeating seasonality. If a time series does have a trend, then we can remove it through a process called differencing, which involves subtracting a value in one time period from a value in a previous time period. More on this later.</p>
<p>Some models need data to be stationary to ensure it’s learning the correct relationships in the data, and doesn’t get fooled from thinking trends will always remain the same.</p>
<p>Let’s take a look at one of our time series. Does it look like it has a constant mean and variance over time?</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-21-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-stationary/chart1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Hmmm, not really. Seems like there is an upward trend to the data. This means that the mean over time will also rise. It probably also has a slightly growing variance. Meaning the year over year growth amount is getting bigger and bigger. Let’s see what we can do to make this data stationary through differencing.</p>
</section>
<section id="types-of-differencing" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="types-of-differencing">Types of Differencing</h3>
<p>There are two main types of differencing. The first is simply taking the difference between two consecutive periods. For example taking the sales in December and subtracting the sales in November (previous month). This is called first order differencing. Let’s try that on our time series and see what happens.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-21-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-stationary/chart2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Ok it’s looking a lot better! Our data is centered around zero, and doesn’t seem to be growing in magnitude over time. Seems like it could be stationary! Another way to apply differencing is by doing it twice, this is called second order differencing. You start by doing a first order difference, then do that same process again on that data. So instead of ending up with the change from period to period. You have the change of the change from period to period.</p>
<ul>
<li>A first order difference measures the change in position over time, which is like velocity</li>
<li>A second order difference measures the rate of change of the rate of change, which is like acceleration (the change in velocity over time)</li>
</ul>
<p>Taking a second order difference is done when the time series still doesn’t have constant mean or variance. Let’s take a second order difference of our example time series.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-21-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-stationary/chart3.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Things changed a little, but not much. Seems like a second order difference may not always be necessary. The final way to difference your time series is through seasonal differencing. This is the difference between an observation and the previous observation from the same season. For example with monthly sales, a season difference would be taking the difference between a month this year and the same month in the previous year. Taking a seasonal difference removes most seasonality in the data, hence the name. Let’s see how our data looks by just taking a seasonal difference.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-21-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-stationary/chart4.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The seasonal difference result looks good. Constant mean and variance throughout time. You can also combine both standard differencing with seasonal differencing. If your data has some seasonality, it’s best to do the seasonal difference first, then take the first order difference after. Let’s see how it looks.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-21-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-stationary/chart5.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We now have a nice mean around zero and no major variance throughout the data. Nice! But how the heck do we know if the data is stationary once we difference it?</p>
</section>
<section id="checking-if-your-data-is-stationary" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="checking-if-your-data-is-stationary">Checking if Your Data is Stationary</h3>
<p>In order to check if the data is stationary, either the original data or data that’s been differenced, you can use something called a unit root test. Specially a Kwiatkowski-Phillips-Schmidt-Shin (KPSS) test. This kind of test runs a few statistical processes and lets you know if the data it was fed was stationary or not. We can take this once step further by leveraging tools that build on this test and tell you how many differences should be applied on your data.</p>
<p>Let’s try running this test on our data and see how many differences we might need to make the data stationary.</p>
<ul>
<li>First order difference: stationary ✅</li>
<li>Second order difference: stationary ✅</li>
<li>Seasonal difference: stationary ✅</li>
<li>Seasonal and first order difference : stationary ✅</li>
</ul>
<p>Sweet! All of our differencing techniques each resulted in our data being stationary. It’s a good idea to pick the method that is the simplest way to get a stationary time series, which in our case is the first order difference. So we can use that going forward when training models.</p>
</section>
<section id="back-transformations" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="back-transformations">Back Transformations</h3>
<p>After you train a model and produce a forecast, the work is still not done. That forecast is the predicting the change between periods, not the actual values for that period. In order to get a final forecast we can use we need to transform that data back to the original units.</p>
<p>To do this we need all original values of the time series. When we difference our data, the process creates missing values at the start of the time series, because we cannot calculate the difference of the first period of the data since it’s the first period of the data. So a first order difference has one missing value at the start of the time series, a second order difference has 2, and a seasonal difference has many more depending on the seasonal periods in the data.</p>
<p>To get our final forecast we need to keep these original values, add them back to the differenced data, then start to add them up one by one. For a first order difference, that just means taking that original value in the first period, adding it to the differenced value in the second period, then adding that new value to the differenced value in the third period, and so on. It’s a daisy chained process to get the original data back. We carry this math forward into the future with our predictions, with the final output being our finished forecast!</p>
<p>Here’s a super simple table breaking this down.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 12%">
<col style="width: 19%">
<col style="width: 35%">
<col style="width: 32%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: center;">Month</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Original Series (Yₜ)</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">1st Order Difference (ΔYₜ = Yₜ - Yₜ₋₁)</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Transformed Back to Original Units</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">Jan 2024</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">100</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">—</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">—</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">Feb 2024</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">105</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">+5</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">—</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">Mar 2024</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">108</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">+3</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">—</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">Apr 2024</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">112</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">+4</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">—</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">May 2024</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">115</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">+3</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">—</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">Jun 2024</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">118</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">+3</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">—</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;"><strong>Forecast</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: center;">—</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">—</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">—</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">Jul 2024</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">—</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">+3 (forecasted)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">121 (118 + 3)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">Aug 2024</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">—</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">+3 (forecasted)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">124 (121 + 3)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">Sep 2024</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">—</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">+3 (forecasted)</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">127 (124 + 3)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="reversal" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reversal">Reversal</h3>
<p>There are cases where differencing your data to ensure it’s stationary is not a good idea. Some models, like arima, have the differencing process built in. So you don’t need to do it beforehand. Other models, like standard linear regressions, don’t need stationary data at all since they can easily learn from trends and seasonal patterns in the data.</p>
<p>Differencing the data can also limit model interpretability, or the ability to explain the forecasted outputs. This becomes even harder once you start to difference your data two or more times, since you are not explaining changes between observations, but instead the change in the changes or even worse. This becomes near impossible to understand for any regular human that might use your forecasts.</p>
<p>A final thing to call out with differencing is that it can remove historical data from the beginning of your time series. This may not be a big deal with a first order difference, but taking a seasonal difference on a monthly data set will remove the first 12 months of the time series. That may not be impactful if you have 10+ years of historical data, but if you only have 3 years to start with this becomes very detrimental to the process. That’s why I try to limit any seasonal differencing when the amount of historical data is low.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>
<p>Stationarity is fundamental to reliable forecasting because it ensures your models are learning stable, meaningful patterns rather than temporary or misleading trends. A stationary time series maintains a constant mean and variance over time, making its behavior predictable and easier for statistical models to learn from.</p>
<p>Differencing is a powerful yet straightforward way to achieve stationarity, paving the path for more accurate forecasts. While simple first-order differencing often does the trick, be cautious with higher-order or seasonal differences, as they can reduce interpretability, remove valuable historical context, and complicate back transformations. Always prioritize the simplest approach that achieves stationarity, keeping both modeling and explanations clear and intuitive. Ultimately, knowing how—and when—to apply stationarity transformations is key to building robust, effective forecasts.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>machine-learning</category>
  <category>time-series</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-21-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-stationary/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-21-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-stationary/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="82" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Your Genes Are Making You Sick</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-15-genetic-methylation/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="what-gets-measured-gets-managed" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-gets-measured-gets-managed">What Gets Measured, Gets Managed</h3>
<p>Our bodies are mostly a mystery to a regular person. Everyone takes vitamins, but do they actually help your body operate better? If you don’t know what kind of vitamins your body needs, there’s a good chance supplements you take every day are actively hurting your body or are simply being pissed down the drain (literally). Nobody wants to take something that is a waste of time. So how do you know what nutrients your body needs? This is where understanding methylation in your body comes in.</p>
</section>
<section id="whats-methylation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-methylation">What’s Methylation?</h3>
<p>Methylation is the process of converting nutrients you eat into things your body can actually use. We eat crude oil in the form of food, and our body uses methylation to process it into gasoline in to use for various processes that help us thrive. The issue is that our body rarely does this all perfectly. Many of us have gene mutations that inhibit this kind of conversation process. Let’s walk through some of the most common gene mutations around methylation and see how we can make sure our bodies are operating at their maximal potential.</p>
</section>
<section id="mthfr" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mthfr">MTHFR</h3>
<p>Commonly known as the “mother fucker” gene, this one can be a real mother fucker. Up to 44% of people in the world carry this gene mutation. MTHFR deals with how our body handles the nutrient called folate. It translates the folate we get from our food into a form our bodies can use called methylfolate or 5-MTHF, which is the methylated version of folate.</p>
<p>5-MTHF helps break down a compound in our body called homocysteine. Which is one of the most inflammatory compound in the human body. Inflammation is very bad for our body folks. When this compound is high all crazy types of things happen. Here are just a couple of things that are impacted.</p>
<ul>
<li>Creating neurotransmitters</li>
<li>DNA repair</li>
<li>Detoxing</li>
<li>Regulating blood pressure</li>
<li>Miscarriages during pregnancy</li>
<li>Anxiety</li>
</ul>
<p>Folate can be found in leafy greens and legumes. But the most common way we consume folate is through a compound called folic acid. Folic acid is the most common additive to our food. It’s literally everywhere. White rice and can flour contain folic acid. When ingredients say “fortified” or “enriched”, that means folic acid was added. This is bad news for people with the MTHFR mutation because they cannot process folic acid into the form our body needs. I will repeat, folic acid is the most common additive in food but cannot be properly processed by almost half of the worlds population. It’s even found in some prenatal vitamins, which has been linked to miscarriages and postpartum depression. Not good!</p>
<p>I know this is kind of scary to read, but thankfully there is some good news. There are easy ways to work around this gene mutation and ensure you are thriving in life. Here’s what to do.</p>
<ul>
<li>Avoid all forms of folic acid, which limits your processed food intake, which is a major health win overall</li>
<li>Take the methylated version of folate, <a href="https://a.co/d/4TwoR4o">called 5-MTHF</a>, at night before going to bed</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="mtr" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mtr">MTR</h3>
<p>Similar to MTHFR, the MTR gene also plays in a role in regulating homocysteine by converting it into another compound called methionine. For this reaction to work, your body needs vitamin B12, specifically the methylated versions of B12 like methylcobalamin or hydroxocobalamin.</p>
<p>If you have this gene mutation, you may experience certain gut issues like these.</p>
<ul>
<li>Gas</li>
<li>Bloating</li>
<li>Diarrhea</li>
<li>Constipation</li>
<li>Cramping</li>
</ul>
<p>Supplementing with B12 is crucial for this gene mutation, but similar to MTHFR not all supplements are created equal. Stay away from a form of B12 called Cyanocobalamin. This form contains hydrogen cyanide, which is a known neurotoxin. It’s often added into cheap energy drinks and even milk! Companies do this because it’s cheap and they don’t care, so care for yourself and avoid it at all costs.</p>
<p>Here’s what to do if you have this gene mutation.</p>
<ul>
<li>Limit alcohol, which depletes methyl donors and can interfere with B12 absorption</li>
<li>Avoid heavy metals (like mercury and lead) that bind to B12, making it unavailable for MTR to use</li>
<li>Take the methylated version of B12, either methylcobalamin or hydroxocobalamin found in <a href="https://a.co/d/fHQiO9z">methylated multivitamins</a>
<ul>
<li>FYI not everyone can process methylcobalamin, but 100% of humans can process hydroxocobalamin in their body</li>
<li>If you also have the COMT gene mutation, you absolutely should be taking hydroxocobalamin since your body can process that better than other forms like methylcobalamin</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="mtrr" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mtrr">MTRR</h3>
<p>This gene works closely with the MTR gene, hence similar names. It helps reactivate B12 that was used by the MTR gene when converting homocysteine into methionine. Over time B12 can become oxidized when used by the MTR gene, so MTRR comes in to convert it back into its methylated form so it can be properly used again. MTRR is also important in the thyroid, helping convert one important thyroid hormone T4 into T3, which happens in your gut.</p>
<p>If you have this gene mutation, you might suffer from the following.</p>
<ul>
<li>Heart burn</li>
<li>Acid reflux</li>
<li>Thyroid issues</li>
<li>Short temper</li>
<li>High blood pressure</li>
<li>Exacerbations of ADD, ADHD, OCD</li>
</ul>
<p>Follow the same guidelines as described in the MTR section above. Avoid the wrong types of B12 and make sure to take versions that your body can actually use.</p>
</section>
<section id="ahcy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ahcy">AHCY</h3>
<p>This gene helps break down S-Adenosylhomocysteine (SAH) into homocysteine and adenosine. This process is critical because SAH is a strong inhibitor of methylation enzymes. If it builds up, it slows down methylation reactions throughout the body. SAH is one of the most inflammatory compounds in your body, even worse than homocysteine.</p>
<p>This is a rare gene mutation to have, but people with it can have addictive tendencies. For example, addiction to video games as kids, then phones as teenagers, then drugs, alcohol, sugar, working out, eating, sex, shopping, working. This is caused by wide ranges in dopamine in the body, which is tied to our behaviors. So people with this mutation tend to seek out dopamine rewarding behavior.</p>
<p>Here’s what to do if you have this gene mutation.</p>
<ul>
<li>Consume collagen to ensure your ingesting enough glycine to help your body balance methionine. If AHCY isn’t efficiently breaking down SAH, excess methionine intake might lead to toxic byproducts instead of proper methylation.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="comt" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comt">COMT</h3>
<p>This gene breaks down major neurotransmitters in the body. Things like dopamine and adrenaline. It’s also responsible for metabolizing estrogens, and having too much of this hormone for both men and women can be bad. When your body can’t break these these things, all sorts of things get out of whack.</p>
<p>If you have this gene mutation, you might suffer from the following.</p>
<ul>
<li>Stress and anxiety</li>
<li>Trouble winding down and sleeping</li>
<li>Quick to anger, slow to calm down</li>
<li>Higher estrogen levels, which can lead to water retention under the belly button and around the waist</li>
<li>Pain sensitivity</li>
<li>ADD or ADHD</li>
</ul>
<p>Thankfully it’s not all bad with this gene mutation. Because things like dopamine stay around longer in your brain, it can lead to higher creativity and deep thinking. But this comes at a cost of overanalyzing and worrying.</p>
<p>Here’s what to do if you have this gene mutation.</p>
<ul>
<li>Avoid green tea and quercitin (found in green tea and other supplements) at all costs. These can make your COMT symptoms much worse.</li>
<li>If you have excess water retention around your belly, look into taking a <a href="https://a.co/d/8Af2hyP">diindolylmethane (DIM) supplement</a>, which can help reduce that water retention by removing excess estrogen in your body.</li>
<li>Consider taking a <a href="https://a.co/d/eZ5ui5I">trimethylglycine (TMG) supplement</a>, which can help regulate the processes that maintain your neurotransmitters</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="how-they-all-connect" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-they-all-connect">How They All Connect</h3>
<p>Processes in our body can be thought of like a group of construction workers passing sandbags to each other in a single line. One gene can do a process the body needs, then pass the output along to another gene to do another process, and so on. But if one of those genes can only pass along 4 sandbags instead of the 10 needed, then the most any of the downstream genes will get is 40% of what’s required.</p>
<p>This is why understanding genetic methylation in our bodies is so important. Each of these 5 genes play a crucial role in making our bodies work.</p>
<p>Let’s do a recap of each gene and what they do in our methylation process.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>MTHFR starts the process by making active folate (5-MTHF)</li>
<li>MTR uses 5-MTHF &amp; B12 to convert homocysteine into methionine</li>
<li>MTRR keeps MTR working by recharging B12</li>
<li>AHCY clears out byproducts and provides fresh homocysteine</li>
<li>COMT uses methylation to break down stress chemicals and estrogen</li>
</ol>
<p>If any of these genes don’t work well, the whole system slows down! The fix is to support each gene with the right nutrients and to avoid things your body may not be able to handle.</p>
</section>
<section id="dna-testing" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dna-testing">DNA Testing</h3>
<p>How the heck do I know if I have any gene mutations? This is where testing comes in. There are a lot of services out there that will do a genetic methylation test for you. They cost a few hundred dollars, but it’s a test you only need to run once in your life.</p>
<p>It’s a simple cheek swab you do at home then mail in. I used a service called <a href="https://10xhealthsystem.com/genetest/">10X Health</a>, but there are many providers out there who can help.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>
<p>I got my results back about a month ago, and things did not look good. I had mutations in all 5 genes except AHCY, with the MTHFR and COMT genes having the strongest mutation (meaning they don’t work). These results are kind of like getting a personality test result. You start to understand who you are as a person more. Why you act and feel a certain way. You start to understand your parents and siblings so much more, because they most likely carry similar genes as you. It’s life changing to receive information that shows you how to live a better life with 100% certainty.</p>
<p>My gene results showed that I had to really crack down on folic acid (MTHFR gene) and green tea/quercetin (COMT). I realized some of my most beloved foods and supplements, that are supposed to be healthy, actually contain things that are the worst to put into my body. Since cleaning those up I have had an easier time falling asleep, and my brain is working better than ever. It’s also been easier to avoid processed food, because I know almost all of it contains things that my body cannot handle well. So the temptation to binge on them has been removed. Thank goodness!</p>
<p>If you’d like to live up to your highest potential in life. Consider taking control of your genetics and get tested! It might just change your life. To learn more about genetic mythlation, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@ultimatehumanpodcast">check out Gary Breka’s channel on YouTube</a>, he’s got tons of great info.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.shutterstock.com/search/watson-crick-dna-model?cr=bc&amp;gclid=c03f1496e24a1f3767de7343192784c5&amp;gclsrc=3p.ds&amp;image_type=illustration&amp;kw=shutterstock&amp;msclkid=c03f1496e24a1f3767de7343192784c5&amp;pl=PPC_BNG_US_DSA-&amp;utm_campaign=CO%3DUS_LG%3DEN_BU%3DIMG_AD%3DDSA_TS%3Dlggeneric_RG%3DAMER_AB%3DACQ_CH%3DSEM_OG%3DCONV_PB%3DMicrosoft-Ads&amp;utm_content=FF%3DDSA-All-Pages_AU%3DSite+Visitors&amp;utm_medium=cpc&amp;utm_source=bing&amp;utm_term=shutterstock">Photo Credit</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>health</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-15-genetic-methylation/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-15-genetic-methylation/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="86" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>February Learnings</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-01-february-learnings/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I love reading books, watching YouTube videos, listening to podcasts, you name it. Anything learning related is my jam. But I realized that if I don’t take notes on what I’m learning, I will probably forget everything. Now when I hear something interesting, I write it down in an Apple note for that month. Below are some of the learnings I jotted down in February, summarized by ChatGPT with additional context added by their new deep research feature. I hope you find them as interesting as I did.</p>
<section id="ai-machine-learning" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ai-machine-learning">AI &amp; Machine Learning</h2>
<section id="knowledge-distillation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="knowledge-distillation">Knowledge Distillation</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>AI Distillation:</strong> Process of transferring knowledge from a large, complex AI model (teacher) to a smaller, efficient model (student). Example: DeepSeek training their R1 model using GPT-4 answers as training data.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="large-language-model-llm-architectures" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="large-language-model-llm-architectures">Large Language Model (LLM) Architectures</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Transformer Architecture:</strong> Neural network architecture characterized by self-attention mechanisms, enabling parallel processing and context awareness.</li>
<li><strong>Mixture of Experts (MoE):</strong> Architecture where subsets of neurons (“experts”) activate selectively per task, significantly reducing computational overhead and inference costs.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="economics-of-ai" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="economics-of-ai">Economics of AI</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Jevons Paradox:</strong> Lowering the cost of AI increases its usage dramatically.</li>
<li><strong>Token Costs:</strong> Input tokens (~¼ the cost of output tokens) allow parallel processing, whereas output tokens are sequential and auto-regressive.</li>
<li><strong>GPU Performance Factors:</strong> Critical aspects for AI training and inference are Floating-point operations (FLOPS), Memory bandwidth (IO), and Chip interconnectedness.</li>
<li><strong>Cost Evolution of AI Models:</strong> GPT-3 costs dropped drastically from ~$60 to ~$0.05 per million tokens between 2022 and 2024, a 1,200x reduction.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="geopolitics-and-ai-chips" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="geopolitics-and-ai-chips">Geopolitics and AI Chips</h3>
<ul>
<li>Chinese companies circumvent U.S. Nvidia GPU export bans by routing purchases through third-party vendors in Singapore.</li>
<li><strong>DeepSeek Origin:</strong> Began as a spinoff of the Chinese hedge fund “High Flyer,” originally focused on GPU-based trading algorithms, later pivoting to AI models.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="cognitive-performance-optimization" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cognitive-performance-optimization">Cognitive &amp; Performance Optimization</h2>
<section id="most-important-question-miq-framework" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="most-important-question-miq-framework">Most Important Question (MIQ) Framework</h3>
<ul>
<li>Regularly clarify and revisit the single most critical, high-level question guiding your decisions, ensuring deep strategic alignment.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="peak-performance-work-strategies" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="peak-performance-work-strategies">Peak Performance Work Strategies</h3>
<ul>
<li>Optimize intense, focused effort for fewer hours (3–5 hours/day) rather than prolonged mediocre sessions.</li>
<li>Reserve creative, high-focus tasks for peak-energy periods; routine tasks during lower-energy periods (e.g., noted dip around 2:30–3:30 pm).</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="mental-state-management" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mental-state-management">Mental State Management</h3>
<ul>
<li>Leverage breathing techniques to control adrenaline and enhance decision-making speed and clarity.</li>
<li>Prioritize reflective time by avoiding immediate stimuli (e.g., smartphones) first thing in the morning.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="quality-over-quantity" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="quality-over-quantity">Quality Over Quantity</h3>
<ul>
<li>Short bursts of deep work significantly outperform extended hours of moderate or distracted effort.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="health-fitness" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-fitness">Health &amp; Fitness</h2>
<section id="training-principles" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="training-principles">Training Principles</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Optimal Training Splits:</strong> “Push-Legs-Pull” split recommended for optimal muscle recovery and growth.</li>
<li>Aim to train each muscle group twice weekly for maximal growth stimulus.</li>
<li>Understand the <strong>interference effect</strong>—heavy back workouts might negatively impact squatting performance the next day.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="protein-intake-recommendations" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="protein-intake-recommendations">Protein Intake Recommendations</h3>
<ul>
<li>Non-lifters: ~0.8 grams per pound of body weight daily.</li>
<li>Lifters aiming for muscle growth: ~1.3 grams per pound daily; significant growth benefit compared to lower intakes.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="effective-supplements-for-muscle-gain" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="effective-supplements-for-muscle-gain">Effective Supplements for Muscle Gain</h3>
<ul>
<li>Creatine (improves strength and power), Protein powder (supports muscle recovery), Multivitamins (general health), Carb powders (Gatorade, Powerade for energy replenishment), Caffeine (enhances workout focus).</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="risks-of-sedentary-behavior" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="risks-of-sedentary-behavior">Risks of Sedentary Behavior</h3>
<ul>
<li>Prolonged sitting significantly increases mortality risk; offset by regular activity and frequent movement breaks.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="behavioral-eating-habit-adjustment" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="behavioral-eating-habit-adjustment">Behavioral Eating Habit Adjustment</h3>
<ul>
<li>When stressed or craving food, first take a 30-minute walk to distinguish genuine hunger from stress-induced urges.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="business-strategy" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="business-strategy">Business &amp; Strategy</h2>
<section id="new-product-strategy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-product-strategy">New Product Strategy</h3>
<ul>
<li>Start by identifying core insights, fire small “test” bullets (low-risk experiments), and upon success, scale with larger, well-resourced “cannonballs.”</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="market-psychology" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="market-psychology">Market Psychology</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Osborn Effect:</strong> Announcing future products too early can stall current sales as customers delay purchasing decisions.</li>
<li><strong>Halo Effect:</strong> Successfully launching a new product enhances brand image, positively affecting the sales of existing products.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="strategic-hiring-expert-filtering" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="strategic-hiring-expert-filtering">Strategic Hiring &amp; Expert Filtering</h3>
<ul>
<li>Identify talent by querying top performers for recommendations, refining the hiring funnel to focus on demonstrated capability and peer recognition.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="economic-insights" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="economic-insights">Economic Insights</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>GDP Growth Simplified:</strong> Driven by the productivity per worker and the total workforce.</li>
<li><strong>Idiot Index:</strong> Metric comparing raw material costs to finished product price, highlighting operational inefficiencies and pricing strategies.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="historical-cultural-insights" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="historical-cultural-insights">Historical &amp; Cultural Insights</h2>
<section id="mongol-empire" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mongol-empire">Mongol Empire</h3>
<ul>
<li>Exceptional warfare tactics: mobility, psychological intimidation, and merit-based leadership. Each soldier crafted their own bows, ensuring skill and accountability.</li>
<li>Mongol rule lasted until Soviet invasion (~1220–1920), marking the longest family-led empire in history.</li>
<li>Genghis Khan’s aggressive strategies rooted partly in personal revenge and necessity after familial trauma.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="korean-language-origins-hangul" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="korean-language-origins-hangul">Korean Language Origins (Hangul)</h3>
<ul>
<li>Hangul invented explicitly due to difficulty in learning complex Chinese characters. Designed for rapid acquisition, enhancing widespread literacy.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="stanfords-touchy-feely-class" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stanfords-touchy-feely-class">Stanford’s “Touchy-Feely” Class</h3>
<ul>
<li>“Interpersonal Dynamics” at Stanford GSB teaches emotional intelligence, authentic communication, and relationship-building skills via experiential T-group sessions.</li>
<li>5 levels of communication
<ol type="1">
<li>Ritual: classic conversations like general greeting</li>
<li>Extended ritual: asking about the weather or a recent sports game</li>
<li>Content: facts about a project or work items</li>
<li>Emotional self-disclosure: saying how you feel emotionally (I feel sad)</li>
<li>Neutral emotional self-disclosure: expressing emotion at another person (I feel proud of you, angry at you, etc)</li>
</ol></li>
<li>To have strong relationships in life and career, you have to get to level 4 and 5</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="psychology-behavioral-science" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="psychology-behavioral-science">Psychology &amp; Behavioral Science</h2>
<section id="behavioral-loops-addiction" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="behavioral-loops-addiction">Behavioral Loops &amp; Addiction</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Scarcity Loop:</strong> Opportunity → Unpredictable reward → Quick repeatability drives addictive behaviors (gambling, social media).</li>
<li><strong>Near-Miss Effect:</strong> Close failures in gambling or gaming increase dopamine and repeat behaviors, driving addiction.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="importance-of-courage" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="importance-of-courage">Importance of Courage</h3>
<ul>
<li>Courage is central to achieving significant outcomes; talent and intelligence without courage lead to stagnation and regret.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="nova-effect" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nova-effect">Nova Effect</h3>
<ul>
<li>Sudden positive events (e.g., winning the lottery) can negatively impact perceived happiness afterward. Gradual progress allows better psychological adaptation.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="miscellaneous-insights-notable-quotes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="miscellaneous-insights-notable-quotes">Miscellaneous Insights &amp; Notable Quotes</h2>
<section id="philosophical-reflections" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="philosophical-reflections">Philosophical Reflections</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Success &amp; Failure:</strong> “Success is going from failure to failure without loss of enthusiasm.”</li>
<li><strong>Life Razor (Personal Decision Framework):</strong> Prioritize actions granting maximum control over personal time.</li>
<li><strong>Seasons of Life:</strong> Life priorities shift naturally through different life stages; adaptability is crucial.</li>
<li><strong>Learning &amp; Reflection:</strong> True learning arises when experience intersects with thoughtful reflection.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="intriguing-observations" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="intriguing-observations">Intriguing Observations</h3>
<ul>
<li>Diamonds priced disproportionately at milestone sizes (2-carat vs.&nbsp;1.99-carat).</li>
<li>Chronic strep throat indicates potential mold exposure.</li>
<li>Epstein-Barr virus (mono) infection necessary precursor for multiple sclerosis.</li>
<li>Icelandic dating app created by the government prevents accidental familial relationships.</li>
<li>Drug companies advertise heavily on news networks, indirectly shaping media narratives.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="notable-quotes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notable-quotes">Notable Quotes</h3>
<ul>
<li><em>“Your life is in your hands; don’t drop it.”</em></li>
<li><em>“The generation that lights the fuse usually gets buried in the rubble.”</em></li>
<li><em>“Be interested, not interesting.”</em><br>
</li>
<li><em>“If more money wouldn’t change how you spend your time, you’re already rich.”</em><br>
</li>
<li><em>“Your health at age 80 is a reflection of your relationships at age 50.”</em></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-01-february-learnings/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 01 Mar 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-01-february-learnings/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Life Principles</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-24-life-principles/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="a-man-must-have-a-code" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-man-must-have-a-code">A Man Must Have a Code</h3>
<p>Every person lives by a set of principles that govern their actions throughout life. They are either principles inherited by the society they were raised in (unconsciously), or principles that were chosen and updated by a person on their own (consciously). The best principles in life are ones you have thought through yourself. Below are the top principles I like to live my life by.</p>
</section>
<section id="bias-for-action" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bias-for-action">Bias for Action</h3>
<p>Action is the best answer to most problems. Sitting around waiting for something to happen to you rarely works out. No one ever get’s lucky sitting on their couch watching Netflix. Action creates luck, creates feedback, and also creates momentum.</p>
</section>
<section id="sense-of-urgency" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sense-of-urgency">Sense of Urgency</h3>
<p>Life is short, and timelines are negotiable. Ever heard of the parkinson principle? It states that work expands to fill the time available for its completion. Got an important work project due in a month? It will probably take you a month to do. Does the same project need to be done by Friday? Then you will also probably finish it Friday morning.</p>
<p>Reality is negotiable. Peter Thiel has a saying: “If you have a 10 year plan of how to get somewhere, you should ask: why can’t I do this in 6 months?”. The quality of your questions determines the quality of your life.</p>
<p>When you combine a sense of urgency with a bias for action, you become an unstoppable force. This brings us to my next principle.</p>
</section>
<section id="high-agency" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="high-agency">High Agency</h3>
<p>Who would you call to break you out of a third world prison? That person has a high sense of agency, which means they have have the ability to control what happens to them in life. Think of it as the opposite of a victim mentality. Agency is the combination of a bias for action with a sense of urgency.</p>
<p>George Mack does a good job discussing agency. <a href="https://x.com/george__mack/status/1661426260327759902?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw%7Ctwcamp%5Etweetembed%7Ctwterm%5E1661426260327759902%7Ctwgr%5E7eacc97032d4e2d008f3d1d669bb67c347937b2c%7Ctwcon%5Es1_&amp;ref_url=https%3A%2F%2Fapp.beehiiv.com%2Flogin%3F_gl%3D11bn3wdj_gaNTI1OTM1NjEuMTY4NjMyNDQzMg.._ga_E6Y4WLQ2ECMTY4NjMyNDQzMi4xLjAuMTY4NjMyNDQzMi42MC4wLjA.&amp;utm_source=clouds-and-dirt.beehiiv.com&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=lindy-library-the-0-1-of-ideas-i-ve-found">Here is a good example</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="zero-expectations" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="zero-expectations">Zero Expectations</h3>
<p>When Charlie Munger was asked about what it takes to live a happy life his response was simple, have low expectations. In a similar vein, Naval Ravikant states that happiness is a simple equation. Happiness = Reality - Expectations.</p>
<p>If you came to Seattle in January and expected it to be warm and sunny, you’d be bummed out if it was 50 degrees with a slight drizzle. Instead if you came expecting it to be cold and constantly raining, then you’d be pleasantly surprised to find out that it didn’t rain much at all. The same external events happened in both examples, but the change in expectations made for a better outcome.</p>
<p>It’s ok to have high expectations for yourself, but having high expectations over things in life you can’t control is a recipe for disaster.</p>
</section>
<section id="time-over-money" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="time-over-money">Time Over Money</h3>
<p>Control over how you spend your time is the ultimate freedom and source of power. It’s the life razor I use to make most decisions in my life.</p>
</section>
<section id="love-over-power" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="love-over-power">Love Over Power</h3>
<p>Most things we chase in life are a <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-03-13-power-pursuits/">form of power</a>. Money, status, fame, beauty, these are all forms of power. They will not make you fulfilled in life. You know what will? Love.</p>
</section>
<section id="giving-without-getting" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="giving-without-getting">Giving Without Getting</h3>
<p>Giving away my time, attention, and skills with no expectations of something in return is very important to me. Nothing grinds my gears like someone doing a good deed in the world then immediately posting about it on social media. They are giving with the intention of receiving status in return. Giving yourself to others is an amazing act in and of itself, full stop.</p>
</section>
<section id="stay-present" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stay-present">Stay Present</h3>
<p>If you think about the future, you are anxious. If you think about the past, you are depressed. Staying in the future moment is the best way to live a happy and purpose filled life.</p>
</section>
<section id="stagnation-is-death" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stagnation-is-death">Stagnation is Death</h3>
<p>If you are coasting, you are going downhill. Always be learning, always be evolving. If you are not learning, you are dying.</p>
</section>
<section id="keep-it-simple" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="keep-it-simple">Keep it Simple</h3>
<p>The best solutions to problems in life are the simplest. Keep it simple stupid.</p>
</section>
<section id="incentives-matter" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="incentives-matter">Incentives Matter</h3>
<p>Charlie Munger once said “show me the incentive and I’ll show you the behavior”. Incentives rule most things in life. Use the right incentive and you will change your life, and maybe the world.</p>
</section>
<section id="run-towards-fear" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="run-towards-fear">Run Towards Fear</h3>
<p>Usually the things you are the most afraid of are the most important things that you need to do to improve your life. Scared of public speaking? Then getting good at it will probably change your life more than anything else.</p>
</section>
<section id="allergic-to-status" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="allergic-to-status">Allergic to Status</h3>
<p>Increasing your status will not create a fulfilling life. So I try not to do things that inflate my status. Comparison is the thief of joy. Never compare yourself to others (aka your status compared to others), only compare yourself to who you were yesterday.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-things-worth-writing-write-things-worth-reading" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-things-worth-writing-write-things-worth-reading">Do Things Worth Writing, Write Things Worth Reading</h3>
<p>This is a quote from Ben Franklin. I think it’s a great life philosophy. I try to do both interesting things, and write interesting things. Heck, you are hopefully reading something interesting right now!</p>
</section>
<section id="what-would-you-do-if-you-couldnt-fail" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-would-you-do-if-you-couldnt-fail">What Would You Do If You Couldn’t Fail?</h3>
<p>This is a fantastic question to ask yourself. It can help you determine your career path and most of your major decisions in life. If you are stuck in your career, asking this question can point you in the right direction.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-makes-for-the-best-story" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-makes-for-the-best-story">What Makes for the Best Story?</h3>
<p>Amjad Masad, CEO of Replit, uses this question as the final decision framework for big life moves. When deciding between two paths, taking the one that makes for the better story will almost always create a better life for you. Choose wisely.</p>
</section>
<section id="did-i-always-do-my-best" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="did-i-always-do-my-best">Did I Always Do My Best?</h3>
<p>John Wooden says that “success is the peace of mind that is the direct result of self-satisfaction knowing you did your best to become the best that you are capable of becoming”. He didn’t care about the score of the game, he only cared that his players rose to their full potential. If they did that, everything else will take care of itself. Even if they lost, they still were at peace because they knew they did their best. This is a powerful idea and one that people today seem to overlook.</p>
</section>
<section id="dont-be-the-best-be-the-only" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dont-be-the-best-be-the-only">Don’t Be the Best, Be the Only</h3>
<p>This comes from the law of category from a book called <a href="https://a.co/d/9bse5C6">The 22 Immutable Laws of Marketing</a>. It’s better to be the first person in a new industry than to be the 10th person. Finding things that you are the only person in the world doing is a good place to be.</p>
</section>
<section id="stop-trying-to-sound-smart" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stop-trying-to-sound-smart">Stop Trying to Sound Smart</h3>
<p>I’ve had to learn this one the hard way. Stop trying to be right all of the time. Stop trying to one up people with more interesting facts or stories. Stop correcting people. Once you stop, the quality of your relationships improve, which improves your entire life.</p>
</section>
<section id="hard-choices-easy-life.-easy-choices-hard-life." class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hard-choices-easy-life.-easy-choices-hard-life.">Hard Choices, Easy Life. Easy Choices, Hard Life.</h3>
<p>This comes from Jerzy Gregorek. If you make the easy choice of eating junk food today, your life will become much harder in the future once you develop diabetes and cardiovascular disease. But if you make the hard choices of diet and exercise today, future you will be happy and healthy. This approach applies to most things in life. Hard now, easy later.</p>
</section>
<section id="gear-over-stuff" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gear-over-stuff">Gear Over Stuff</h3>
<p>This was outlined in Michael Easter’s book called <a href="https://a.co/d/2GHLZeR">Scarcity Brain</a>. Having more stuff in my life weighs me down, increasing stress. Instead gear serves a purpose in your life. You can have tons of stuff, but only so much gear.</p>
</section>
<section id="avoid-scarcity-loops" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="avoid-scarcity-loops">Avoid Scarcity Loops</h3>
<p>This is the main concept outlined in Michael Easter’s book called <a href="https://a.co/d/2GHLZeR">Scarcity Brain</a>. It has three parts.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Opportunity</li>
<li>Unpredictable Rewards</li>
<li>Quick Repeatability</li>
</ol>
<p>Scarcity loops are built to make us crave certain behaviors that are most likely not good for us. Once you learn this you see it everywhere. Let’s take checking your email. It’s easy to open the app on your phone (opportunity), you may or may not have any new unread emails (unpredictable rewards), and you can easily recheck for new emails five minutes later (quick repeatability). Checking your email constantly is obviously not good for you, but scarcity loops change your behavior for the worst. There are also scarcity loops on social media, junk food, drinking, drugs, gambling, online shopping, and literally anything else that is not healthy for you.</p>
<p>Avoid them at all cost.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-most-important-question" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-most-important-question">The Most Important Question</h3>
<p>Josh Waitzkin has a framework called <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UnGtVDU-Yw4&amp;t">the most important question</a> that helps train you on discovering what matters most. Knowing where to focus your energy is often more important than how hard you work at something. Remember, the quality of your questions determines the quality of your life. So being able to think about <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dfv2d1ItzOQ">the most important question to solve</a> for in your job, marriage, etc. is paramount.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>
<p>To live a quality life you must have quality principles. If you don’t, you will be easily influenced to live an unauthentic life based on the expectations of society. Feel free to take some of mine to use as your own principles, or don’t! I could care less, because I have zero expectations about people reading this post.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.hardwoodandhollywood.com/pop-culture-spin/2015/01/28/wire-five-omar-littles-greatest-quotes/">Photo Credit</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-24-life-principles/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-24-life-principles/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="95" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Data Cleaning: Box-Cox Transformations</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-05-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-boxcox/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>This post is part of the <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-03-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning">data cleaning chapter</a> within a larger learning series around time series forecasting fundamentals. <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-25-ts-fundamentals/">Check out the main learning path</a> to see other posts in the series.</em></p>
<p><em>The example monthly data used in this series <a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/posts/2024-10-02-ts-fundamentals-whats-a-time-series/example_ts_data.csv">can be found here.</a> You can also find the <a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/notebooks/2025-02-05-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-boxcox.ipynb">python code used in this post here.</a></em></p>
<section id="keeping-it-in-between-the-lines" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="keeping-it-in-between-the-lines">Keeping It In Between The Lines</h3>
<p>Most of time series forecasting is all about trying to fit a line to your data. There are a million ways to do it, but at its core we want to fit a line that’s as close as possible to the original data and where we think future data points might lie.</p>
<p>The easiest line to fit is already a straight line, or one that has linear growth. Consider the chart below. What do you think the future forecast will be? Pretty easy, a model can just extend the same upward linear growth going forward.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-05-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-boxcox/chart1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We would always prefer to model a time series that has a linear trend. But often that’s not the case in businesses. Revenue might double every year, and that my friend is not a linear line, but instead an exponential one. A time series growing exponentially is harder for many models to forecast because most models expect the variance of the data to stay the same over time (more on this in the stationary post), and a expanding time series violates this assumption. Consider one of our example time series in our dataset below. See how it grows not at a linear pace but a hockey stick like exponential pace?</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-05-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-boxcox/chart2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>A good way to handle this exponential growth is to transform it into one that looks more linear. This is where a technique called a box-cox transformation comes in handy.</p>
</section>
<section id="box-cox-enters-the-chat" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="box-cox-enters-the-chat">Box-Cox Enters The Chat</h3>
<p>The Box-Cox transformation is a family of power transformations that aim to make data more normally distributed and stabilize its variance​. In simple terms, it transforms your original values using an exponent (λ, “lambda”) to reduce skewness.</p>
<p>Lambda can take many values. A lambda of 0 corresponds to a log transform. A value of 0.5 is a square root transform. By transforming our data this way we can in essence de-scale the data to ensure any large spikes are dampened and easier for a model to fit the data. This can transform our data to be homoscedastic, or having constant variance. Let’s see how our time series looks after applying a few box-cox transformations.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-05-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-boxcox/chart3.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-05-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-boxcox/chart4.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The log transformation (lambda = 0) seems to have done a great job at turning our exponential growth into linear growth. The square root transformation (lambda = 0.5) didn’t do as well. Choosing the right value of lambda is important, thankfully there is an automated process that can do it for us. Let’s see how the data looks with an optimal lambda value chosen automatically.</p>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-05-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-boxcox/chart5.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The automated process chose a lambda value very close to zero. So it basically did a simple log transformation. Now our data has become much easier to model correctly, how cool is that!</p>
</section>
<section id="reversal" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reversal">Reversal</h3>
<p>There are no perfect solutions, only tradeoffs. Here are a few when using box-cox transformations.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Runaway exponential trends</strong>: If your time series has exponential trend aspects, but isn’t actually a true exponential trend, there can be big repercussions. A model might take that transformed data and start creating future forecasts that are astronomical in size, going from thousands to trillions in a few periods. A good example is a time series that is stable for most of its history, then at the very end it all of a sudden has tripled in value over one or two periods. A box-cox transformation will pick up on this and transform the data in a way that a model might pick up on as a trend that should grow into the future. So each subsequent forecast period might continue to triple in value. That’s not good.</li>
<li><strong>Time series can’t be zero or negative</strong>: All zero values must be changed to be a placeholder value like 0.1 or 1, that way things like a log transformation can work. There also can’t be any negative values, again because you can’t take the log of a negative number, which in some time series is unavoidable.</li>
<li><strong>Need to back transform the data after forecasting</strong>: After you train a model and create a forecast on the transformed data, you must transform the forecast back to the original units. So you have to make sure you keep the lambda value used in the box-cox transformation handy, because you will need it to inverse the transformation.</li>
<li><strong>Less model interpretability</strong>: Because a model is learning on transformed data, being able to explain the models decisions become harder. Know there is always a tradeoff between model accuracy and model interpretability.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>
<p>Box-Cox transformations are a powerful tool for taming exponential growth in time series, making trends easier to model and forecast. However, like any transformation, they come with tradeoffs. Potentially misleading trends, the need for careful handling of zeros and negatives, and additional steps to back-transform predictions. Despite these challenges, applying box-cox correctly can make a significant difference in forecasting accuracy. The key takeaway? Use transformations thoughtfully, always validate their impact on your specific dataset, and remember that the best forecast starts with well-prepared data.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>machine-learning</category>
  <category>time-series</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-05-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-boxcox/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-05-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-boxcox/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Data Cleaning For Time Series</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-03-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>This post is part of a larger learning series around time series forecasting fundamentals. <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-25-ts-fundamentals/">Check out the learning path</a> to see other posts in the series.</em></p>
<section id="data-overview" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-overview">Data Overview</h3>
<p>The result of exploratory data analysis can reveal a lot about your data. One factor it can bubble up is how clean the data is, and if there needs to be any interventions done before we start training models. Cleaning your data is an important next step. If your data is garbage, you will create a garbage forecast. <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-04-08-time-series-garbage/">Gargbage in, garbage out.</a></p>
</section>
<section id="data-cleaning-for-time-series" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-cleaning-for-time-series">Data Cleaning for Time Series</h3>
<p>The way you clean your time series data is very different than of machine learning domains. Here are the building blocks of good data cleaning. Some are the same posts from previous chapters, but they still apply here. Click on each to explore further.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-11-26-ts-fundamentals-missing-outliers/">Missing Values, Outliers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-05-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-boxcox/">Box-Cox Transformation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-03-21-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning-stationary/">Stationary</a></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>machine-learning</category>
  <category>time-series</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-03-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-03-ts-fundamentals-data-cleaning/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>January Learnings</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-01-january-learnings/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I love reading books, watching YouTube videos, listening to podcasts, you name it. Anything learning related is my jam. But I recently realized that if I don’t take notes on what I’m learning, I will probably forget everything. Now when I hear something interesting, I write it down in an Apple note for that month. Below are some of the learnings I jotted down in January, summarized by ChatGPT. I hope you find them as interesting as I did.</p>
<section id="work-life-balance-fulfillment" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="work-life-balance-fulfillment">1. Work-Life Balance &amp; Fulfillment</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Fun, not discipline</strong>: Scheduling enjoyable activities each week prevents work from creeping into all free time.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Success definition</strong>: True success is loving both your work and your personal life.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Capping success</strong>: Decide how much growth you can handle without losing who you are.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="tradeoffs-decision-making" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tradeoffs-decision-making">2. Tradeoffs &amp; Decision-Making</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>No perfect solutions</strong>: Everything has pros and cons; success lies in choosing the right tradeoff.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Red flags</strong>: If you find yourself thinking “but it’s so much money,” reassess your motives.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Fear of big goals</strong>: While aiming high is less crowded, it can also be used as an excuse if you fail.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="competition-high-performance" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="competition-high-performance">3. Competition &amp; High Performance</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Hidden costs</strong>: Emulating high performers may mean accepting hidden sacrifices.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Consistency</strong>: Deliberate, ongoing practice filters out those who can’t sustain effort.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Focus vs.&nbsp;Obsession</strong>: The lazy lose to the average, the average lose to the focused, the focused lose to the obsessed.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="adaptability-innovation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adaptability-innovation">4. Adaptability &amp; Innovation</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Pivot or perish</strong>: Like Western Digital clinging to telegrams post-telephone, ignoring new tech can be fatal.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Company reinvention</strong>: Nintendo, YouTube, and Slack all started with entirely different products.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="human-needs-motivations" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="human-needs-motivations">5. Human Needs &amp; Motivations</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Beyond basics</strong>: After food and shelter, people want affiliation, status, and freedom from fear.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Status &amp; affiliation</strong>: These drive many personal and social decisions, from kids to career choices.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="simplicity-execution" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="simplicity-execution">6. Simplicity &amp; Execution</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Complexity as an enemy</strong>: Simpler approaches often yield better execution (Tony Robbins).<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Stress from neglect</strong>: Stress arises from ignoring important tasks or problems.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="personal-growth-mindset" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="personal-growth-mindset">7. Personal Growth &amp; Mindset</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Meditation zones</strong>: Mindfulness, Support, Flow, and Awakening each expand consciousness in different ways.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Courage gap</strong>: For most smart people, the missing piece is the bravery to act.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Thinking in writing</strong>: Writing clarifies thoughts and fosters deeper understanding.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="entrepreneurship-career" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="entrepreneurship-career">8. Entrepreneurship &amp; Career</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Keys to success</strong>:
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Courage</strong> to start<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Perseverance</strong> to test multiple approaches<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Skills</strong> to build, sell, and harness luck<br>
</li>
</ol></li>
<li><strong>Building an audience</strong>: Focus on the right followers, share your niche expertise, and aim for ongoing improvement.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>If you don’t choose a goal</strong>: Society will assign you one you might not want.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="health-well-being" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-well-being">9. Health &amp; Well-Being</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Weight control</strong>: Balance palatability with low calorie density.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Dental health</strong>: Poor oral care can raise dementia risk by up to 30%.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Marriage vs.&nbsp;career</strong>: A great marriage and an average job can be happier than a great job but unhappy marriage.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="education-parenting" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="education-parenting">10. Education &amp; Parenting</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Raising a sovereign child</strong>: Freedom over control; allow exploration and independent thought.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Scaffolding</strong>: Provide temporary support or structure until a child (or learner) can handle it on their own.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Beware status games in youth</strong>: Sports can become more about prestige than personal growth.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="angel-investing-business-acumen" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="angel-investing-business-acumen">11. Angel Investing &amp; Business Acumen</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Founder first</strong>: Investors should look at who’s running the startup more than the idea itself.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Pratfall effect</strong>: Revealing small imperfections <strong>after</strong> showing competence makes you more relatable.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="societal-observations-history" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="societal-observations-history">12. Societal Observations &amp; History</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Slowing progress</strong>: Bigger scientific fields often have slower breakthroughs.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Policy &amp; power</strong>: Politicians can stifle innovation (e.g., Facebook’s Libra).<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Odd facts</strong>: 80% of US cash is in $100 bills; 70% of restaurant food is delivered.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="influence-conformity" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="influence-conformity">13. Influence &amp; Conformity</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Preference falsification</strong>: Publicly supporting what you don’t believe privately.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Conformity vs.&nbsp;prestige</strong>: We follow the crowd for safety or follow those with status to elevate ourselves.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="ai-the-future-of-work" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ai-the-future-of-work">14. AI &amp; the Future of Work</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Leadership vs.&nbsp;management</strong>: As AI handles tasks, leadership (direction, strategy) grows more important than micromanagement.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Using AI</strong>: Either harness AI to assist your projects or risk falling behind.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="overarching-wisdom" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="overarching-wisdom">15. Overarching Wisdom</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>“Enough” vs.&nbsp;“more”</strong>: Don’t let the pursuit of endless growth blind you to the beauty of having enough.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Fail fast, learn faster</strong>: The cost of being wrong is often lower than the cost of doing nothing.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Mind as friend</strong>: Wisdom comes from taming your own mind.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-01-january-learnings/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-02-01-january-learnings/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What Item Would You Bring to a Deserted Island?</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-31-knowledge/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>For the first time in history, the answer to the following questions of “what item would you bring to a deserted island” and “what item would you keep to start civilization over from scratch” is now the same thing. You would bring ChatGPT, or put more generally a large language model (llm) or generative AI model. At its core, these AI models condense the knowledge of the data it was trained on. It can acquire knowledge and know how to apply it, which is the definition of intelligence. This proves that the most important thing in our world is access to knowledge and how to use it, aka intelligence, and AI models are the best container for knowledge. Let’s dive deeper into why ChatGPT is the best item to bring to a deserted island. Before everyone gets their panties in a bunch about needing internet access for ChatGPT, let’s assume it’s an offline model running locally inside an indestructible cube that is powered by a hand crank and solar panels. Ok? Good. Let’s continue.</p>
<p>When you crash on the island, the AI would tell you what you need to do first to survive. Most likely how to build a shelter with the elements you have around you. Teach you how to get fresh water. Show you which mushrooms are poisonous and which make for a tasty treat. It could entertain you with stories. Even act as a friend for companionship in a lonely place. Having a physical tool like a hatchet would be nice, but it’s not going to help administer first aid to you when you accidentally cut yourself while chopping wood.</p>
<p>Imagine trying to bring other forms of knowledge to the island. Maybe a waterproof copy of a survival manual. That would definitely help you survive the first few nights and eventually thrive on the island. But only for your most basic needs. What if you found other people on the island? Maybe a potential partner you want to settle down with and start a family? The survival book is not going to help you deliver a child.</p>
<p>Instead of a survival book you could bring an entire encyclopedia. Either one of those old school physical books, or a print out of everything on Wikipedia. That could help you with a lot of things. But now your problem is knowing where to find the right knowledge to help you with new problems. Does that rash on your arm match with the description of a rare disease in the encyclopedia? Hard to say. You then find another tribe on the island that speaks a different language as you and they seem pretty pissed off. Scrolling through Wikipedia for 30 minutes can’t help you there. So it’s not enough to have the knowledge itself at hand, but easy ways to access exactly what you need, when you need it.</p>
<p>Easy access to knowledge used to be driven by search engines like Google and Bing. They could search through various information for you automatically. In a sense they condensed the entire internet into a text box to ask questions. But what came out on the other side are things that might be able to help, but not the exact knowledge you might need immediately or how to apply it to solve your problem. New AI services like ChatGPT can do just that. It knows most of what a search engine might know, but it can find the right answer immediately. It’s also able to create new information never thought possible, because it wasn’t in the original training data. Google search may not know what to do when a completely new event like a meteorite hits your island. But ChatGPT can reason and give you the knowledge and implementation to deal with the incident. It not only knows what, it also knows how. Knowledge is power. But being able to apply knowledge correctly, aka intelligence, is even more powerful.</p>
<p>The cost of intelligence with AI is quickly going to zero. What happens then? It feels like the two most important jobs going forward in an AI future is either building smarter AI models. Or finding the right data to feed them. By building smarter models you are improving the how (intelligence), and by getting better data you are improving the what (knowledge). The scary part is that AI models can now create their own synthetic training data, and techniques like reinforcement learning allow them to essential train themselves. So manual human intervention in these models might go away too. What’s left to do if the AI can train itself and get better every day?</p>
<p>The answer is to use the AI to make humans better. To increase their knowledge of the what and the how. Imagine a 30 year old accountant who has never camped outside in their life lands on the island with ChatGPT. They would most likely be able to get by with the help of the AI, but they would still struggle initially, maybe even perish from plain bad luck. Now replace that person with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bear_Grylls">Bear Grylles</a>, the famous British survival expert. I mean, the dudes name is literally “Bear”, how could he not survive in the wild? Combine him with ChatGPT and now he turns into a superhuman. He already knows how to survive, and paired with ChatGPT he can now build an island empire.</p>
<p>Having a smart AI is good, but having a smart AI combined with a smart human is even better. As these AI models get smarter, they should also enable humans to get smarter as well. If you want to start learning how to code today, you shouldn’t read a textbook on python. Instead have ChatGPT start teaching you. It’s a world class tutor available 24/7, tailored to your learning style, and is infinitely patient. It can write code for you, explain how it works, and then quiz you about it. <strong>Using AI to increase the collective knowledge and intelligence of every person in the world should be a top priority.</strong></p>
<p>So many problems in our world today can partly be due to a lack of education. When using a college degree as a proxy for education, the problems in our society stick out. People who don’t have a college degree have more problems.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://www.idra.org/resource-center/college-degrees-are-worth-it-people-with-bachelors-degrees-have-lower-poverty-rates/">Poverty</a>: In 2019 people with a college degree earned $25,000 more than someone with only a high school diploma.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.prisonpolicy.org/blog/2018/10/30/education-report/">Crime</a>: Less than 4% of formerly incarcerated people have a college degree.</li>
<li><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28756896/">Suicide</a>: Men without a college degree are twice as likely to die from suicide compared to a college graduate.</li>
</ol>
<p>Having a college degree is not a perfect measure of who has knowledge and who does not. But the above stats paint a bad picture for those without a degree. Soon everyone with an internet connection will have access to the best tutor in the world, essentially for free. AI tutors can teach billions of people at once. The only limiting factors will become tailoring the AI tutor to each persons wants and needs, and a person’s thirst for knowledge. There’s an old saying that goes: “The cure for boredom is curiosity. There is no cure for curiosity.” We can tailor the AI tutors to the learner, but creating the want inside of people to learn is the hard part. In a world of video games and TikTok, getting someone excited to learn about chemistry or to simply read a book will be a challenge.</p>
<p>This is where the multimodal nature of AI models can save the day. The AI can print out text, talk to you via voice, even create photos and videos. This unlocks limitless ways for an AI to teach you something. Someone may prefer a book like experience with an AI using chat, whereas another may learn best through a superhero movie that teaches you about greek mythology. Creating an AI tutor that a person can’t turn away from is one of the most important problems to work on. Imagine your 10 year old staying up all night because they don’t want to stop learning about the migratory patterns of birds, or how nuclear fusion works, instead of watching TikTok dance trends. This is a possible future. AI is up to the task.</p>
<p>AI models are not only positioned to make the world better, they are also well positioned to make humans better. Let’s go build one.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>AI</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <category>school</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-31-knowledge/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-31-knowledge/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploratory Data Analysis: External Regressors</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-24-ts-fundamentals-eda-xregs/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>This post is part of the <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-10-03-ts-fundamentals-eda/">exploratory data analysis chapter</a> within a larger learning series around time series forecasting fundamentals. <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-09-25-ts-fundamentals/">Check out the main learning path</a> to see other posts in the series.</em></p>
<p><em>The example monthly data used in this series <a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/posts/2024-10-02-ts-fundamentals-whats-a-time-series/example_ts_data.csv">can be found here.</a> You can also find the <a href="https://github.com/mftokic/mftokic.github.io/blob/main/notebooks/2025-01-24-ts-fundamentals-eda-xregs.ipynb">python code used in this post here.</a></em></p>
<section id="may-the-outside-forces-be-with-you" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="may-the-outside-forces-be-with-you">May The Outside Forces Be With You</h3>
<p>When creating a time series forecast, you really only need three columns. One to identify one time series from another, a timestamp (date) column, and your target variable. With these three things you can produce high quality forecasts. Unfortunately most time series do not live in a vacuum, and are subject to outside forces. These forces could be things like macroeconomic factors like inflation or consumer sentiment. The growing market share of your competitors. Or even when your product might go on sale. These are all external regressors (xregs), or outside data points that can be used to improve the predictive accuracy of our time series forecast.</p>
<p>External regressors come in many shapes and sizes. They are usually chosen based on the <a href="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-04-02-time-series-domain-expertise/">domain expertise</a> of whatever you’re trying to forecast. Outside of a hunch that they might work, how can we tell if they should be used in our time series forecast? Let’s walk through a few methods to measure the relationship between external regressors and our target variable.</p>
</section>
<section id="measuring-linear-relationships" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="measuring-linear-relationships">Measuring Linear Relationships</h3>
<p>The most straightforward approach is a simple correlation analysis. We take the external regressor time series, and calculate the correlation against our target variable time series. This gives us a value between -1 and 1. Having either a strong negative correlation or positive correlation are both helpful. Here are a few rules of thumb to measure strong correlations of external regressors based on the date grain of your data.</p>
<ul>
<li>Year/Quarter/Month: Absolute value correlation of 0.5 or higher.</li>
<li>Week/Day: Absolute value correlation of 0.2 or higher.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s important to note that those values are arbitrary. This isn’t a perfect threshold to use. So make sure you adjust that based on your own time series data. Let’s take a time series from our example dataset and calculate the correlation against a few external regressors.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Date</th>
<th>Country</th>
<th>Product</th>
<th>Revenue</th>
<th>xreg1</th>
<th>xreg2</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2019-01-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>12.37</td>
<td>27</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2019-02-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>15.73</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2019-03-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>39.68</td>
<td>67</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2019-04-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>60.17</td>
<td>95</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2019-05-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>72.84</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2019-06-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>53.31</td>
<td>21</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2019-07-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>9.65</td>
<td>31</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2019-08-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>12.20</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2019-09-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>10.04</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2019-10-01</td>
<td>United States</td>
<td>Cookies</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>19.62</td>
<td>88</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><img src="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-24-ts-fundamentals-eda-xregs/chart1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The first external regressor (xreg1) seems to have similar trend and seasonality patterns as our revenue target variable. The second external regressor (xregs2) on the other hand is all over the place. Here is the correlation with each xreg.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Variable 1</th>
<th>Variable 2</th>
<th>Correlation</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1</td>
<td>0.83</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2</td>
<td>0.05</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The table confirms our initial smell test after reading the line chart. Xreg1 has a strong correlation, and xreg2 does not. This tells us that xreg1 could be a good candidate to use as a feature in our ML forecast model. What if we don’t know what xreg1 values are going to be in the future? That’s where calculating correlation on lags becomes valuable. We can calculate lags for 1 month, 2 months, 3 months, and onward to see if lag values of our external regressors can also be used as features.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Variable 1</th>
<th>Variable 2</th>
<th>Correlation</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1</td>
<td>0.83</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2</td>
<td>0.05</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_1</td>
<td>0.64</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_2</td>
<td>0.24</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_3</td>
<td>-0.17</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_6</td>
<td>-0.07</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_9</td>
<td>-0.43</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_12</td>
<td>0.65</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_1</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_2</td>
<td>-0.11</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_3</td>
<td>-0.15</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_6</td>
<td>0.17</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_9</td>
<td>0.04</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_12</td>
<td>0.15</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>In addition to the original xreg1 (at lag 0), the 1 and 12 month lags also have a high correlation. A 12 month lag shows that there is strong seasonality in both our original time series and xreg1. This will be helpful once we start to train models.</p>
</section>
<section id="measuring-non-linear-relationships" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="measuring-non-linear-relationships">Measuring Non-Linear Relationships</h3>
<p>Traditional correlation is great and all, but falls short if there are non-linear relationships between the variables. In order to capture non-linear relationships, we have to bring in some heavy firepower. Using either of the below approaches.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Mutual Information (MI)
<ul>
<li>Overview:
<ul>
<li>Measures the shared information between two variables (or time series).</li>
<li>Captures linear and non-linear dependencies.</li>
<li>Based on information theory: higher MI indicates more shared patterns or dependencies.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Key Points:
<ul>
<li>Values are always non-negative.</li>
<li>MI = 0: No dependence (variables are independent).</li>
<li>Higher MI: Greater dependency or shared information.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Interpretation:
<ul>
<li>MI doesn’t distinguish between positive or negative relationships (unlike correlation).</li>
<li>It only reflects the strength of dependency, not its direction or type.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Distance Correlation (dCor)
<ul>
<li>Overview:
<ul>
<li>Measures the dependence between two variables by analyzing distances between all pairwise points.</li>
<li>Captures both linear and non-linear relationships.</li>
<li>Unlike MI, dCor is normalized to a specific range.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Key Points:
<ul>
<li>Values range from 0 to 1.</li>
<li>dCor = 0: Variables are independent.</li>
<li>dCor = 1: Perfect dependence (linear or non-linear).</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Interpretation:
<ul>
<li>A value closer to 0: Weak or no dependency.</li>
<li>A value closer to 1: Strong dependency.</li>
<li>It is symmetric and doesn’t distinguish between causation or directionality.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>Distance correlation is easier to understand and compare scores across different data sets, but mutual information can understand more complex non-linear relationships. So either can be helpful. Dealers choice on what you want to use. Let’s calculate a mutual information score on our external regressors and their lags.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Variable 1</th>
<th>Variable 2</th>
<th>Mutual Information</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1</td>
<td>0.52</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_1</td>
<td>0.18</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_2</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_3</td>
<td>0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_6</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_9</td>
<td>0.04</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg1_lag_12</td>
<td>0.05</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_1</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_2</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_3</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_6</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_9</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>xreg2_lag_12</td>
<td>0.00</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Similar to regular correlation, xreg1 shows a strong relationship with revenue. But for MI it only has a relationship with lag 0 and lag 1. All other values are either very small or zero, meaning there is not strong relationship. This differs from the original correlation values. Usually it’s a good idea to use a few of these methods together. If external regressors are flagged as important in more than one of these approaches, then it’s safe to say they have some predictive power for our target variable. So for our data we can keep xreg1 to use in our model and drop xreg2 since it’s mostly noise with no signal.</p>
</section>
<section id="dealing-with-binary-regressors" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dealing-with-binary-regressors">Dealing With Binary Regressors</h3>
<p>There’s one final type of analysis we are missing. Sometimes adding simple binary variables as external regressors can result in major accuracy improvements. These are 1 or 0 values that can represent a certain event or action happening. For example you might have new product launches in random months throughout the year. These can be represented with a 1 when there is a product launch, and a 0 when there is not. Without this binary data, a model may pick up on trends and patterns that may not repeat in the future. Your business might thrive during the months leading up to the US presidential election, but that only comes around every four years. So giving the model context of those events is important.</p>
<p>An interesting binary regressor in recent years has been a COVID-19 flag. This shows when COVID was impacting the world the most. When looking at the chart of our time series above, we can see a large dip in 2020. So it looks like COVID has a potential effect. Let’s create a COVID flag with a value of 1 for every month in 2020 and a value of 0 for all other months. We will also create a second flag that contains random 1 and 0 values to see if we can determine which regressor is important to our specific time series.</p>
<p>We can calculate a mutual information score for each one.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Variable 1</th>
<th>Variable 2</th>
<th>Mutual Information</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>COVID Flag</td>
<td>0.0033</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Revenue</td>
<td>Random Flag</td>
<td>0.0000</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>While the mutual information score for COVID is small, it’s still above zero. Which proves that this COVID flag may help improve our models predictive performance.</p>
<p>Finally there are other ways to figure out the importance of external regressors, but most of them deal with training actual models. I’ll wait on discussing those techniques until we build up some more foundational knowledge and eventually get to the sections on models themselves. Stay tuned.</p>
</section>
<section id="reversal" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reversal">Reversal</h3>
<p>When working with external regressors, it’s important to approach correlations and relationships critically. A strong correlation might suggest a connection, but it does not prove causation. This distinction is crucial, as relying on variables without clear logical links to your target can mislead your analysis and undermine your forecast.</p>
<p>Another issue to watch for is multicollinearity. This happens when external regressors are highly correlated with one another. Models can struggle to differentiate the effects of variables that overlap significantly, leading to instability in coefficient estimates and diminished interpretability. To mitigate this, examine the correlations among your regressors before including them. If two variables are redundant, consider removing or transforming one to reduce redundancy.</p>
<p>Ultimately, external regressors should be chosen based on both statistical evidence and domain knowledge. They should have a clear, interpretable relationship with the target variable. Without this foundation, even the most promising-looking variables can introduce unnecessary complexity and noise.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>
<p>Incorporating external regressors into your time series analysis can significantly enhance the accuracy and robustness of your forecasts when done carefully. The methods discussed, including correlation analysis and mutual information, are essential tools for evaluating potential regressors. However, they should always be applied alongside sound reasoning and a thorough understanding of the business.</p>
<p>It’s also worth noting that the relationship between external regressors and your target may not always be straightforward. Non-linear relationships, lags, and interactions with other variables often require additional exploration to capture their full impact. This underscores the importance of iterative experimentation and validation throughout the forecasting process.</p>
<p>As you refine your approach, prioritize quality over quantity. A well-selected set of regressors tailored to the problem at hand will yield better results than an overly broad or poorly vetted selection. The goal is not just to improve the model’s performance but to ensure that the improvements are grounded in meaningful insights.</p>
<p>In time series forecasting, the integration of external regressors bridges the gap between historical patterns and the broader forces shaping the future. By combining statistical rigor with contextual understanding, you can build models that not only predict but also provide actionable insights into the dynamics of your business.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>machine-learning</category>
  <category>time-series</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-24-ts-fundamentals-eda-xregs/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-24-ts-fundamentals-eda-xregs/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>80/20 SaaS: Why AI-Driven Customization Is the Future</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-02-80-20-saas/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="introduction-will-ai-kill-saas" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction-will-ai-kill-saas">Introduction: Will AI Kill SaaS?</h2>
<p>Artificial intelligence (AI) has advanced to a point where one or two developers, working with AI-generated code, can build functional software in a matter of weeks. That prospect has led some to conclude that it spells the end of Software-as-a-Service (SaaS). After all, why rent a platform if you can build a decent alternative in-house—cheaply and on-demand?</p>
<p>However, I believe there’s a more practical way forward. Instead of entirely replacing SaaS with AI-built tools, <strong>SaaS providers should deliver 80% of the core features</strong> and allow customers to <strong>customize the remaining 20%</strong> via AI. This approach maintains the convenience of off-the-shelf software while offering personalized functionality.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-some-believe-ai-will-kill-saas" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-some-believe-ai-will-kill-saas">Why Some Believe AI Will Kill SaaS</h2>
<p>The primary argument for “AI replacing SaaS” goes like this:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lower Development Costs:</strong> With AI writing boilerplate code, you need fewer developers.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Faster Time to Market:</strong> AI can generate basic functionality quickly.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Tailored Features:</strong> Instead of dealing with generic solutions, an in-house AI tool can theoretically be customized to meet specific business needs.</li>
</ul>
<p>On paper, this sounds like a dream come true for businesses. But the reality is more complicated. Building robust, production-grade software, from scratch, requires <strong>significant resources</strong>, including project management, maintenance, and ongoing support. Most companies aren’t equipped (or willing) to handle the long-term overhead that comes with building and hosting complex systems themselves.</p>
</section>
<section id="embracing-the-8020-model" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="embracing-the-8020-model">Embracing the 80/20 Model</h2>
<p>Rather than viewing AI and SaaS as competing forces, I propose a hybrid model. The <strong>80/20 approach</strong> involves:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Core Product (80%)</strong>
<ul>
<li>SaaS providers develop and maintain a set of core features that almost every customer needs. Think user authentication, data storage, basic dashboards, etc. This allows them to keep their development teams lean and focus on rock-solid functionality.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Customer Customization (20%)</strong>
<ul>
<li>Customers then use AI (offered as part of the SaaS platform) to build out the features that are specific to their individual business needs. This might involve specialized workflows, custom dashboards, or niche integrations.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>By dividing responsibilities this way, the SaaS provider avoids bloating its product with endless feature requests. Customers, in turn, get <strong>exactly what they want</strong> without having to pay for an army of developers.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-crm-example" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-crm-example">A CRM Example</h2>
<p>Consider Customer Relationship Management (CRM) software. Giants like Salesforce and Microsoft Dynamics offer thousands of features, but not every company needs each one. Despite the vast customization options, many organizations still find themselves <strong>adapting to the CRM</strong>, not the other way around.</p>
<p>What if a startup CRM provider offers a bare-bones product that covers 80% of what most sales teams require. Things like contact management, basic analytics, and lead tracking, and then <strong>invites customers to build the rest</strong> with AI-driven tools? For instance:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>A sales manager wants automated follow-up emails that adapt to different time zones.<br>
</li>
<li>She types her request into the built-in AI feature: “Generate customized follow-up emails that go out at optimal local times for each lead.”<br>
</li>
<li>The AI creates this functionality on the fly, integrating it seamlessly into the CRM interface.</li>
</ol>
<p>No waiting for lengthy releases, no large development staff. Just a straightforward 80% solution with a customizable 20%.</p>
</section>
<section id="benefits-for-both-sides" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="benefits-for-both-sides">Benefits for Both Sides</h2>
<section id="for-saas-providers" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="for-saas-providers">For SaaS Providers</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lean Development Team:</strong> Focus on a stable core, lowering overhead.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Reduced Feature Creep:</strong> No more chasing every edge case. Let AI and customers handle that final 20%.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>New Revenue Streams:</strong> Providers can charge a flat monthly fee for the core product plus incremental fees for AI-built custom features.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="for-customers" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="for-customers">For Customers</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Faster Customization:</strong> No waiting for your feature request to pass through the SaaS provider’s roadmap.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Lower Costs:</strong> Pay for essential features plus only the custom pieces you really need.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Reduced Risk:</strong> Save time and money by not building entire applications from scratch.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="potential-challenges" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="potential-challenges">Potential Challenges</h2>
<p>Of course, the 80/20 model comes with its own complexities:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Maintenance of Custom Features</strong>
<ul>
<li>AI-generated features could break when the core platform updates. SaaS providers will need robust versioning and testing to ensure stability.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Security &amp; Compliance</strong>
<ul>
<li>As customers add custom modules, the platform must ensure data remains secure and compliant with regulations like GDPR.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Quality Control</strong>
<ul>
<li>Who is responsible when an AI-built feature malfunctions? Customers will demand that providers offer at least minimal support for AI-generated functionality.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Training Data &amp; Privacy</strong>
<ul>
<li>AI systems rely on data to learn. Providers must have clear policies on how user data is used to train and improve models.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="startups-vs.-giants" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="startups-vs.-giants">Startups vs.&nbsp;Giants</h2>
<p>This business model has the potential to disrupt established SaaS giants. Companies like Salesforce and Microsoft <strong>already offer</strong> highly customizable platforms, but they are weighed down by <strong>thousands of existing features</strong>. Re-engineering their entire codebase to an AI-first platform would be like trying to rebuild an airplane in mid-flight.</p>
<p>Enter the <strong>new startups</strong>:<br>
- <strong>Clean Slate:</strong> They can design products from the ground up with an 80/20 approach.<br>
- <strong>Modern Architectures:</strong> They can embed AI customization layers from day one, rather than retrofitting existing systems.<br>
- <strong>Agile Mindset:</strong> Less legacy overhead means they can pivot faster to market demands.</p>
<p>The incumbents won’t disappear overnight, but they may lose out on smaller, more agile customers who prefer a streamlined, customizable experience.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion-thriving-in-an-ai-future" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion-thriving-in-an-ai-future">Conclusion: Thriving in an AI Future</h2>
<p>AI may not spell the end of SaaS, but it <strong>will</strong> transform it. By offloading the final 20% of custom features to AI, SaaS providers can remain lean, stay focused on a reliable core, and still give customers the freedom to adapt software to their unique processes.</p>
<section id="final-thought" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thought">Final Thought</h3>
<p>Are you ready to adapt? If you’re a <strong>SaaS provider</strong>, consider slimming your product down to the essential core and building out an AI-driven customization layer. If you’re a <strong>customer</strong>, think about the time and money you could save by adopting an 80/20 approach, rather than building or buying bloated software.</p>
<p>The future of SaaS will hinge on who best embraces this new reality. Those who see AI not as a rival to existing software, but as an ally in creating truly personal, on-demand solutions.</p>
<p><strong>Which side of the 80/20 equation is your business on?</strong></p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>AI</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-02-80-20-saas/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-02-80-20-saas/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>December Learnings</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-01-december-learnings/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I love reading books, watching YouTube videos, listening to podcasts, you name it. Anything learning related is my jam. But I recently realized that if I don’t take notes on what I’m learning, I will probably forget everything. Now when I hear something interesting, I write it down in an Apple note for that month. Below are some of the learnings I jotted down in December, summarized by ChatGPT. I hope you find them as interesting as I did.</p>
<section id="business-entrepreneurship" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="business-entrepreneurship">1. Business &amp; Entrepreneurship</h3>
<section id="passive-income-productized-services" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="passive-income-productized-services">Passive Income &amp; Productized Services</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Best passive income model:</strong> Offer a service that helps companies make more money.
<ul>
<li>Ideally, “productize” your service so it’s standardized, repeatable, and less reliant on your day-to-day involvement.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="starting-a-company-from-scratch" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="starting-a-company-from-scratch">Starting a Company From Scratch</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Validate demand first:</strong> Ask people if they want what you’re selling; presell if possible.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Find a repeatable way to get customers</strong> (test channels early).<br>
</li>
<li>Build only after talking to potential customers; keep it simple until proven.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Know if you’re building to sell or building to run:</strong>
<ul>
<li>LLC if you want to pay yourself along the way.<br>
</li>
<li>C Corp if you want to sell eventually (consider QSBS after five years).</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="monetization-branding" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monetization-branding">Monetization &amp; Branding</h4>
<ul>
<li>Even in a commodity space, <strong>branding can create a unique edge</strong> (e.g., Liquid Death water).<br>
</li>
<li>“Startups fail, founders don’t”: Persistence leads to eventual success if you keep learning.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="key-mindsets" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-mindsets">Key Mindsets</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>“The fundamental algorithm of life is to repeat what works.”</strong><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Pair your primary metric with a “check” metric</strong> (e.g., revenue + profit margin) to avoid over-optimizing in one direction.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="management-leadership" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="management-leadership">2. Management &amp; Leadership</h3>
<section id="types-of-delegation" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="types-of-delegation">Types of Delegation</h4>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Tell them what to do.</strong><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Allow them to make decisions.</strong>
<ul>
<li>Aim for #2, but you might start with #1 until trust and competence are established.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="avoid-monkeys-on-your-back" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="avoid-monkeys-on-your-back">Avoid “Monkeys on Your Back”</h4>
<ul>
<li>When employees bring a problem, coach them to leave with their own solution.<br>
</li>
<li>Ask guiding questions (“Are you sure we need to do anything right now?”) instead of providing answers.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="one-metric-management-peter-thiels-approach" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="one-metric-management-peter-thiels-approach">One Metric Management (Peter Thiel’s Approach)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Assign each employee exactly <strong>one</strong> main metric or goal.<br>
</li>
<li>That’s all you focus on in 1:1s.<br>
</li>
<li>They own the outputs and figure out the inputs themselves.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="firing-role-clarification" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="firing-role-clarification">Firing &amp; Role Clarification</h4>
<ul>
<li>The moment you think “this might be a firing situation,” have a clarifying conversation about expectations.<br>
</li>
<li>Firing ultimately benefits both parties if the role isn’t a fit.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="hiring-strategy-for-new-business" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hiring-strategy-for-new-business">Hiring Strategy for New Business</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>First hire:</strong> Virtual assistant to free up time (low-risk, low-cost).<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Second hire:</strong> Sales/marketing to boost cash flow, then operations.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Hiring internationally</strong> can be a “no-brainer” for cost savings (e.g., via Shepherd).</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="who-not-how" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="who-not-how">Who, Not How</h4>
<ul>
<li>When a problem arises, ask <strong>“Who can solve this for me?”</strong> instead of <strong>“How will I solve it?”</strong><br>
</li>
<li>This mindset shift helps you move from owning a ‘job’ to owning a ‘business.’</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="productivity-personal-growth" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="productivity-personal-growth">3. Productivity &amp; Personal Growth</h3>
<section id="daily-vitamins-for-health" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="daily-vitamins-for-health">Daily “Vitamins” for Health</h4>
<ul>
<li>Walks/Nature<br>
</li>
<li>45 minutes of exercise<br>
</li>
<li>Reading, YouTube (educational), Writing, Building<br>
</li>
<li>1:1 time with family/friends<br>
</li>
<li>150 grams of protein</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="preventing-burnout" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="preventing-burnout">Preventing Burnout</h4>
<ul>
<li>Ask: <strong>“Is this important? Will it make a difference?”</strong> Only focus on the important.<br>
</li>
<li>Our <strong>state determines our story</strong>—manage your energy and emotions.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="habits-dopamine" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="habits-dopamine">Habits &amp; Dopamine</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Dopamine gained without effort</strong> (e.g., instant gratification) can be dangerous.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Good results</strong> today come from consistent, small choices made previously.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="time-freedom-over-money" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="time-freedom-over-money">Time Freedom Over Money</h4>
<ul>
<li>Many people chase money for freedom but ironically lose freedom by obsessing over it.<br>
</li>
<li>Consider designing a life you enjoy <strong>now</strong>, rather than waiting for a financial milestone.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="health-longevity" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-longevity">4. Health &amp; Longevity</h3>
<section id="key-factors" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-factors">Key Factors</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Excess fat (adipose tissue)</strong> has the largest negative impact.<br>
</li>
<li>Maintain a healthy weight and an 80–90% healthy diet for most of the benefits.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="other-longevity-insights" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="other-longevity-insights">Other Longevity Insights</h4>
<ul>
<li>Developing countries often have lower life spans due to poor indoor air quality.<br>
</li>
<li>As you age, <strong>vacations should be longer</strong> because your body needs more time to relax.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Creativity</strong> correlates with longevity.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="environmental-lifestyle-factors" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="environmental-lifestyle-factors">Environmental &amp; Lifestyle Factors</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Blue light</strong> and <strong>flickering LEDs</strong> can contribute to stress or weight gain.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Posture</strong> affects how much you believe your own thoughts—mind your physical stance.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="mindset-philosophy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mindset-philosophy">5. Mindset &amp; Philosophy</h3>
<section id="q-filters-test-jon-acuff" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="q-filters-test-jon-acuff">3Q Filters Test (Jon Acuff)</h4>
<ol type="1">
<li>Is it <strong>true</strong>?<br>
</li>
<li>Is it <strong>helpful</strong>?<br>
</li>
<li>Is it <strong>kind</strong>?</li>
</ol>
<p>If your thoughts are not one of these, discard it immediately.</p>
</section>
<section id="socratic-method-curiosity" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="socratic-method-curiosity">Socratic Method &amp; Curiosity</h4>
<ul>
<li>Instead of disagreeing, ask questions to uncover someone’s reasoning.<br>
</li>
<li>Serve as a “midwife” to help them birth new ideas rather than forcing your own.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="quotes-wisdom" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="quotes-wisdom">Quotes &amp; Wisdom</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>“Content is about emotion, not information.”</strong> —Shaan Puri<br>
</li>
<li><strong>“Slow is smooth, smooth is fast.”</strong><br>
</li>
<li><strong>“No one is wrong on purpose.”</strong> —Socrates<br>
</li>
<li><strong>“Make a sense of humor your default emotion.”</strong> —Matthew McConaughey<br>
</li>
<li><strong>“If you want to win, only run races where winning is up to you.”</strong> —Epictetus</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="identity-diversification" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="identity-diversification">Identity Diversification</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Don’t let your job (or parenthood) be your sole identity.</strong><br>
</li>
<li>Spread your sense of self across multiple areas for resilience.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="live-verb-focused-not-noun-focused" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="live-verb-focused-not-noun-focused">Live Verb-Focused, Not Noun-Focused</h4>
<ul>
<li>Focus on what you <strong>do</strong>, not the title you hold.<br>
</li>
<li>Prioritize experiences and meaningful actions over static labels.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="relationships-social-insights" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="relationships-social-insights">6. Relationships &amp; Social Insights</h3>
<section id="delegation-autonomy" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="delegation-autonomy">Delegation &amp; Autonomy</h4>
<ul>
<li>Not every employee wants total autonomy; many prefer structure and a clear path to win.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="friendships-connections" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friendships-connections">Friendships &amp; Connections</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>“What is a friend? A single soul dwelling in two bodies.”</strong> —Aristotle<br>
</li>
<li>~200 hours of shared experience can turn an acquaintance into a close friend.<br>
</li>
<li>25% of adults are estranged from a parent; relationships can be complex, so invest in those that matter.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="family-societal-trends" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="family-societal-trends">Family &amp; Societal Trends</h4>
<ul>
<li>People have fewer kids because <strong>expectations</strong> (and costs) for each child have gone up dramatically.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="handling-lows-in-relationships" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="handling-lows-in-relationships">Handling Lows in Relationships</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>“It’s the lows, not the highs, that make or break a relationship.”</strong><br>
</li>
<li>Approach conflicts with empathy, short bursts of feedback, and open communication.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="planning-year-end-reflection" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="planning-year-end-reflection">7. Planning &amp; Year-End Reflection</h3>
<section id="close-out-the-year" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="close-out-the-year">Close Out the Year</h4>
<ul>
<li>Clear old emails, clothes, subscriptions; do a full evaluation.<br>
</li>
<li>Implement a consistent “planning system” to incorporate mini-adventures regularly.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="adding-one-new-winning-habit-per-quarter" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adding-one-new-winning-habit-per-quarter">Adding One New Winning Habit per Quarter</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Incremental habit-building:</strong> small, sustainable changes that compound over time.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="misogi-year-defining-challenge" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="misogi-year-defining-challenge">Misogi (Year-Defining Challenge)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Each year, take on one big challenge or adventure.<br>
</li>
<li>Meanwhile, schedule smaller weekly “mini-adventures” to stay engaged and curious.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="common-threads" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="common-threads">Common Threads</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Empowerment Through Delegation &amp; Systems</strong>
<ul>
<li>From “One Metric Management” to “Who Not How,” there’s a recurring emphasis on freeing yourself from minutiae so you can focus on strategic, high-impact work.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Validation &amp; Focus in Business</strong>
<ul>
<li>Your notes repeatedly stress testing ideas early (e.g., presales), focusing on the one crucial metric or channel, and doubling down on what works.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Healthy Mind &amp; Body for Sustainable Success</strong>
<ul>
<li>Longevity strategies, stress management, and daily rituals (walks, exercise, reading) show a consistent theme of taking care of yourself to thrive over the long term.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Mindset Shifts &amp; Philosophical Anchors</strong>
<ul>
<li>Using the 3Q filter, the Socratic method, and quotes that highlight freedom, creativity, and identity diversification. Emphasizing how perspective, curiosity, and humor make life richer.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Importance of Connection &amp; Relationships</strong>
<ul>
<li>Whether it’s rotating leadership roles, maintaining close friendships, or supporting employees appropriately, relationships and the way you interact with people matter.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Continuous Reinvention &amp; Reflection</strong>
<ul>
<li>The idea of year-end reviews, building new habits quarterly, and tackling “misogi”-level goals underscores the desire for ongoing personal evolution and adaptability.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>learning</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-01-december-learnings/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2025-01-01-december-learnings/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Who Ya Gonna Call? ChatGPT!</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-12-19-who-ya-gonna-call/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>OpenAI has gotten into the holiday spirit by launching <a href="https://openai.com/12-days/">12 Days of OpenAI</a>. Each day at 10am PST they release a new product or feature to the world. We are currently on day 11 of their 12 day ship’mas extravaganza. Previous days have seen massive product launches of their new Sora video model and ChatGPT Search. The most exciting one of them all though has been the product they launched yesterday on day 10, something called 1-800-chatgpt.</p>
<p>You can now, toll free, call ChatGPT on any phone in the United States. For people outside of the US you can talk to it via WhatsApp. How cool is that! No account or credit card required. Just a friend you can phone 24/7 for whatever you need. This may seem like a small gimmicky feature but it’s actually one of their most profound launches to date, because now everyone has easy access to AI.</p>
<p>Nothing is truly mainstream until our parents, and to an extent our grandparents, start using the technology. My grandpa lives on a small farm in Kansas. He has no WiFi at his house, and most days he keeps his cell phone turned off and in a drawer. He does use his landline phone every day though. With this latest launch he can now talk to the most powerful language model in the world, using only his voice. No set up necessary, just call and chat. AI has jumped the walled garden of the internet and is getting embedded into more aspects of our lives. Now it can live as a contact in our phones. The barrier to entry on AI is getting closer to zero.</p>
<p>In addition to having the technically challenged use AI, there are countless other use cases of the new toll free AI number.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Anywhere there is poor cell service. Stranded in the middle of Montana with a flat tire? The ChatGPT app may not work but you might be able to make a phone call. Now the AI can walk you through step by step how to change that flat tire, all for free.</li>
<li>Find yourself in jail for a crime you were wrongly convicted for? The AI can be your one phone call, and might give you better advice than a paid lawyer.</li>
<li>Are you one question away from untold riches on “Who wants to be a millionaire?” Phone your AI friend and have them provide an immediate answer to win the cash prize.</li>
</ol>
<p>The power of AI is now available to everyone. No one knows what will happen when every human has equal access to limitless intelligence. Now we are one step closer. If you’ve never tried out ChatGPT before, get out your phone and make the call!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>AI</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-12-19-who-ya-gonna-call/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-12-19-who-ya-gonna-call/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>ChatGPT Pro is Cheap</title>
  <dc:creator>Mike Tokic</dc:creator>
  <link>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-12-06-chatgpt-pro-is-cheap/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The latest offering from OpenAI costs $200 a month, and it’s actually a steal. It’s called <a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-chatgpt-pro/">ChatGPT Pro</a> and it’s 10x more expensive than their existing paid product called ChatGPT Plus. That sounds like a steep price tag but if you write code or do any complex reasoning for a living it could well be worth it.</p>
<p>Let’s break down the math. The average software engineer in the United States <a href="https://www.indeed.com/career/software-engineer/salaries">get’s paid $105,000 a year</a>. In Seattle and SF that can be 2-3x higher. But let’s just use the average. The new ChatGPT Pro subscription costs around 2% of their annual salary. To be worth it the product needs to give them back the same amount in productivity.</p>
<ul>
<li>$105,000 salary</li>
<li>250 days worked a year (50 weeks of 5 days, 2 weeks for vacation)</li>
<li>$420 daily salary (105000/250)</li>
</ul>
<p>If a dev makes $420 a day writing code, then paying $2,400 a year for ChatGPT Pro equals out to just under 6 days of their salary. The new models offered in ChatGPT Pro are the best in the world at coding. So it’s safe to say using them will make a developer more productive. If using the service saves you one hour a week in time spent coding then it will have already paid for itself.</p>
<ul>
<li>200x12 = $2,400</li>
<li>2,400/420 = 5.7 days</li>
<li>5.7x8 = 46 hours</li>
</ul>
<p>So by using the service you are technically getting 6 more hours of yearly productivity for free, which is about $315. Using the new service is actually putting more money in your pocket.</p>
<p>If you think paying buku bucks for services like this is stupid, well you are just not using them correctly. AI will become the most powerful form of leverage in the world, so not using it to its max today will only hurt you tomorrow. OpenAI said they will also be rolling out more features to the pro service going forward. This could include access to the next generation of models like GPT5 and access to their upcoming agents capabilities. Once these come out you will gladly fork over thousands a month for them, because they will allow you to get 2-3x more done. So paying $200 a month now might just be a steal.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>AI</category>
  <category>work</category>
  <guid>https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-12-06-chatgpt-pro-is-cheap/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://mftokic.github.io/posts/2024-12-06-chatgpt-pro-is-cheap/image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
